<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The history of His sacred Majesty Charles the II, King of England, Scotland, France &amp; Ireland, defender of the faith &amp;c. begun from the murder of his royall father of happy memory &amp; continued to this present year, 1660 / by a person of quality.</title>
            <author>Dauncey, John, fl. 1663.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 247 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 112 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B21038</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D292</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11195057</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11195057</idno>
            <idno type="VID">204891</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B21038)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 204891)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1439:29)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The history of His sacred Majesty Charles the II, King of England, Scotland, France &amp; Ireland, defender of the faith &amp;c. begun from the murder of his royall father of happy memory &amp; continued to this present year, 1660 / by a person of quality.</title>
                  <author>Dauncey, John, fl. 1663.</author>
                  <author>Davies, James.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 191, [18] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Reprinted by William Smith,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Cork :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing and NUC pre-1956 imprints to John Dauncey.</note>
                  <note>Sometimes attributed to James Davies--NUC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Stuarts, 1603-1714.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:204891:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:204891:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE HISTORY OF His SaCRed Majeſty CHARLES the II. KING of <hi>England, Scotland, France,</hi> &amp; <hi>Ireland,</hi> Defender of the Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Begun from the Murder of his Royall Father of Happy Memory, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued to this preſent year, 1660.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a Perſon of Quality.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bona agere &amp; mala pati Regium eſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>royal coat of arms or blazon</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>CORK,</hi> Reprinted by <hi>William Smith, Anno Dom:</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:204891:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:204891:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable <hi>HENRY</hi> Lord Marqueſs of DORCHESTER, Earl of <hi>Kingſton,</hi> Viſcount <hi>Newark,</hi> Lord <hi>Pierrepoint</hi> and <hi>Manvers,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was not upon long Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but eaſie reſolutions, that I pitched upon your Lordſhip, &amp; determined to preſume upon your patronage of this ſmall review of the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his SACRED MJESTY,) whoſe hard fortunes may now demand a Subjects protection ſince I could no where elſe find a perſon who bears ſo great a name of true Honour and Generoſity, nor one whoſe aſſured loyalty will make him leſſe aſhamed or afraid to owne his Prince.</p>
            <p>And indeed (my Lord) when I looked
<pb facs="tcp:204891:3"/>upon theſe Nations, once I may ſay almoſt peopled with Nobles, and now in a great meaſure deprived both of her Nobility and Gentry, 'twas eaſie for me to find out the Prime of thoſe remaining, which a ſmall ſearch told me was your Lordſhip; who, though you have been no whit behind the foremoſt in Loyalty, yet God hath been pleaſed to make others drinke deeper in the Cup of affliction then your ſelfe.</p>
            <p>But all thoſe miſeries which either your Lordſhip or other loyal perſons have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, cannot come in competition with thoſe undergon by his SACRED MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>JESTY, who hath drunk up the very dregs of the Cup, and ſuffered more then can be well ſpoken; yet all with ſo incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable a patience as worthily deſerves our wonder.</p>
            <p>My Lord, you are amongſt the Prime of the Nobility, which God hath yet been pleaſed to ſpare this miſerable Nation; &amp; as you are ſo, I could not think any perſon fitter for the patronage of this ſmall piece; ſince both your loyalty may make you wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,
<pb facs="tcp:204891:3"/>and your power able to protect it.</p>
            <p>If I have ſoar'd too high either in the ſubject or dedication, I ſhall humbly crave your Lordſhips pardon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and anſwer to the firſt? That I was willing to vindicate my Sovereign (as far as in me lay) from thoſe many reproaches and calumnies caſt upon him by his back-biting enemies by giving the beſt account (that either my own knowledge or the ſureſt intelligence I could get might enable, me to) of all his actions that he might appear the contrary of what he is repreſented, &amp; dirt be caſt in the faces of his Accuſers. To the ſecond, I wholly caſt my ſelfe on your Lordſhip, either to pardon or condemn.</p>
            <p>But if my Love to his Majeſtie may in the judgements of ſome have ſtrained my pen too much in his favour, I deſire it may be imputed not to my intent, but paſſion; for the unworthy ſufferings of ſo worthy a Prince would irritate any loyall Subject.</p>
            <p>My Lord, whilſt yotr Lordſhip ſhall be gratiouſly pleaſed to patronize this ſmall worke, that GOD would be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb facs="tcp:204891:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>to reſtore his Majeſty to be Patron of his Kingdoms and people, and bleſſe your Lordſhip with all imaginary bleſſings; ſhall be the daily prayers of,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt humble Servant, <hi>I. D.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:204891:4"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable, Major General <hi>Richard Brown,</hi> Colonel of the Regiment of horſe of the City of-<hi>London:</hi> Alderman <hi>John Robinſon,</hi> Colonel of the <hi>Green</hi> Regiment of the Cities Trained Bands: Ald. <hi>Anthony Bateman</hi> Col. of the <hi>Red.</hi> Ald. <hi>Will. Wale</hi> Col. of the <hi>White: William Vincent</hi> Col. of the <hi>Blew: Thomas Bludworth</hi> Col. of the <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range,</hi> and <hi>Lawrance Bromfield</hi> Col. of the <hi>Yellow.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Alice and error are the Epide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical diſeaſes of our time and land: ſo that whoever as a friend to his Country, ſhall preſume to diſcover any thing of a ſpirit of Love or truth, is likely to exaſperate not a few. That, I truſt, both the Author and my ſelfe the Stationer, have endeavoured to do, and
<pb facs="tcp:204891:5"/>therefore muſt expect to meet with the hard cenſures and Calumnies of many, yea even of ſuch, of whom we have no worſe thoughts, then that they ſuffer themſelves to be abuſed with popular miſtakes, and unneceſſary jealouſies concerning that moſt Chriſtian and Illuſtrious, (though now clouded) Prince, the ſubject of the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Book. Whoſe eares according to the <hi>Epheſians</hi> Hieroglyphick of Calumny) have been opened too wide to the malevolent aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertions of ignorant and illintereſted per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and are therefore prejudiced againſt every relation that may repreſent him to the World as lovely and deſirable. We know <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> had the unhappy ſate to be rendred odious to the people by <hi>Ariſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,</hi> gallant perſons both, but the latter un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a miſtake. Theſe we pity rather then be angry at them, and deſire to cure them of their beloved diſtemper by preſenting them with this ſuccinct &amp; faithfull Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. But yet that I may not be altogether unprovided of a ſhelter, if the ſtorm of their zealous frenzie ſhould chance to fall
<pb facs="tcp:204891:5"/>upon me (beſides a recourſe to my own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity, which <hi>Ianus</hi>-like will make me <hi>Tanto frontoſior, quanto innocentior</hi>) I humbly crave a room under the ſhadow of your wings, where I queſtion not but to lye ſafe. Your honours have taken a charge upon you, which obliges you to maintain the publick and common good intereſt of this Land and City, where
<q>
                  <l>— Res eſt publica Caeſar,</l>
                  <l>Et de communi pars quoque noſtra bono eſt.</l>
               </q> 
            </p>
            <p>Therefore to patronize the recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of his virtues for imitation, and of his ſufferings for commiſeration, cannot be unworthy your honours, which is the humble deſire of,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Humble and Obedient Servant <hi>JAMES DAVIES.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:204891:6"/>
            <head>To all loyal Englishmen. <hi>Gentlemen and fellow-Subjects.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Here preſent you an Hiſtory which though now you may, confident I am you very lately could not in reaſon expect; ſuch was the perverſneſſe and crookedneſs of theſe times, that no loyal ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject might without danger attempt to write, nay hardly to ſpeak the truth of his Soveraign: for a ſort of men there were, who having by vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence uſurped his Dominions, though that they had no ſurer ground to maintain their unjuſt poſſeſſion, then by ſcandalizing his moſt SA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CRED MAIESTY and deceiving of his Subjects, many of whom had not but by ſuch deceites converted their loyalty into Treaſon.</p>
            <p>Yet GOD I hope will now be pleaſed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn them to their Allegiance, and give encour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to thoſe who have conſtantly continued loyal, that they may at length once more enjoy hapineſſe, and every man ſit under his own Vine and under his own fig-tree; which, the GOD of HEAVEN be praiſed, we have now greater hopes of then ever.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:204891:6"/>
            <p>If I have in this Hiſtory offended any loyal perſon, I am hartily grieved, I have imparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally endeavoured the truth, and if I be found in the contrary, reaſon will eaſily convince me; and I ſhall be ſory that neither my knowledge or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence extended to a more narrow ſearch.</p>
            <p>I think I have repreſented his Majeſty no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then any loyal perſon (for this age re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires that diſtinction) that hath either heard of or know him will confeſſe him to be; but if they will not, let them be convinced by that ſaying of a worthy Gentleman long time an attendant upon his Majeſty, who having given me a large account of his virtues, at length concluded, <hi>That</hi> Tully <hi>himſelfe (if now alive) could not ſufficiently expreſſe his praiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Gentlemen, it is to you in Generall that I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent this Hiſtory, that you may ſee, and be ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, to whom you have been loyal, and then I believe that you will judge that your loyalty hath found it's just reward in being loyal to ſo juſt a Prince: and if any of you have ſuffered for him, read but his ſufferings, and you cannot value your own. Yet I intend not this at all to his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Tavern friends; which I believe (whilſt
<pb facs="tcp:204891:7"/>they are ſo) are ſo onely there, and indeed I cannot looke upon theſe as faithful Subjects; for how can that man be loyal to his Prince, who hath not the power to be true unto himſelfe. Drunken Subjects, though never ſo loyal, will prove the ruine both of themſelves and their Soveraign.</p>
            <p>Gentlemen, let thoſe that are truly loyal joyn their Prayers with mine for the happineſs of his most SACRED MAIESTY, ſince in his we muſt neceſſarily conclud our own, and more then ours, our COVNTRIES.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:204891:7"/>
            <head>To the Readers in general.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Readers</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F in this Hiſtory I have diſpleaſed any perſon, they cannot be ſo much diſpleaſed as I am ſory; I have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to pleaſe all, nor have I more then Juſtice enforced me to, favoured any; I have laboured (as J profeſſed) to write impartially, where J have not done ſo, J am confident there will not want Carpers.</p>
            <p>Jf in ſome particulers affection hath ſway<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me, (though J confeſſe it a fault) yet it brings it's excuſe. What loyal ſubject can relate his Soveraigns ſufferings without a paſſion? what Free born <hi>Engliſh</hi> man's heart begins not to riſe within him, when he does but think of thoſe Tyrannies &amp; Oppreſſions his Native Countrey hath of late groaned under? where J have been bitter, it has been with reaſon; where ſweet, with a great deal of Juſtice.</p>
            <p>Yet one thing J ſhall deſire the Reader to take notice of, that when J ſpeak of the <hi>presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians,</hi> J mean not thoſe moderate people, who are as truly loyal as they are godly; but ſome
<pb facs="tcp:204891:8"/>amongſt them like wolves in ſheeps cloathing (ſuch as <hi>Straughan</hi> and <hi>Kerry</hi> in <hi>Scotland</hi>) who onely pretend themſelves to be <hi>Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> but are in their proof found Sectaries, theſe are the Flea-bitten Cleargy, the Sowers of ſtrife and ſedition; and a ſcandal to thoſe to whom they pretend to be Brethren.</p>
            <p>To conclude, that all the Subjects of this Land may with one heart and voice agree together for the Reſtauration of our afflicted Soveraign, but of our more afflicted ſelves to juſt Rights and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, is the earnest prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A Hearty well-wiſher to his Countrey.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:204891:8"/>
            <head>THE HISTORY OF <hi>CHARLES</hi> the II. Third MONARCK of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Hiſtories of <hi>Englands</hi> late o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſours have already cloyd and overladed the exuberant Preſs, whole Volums daily coming forth, either of the Actions of the late long Parliament, or the life of their aſpiring Generall <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi> which though adorn'd with all thoſe flatteries, that could poſſibly proceed from the moſt beneficed pens, yet cannot in the leaſt juſtifie their actions to the more ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſort of people; for though their me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:204891:9"/>may here ſmell ſweet to ſome, who have rather taſted of their favour, then ſuffered under their opreſſion, yet do they but render them to the ſufferers more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous, and to the Neuter ridiculous, like <hi>the extolling of Don Quixot's Chivalry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And though there have been ſome who have adventured to ſet them out to the life, and paint them in their own colours; yet have many of theſe as farr exceeded the bounds of Truth, as the others came ſhort of it, rather exaſperated by their own, or to pleaſe their fellow ſufferrers, into ſo great extreams have either ſide been lead, out of fear or flattery, anger or paſſion.</p>
            <p>Moderation and Impartiality are the chiefeſt virtues of an Hiſtorian, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he who writs an Hiſtory, ſhould chuſe ſuch a ſubject to write on, where neither fear nor gain can induce him to flatter, anger or paſſion, or to too much bitterneſſe.</p>
            <p>Moſt of our modern Hiſtorians have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to themſelves either profit, advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage or employment by their Works,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:204891:9"/>which hath made them run into their ſo many groſſe errours and flatteries; whilſt had they only endeavoured to repreſent things, perſons and actions impartially, they had gained to themſelves farr great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er honour of true Writing.</p>
            <p>I have choſen a ſubject to write of, which I conceive may lead me to a mediocrity, the Perſons afflictions may induce me to pity him, but they will in moſt mens judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments reſtrain me from flattery. Nor need I out of fear, I being now (though un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingly) out of his reach, mince the truth of his (if any) bad actions.</p>
            <p>I confeſſe the Task I undertake is high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adventurous, my pen may ſlip, times may change, however my heart ſhall guide me to an impartiality.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>CHARLES</hi> the II. Heir apparent to the Crown of <hi>Great Britain</hi> and <hi>Jreland,</hi> and crowned King of <hi>Scots,</hi> whoſe Hiſtory I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to treat of, was born on the 29. of <hi>May,</hi> 1630, to the great joy of the King, Queen, and indeed the whole Nation; for never
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:204891:10"/>yet had <hi>England</hi> a Prince born of ſo noble an extract and grand Alliance, his father by lineal right &amp; deſent King of <hi>Great Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> and <hi>Jreland,</hi> his mother daughter to that thrice illuſtrious Prince <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, King of <hi>France,</hi> and worthily ſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named the Great, and <hi>Maria de Medicis.</hi> By his Grandmothers ſide was he near al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied to the Kings of <hi>Denmark,</hi> by the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of his Aunt, the noble Princeſſe <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi> to the Elector Palatine of <hi>Rhene,</hi> &amp; King of <hi>Bohemia;</hi> and afterwards by the marriage of his Royal Siſter the Princeſſe <hi>Mary,</hi> to the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi> Thus was he allied to moſt, of the moſt potent Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in Chriſtendome. And happy might this Nation have been under his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if we may believe the vogue of that wiſeſt of men <hi>Solomon,</hi> who pronounces that Kingdome bleſſed <hi>whoſe Prince is the ſon of Nobles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He was ſome years after his birth (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ancient Cuſtomes of <hi>England</hi> for the Kings Eldeſt Son) inveſted Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> Duke of <hi>Cornwall,</hi> and Earle of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:204891:10"/>
               <hi>Chester,</hi> and was in his minority brought up under the care of the Earle of <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> till in the year 1646. the Lord <hi>Hopton</hi>'s Army, in which he was, being near inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> Generall of all the Parliaments Forces in the <hi>Devizes</hi> of <hi>Cornwall,</hi> and the King his Fathers affairs being in a deſperat condition all over <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> he was by the ſerious advice of his beſt friends, perſwaded to take ſhipping, and depart for the <hi>Scillies,</hi> from whence he was by the Parliament invited to return to <hi>London,</hi> but he thought it ſafer for his Perſon to depart from thence to his Siſter at the <hi>Hague,</hi> till the Royall affairs in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> might gain a better poſture, which he did, and there found a reception an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to his Birth.</p>
            <p>Not long after the King his Royall Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, being in danger to be incloſed in Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford by General <hi>Fairfax,</hi> who returning out of the <hi>West,</hi> had deſigned to block it up, took care for his ſafety, and attended only by Mr. <hi>Aſhburnham</hi> (or as ſome ſay, attended on him) went privily our thence,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:204891:11"/>and threw himſelfe upon the <hi>Scotch</hi> Army then at <hi>Newark,</hi> who ſhortly after notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding his confidence of them, for a ſum of money delivered him up moſt perfidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and traiterouſly to his implacable Enemies; the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army. Theſe, after many pretences of Treaties, and ſeeming willingneſs to come to an accord with him, on that black day the 30. of <hi>January</hi> 1648. moſt villaniouſly and trayterouſly, beyond the imagination of the World, murder'd him.</p>
            <p>Thus far is a ſhort view of thoſe hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips and afflictions undergone by this no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Prince, during his Fathers Life &amp; Reign, we will now proceed to thoſe he hath ſince ran through, which we may more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly and particularly call his Own.</p>
            <p>Among which the Chief and greateſt, and from whence all his other miſeries flowed as from their ſpring head, was the deprivation of his Kingdome &amp; Royalties; For that part of the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> which had uſurped the whole power or more, were not onely content to take a way
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:204891:11"/>his fathers life, but by their Proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, deprive him of all right in the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thoſe three Kingdomes, which they take upon themſelves contrary both to the Word of God, the Fundamental Laws of the Nation, and his own undoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted right by birth, he being lineally deſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from that Family, which had ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively governed <hi>England</hi> for above three hundred years.</p>
            <p>He was at that time of his Fathers death, at the Court of his Siſter the Royal Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of <hi>Orange</hi> in the <hi>Hague,</hi> in expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to hear rather of the Concluſion of a Treaty then of his murder, to which effect he writ by the Lord <hi>Seymour</hi> the following Letter to him ſome ſhort time before his Death.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>For the King.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>HAving no means to come to the knowledge of your Majeſties preſent condition, but ſuch as I receive from the Preſs, or (which is
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:204891:12"/>as uncertain) reports. I have ſent this bearer</hi> Seymour <hi>to wait upon your Majeſty, and to bring me an account of it, that I may withall aſſure your Majeſty, I doe not onely pray for your Majeſty according to my duty, but ſhall alwayes be ready to doe all which ſhall be in my power to deſerve that bleſſing which I now humbly beg of your Majeſty upon</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Sir, </salute>
                     <signed>Your Majeſties Moſt humble and moſt obedient Son and Servant, <hi>CHARLES</hi>—</signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Hague</hi>
                        <date>Jan. 23. 1648.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>And here he ſtaid till he heard the heart breaking news of his Fathers Murther, then ſhortly after he took his Iourney to the Queen his mother in <hi>France;</hi> hoping there to get aid, but found none which might render him in a capacity to revenge his Father's Death, or demand his own right by force; and in vain it was to think of any fair means to attain it. Yet there
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:204891:12"/>wanted not ſome friends of his in <hi>England,</hi> who willing to demonſtrate how ready they were to adventure themſelves for him &amp; his right, (as far as their weak abilities would ſtrech,) cauſed under hand a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation to be printed, proclaiming him King of <hi>England, Scotland, France</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and adviſing all his good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to give all due Allegiance to him; but the low condition of the Royaliſts then in <hi>England,</hi> and the great ſtrength and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency of the Parliaments Army, made this Proclamation unvalid, and thoſe who at a fit opportunity would willingly have complied with it, were forced to direct their Obedience to the contrary Goal.</p>
            <p>But though <hi>England</hi> prov'd thus defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to his intereſt, not ſo much I dare ſay in Allegiance as power. Yet <hi>Jreland</hi> is at his Devotion, for the Marqueſs of <hi>Ormond</hi> and the Lord <hi>Inchiquin,</hi> having made a peace with the <hi>Quondam</hi> Rebels, he is by joynt conſent both of Papiſts and Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants proclaimed King in moſt towns of that Nation, <hi>Dublin,</hi> and <hi>London-Derry</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:204891:13"/>excepted, which were kept from their Allegiance, the one by the Lieu. General <hi>Iones,</hi> the other by Sir <hi>Charles Coote,</hi> who joyntly ſtrove to juſtifie the Parliament of <hi>Englands</hi> late actions.</p>
            <p>He being thus proclaimed there, is ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly invited to come over to them, to which invitation, his Mother earneſtly adds her deſires, but the beſt of his friends and Counſellours, as earneſtly diſſwaded him, upon reaſons drawn both from pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Policy, ſince in probability the deſign not ſucceeding, it would utterly ruine his hopes, with all the Proteſtant party then ſtedfaſt to him both in <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>England:</hi> or that if he would needs ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture himſelfe with this party, they deſired him at leaſt to attend, whether by any good event of theirs, there might be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny probability of ſucceſſe.</p>
            <p>'Tis ſuppoſed that this Council ſwaied with him more out of his real affection to the Proteſtant Religion then any other Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick reaſon. Yet he immediately after took a journey to the Iſle of <hi>Ierſey,</hi> which
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:204891:13"/>ſtartled ſome as though he had intended to have proceeded thence for <hi>Ireland,</hi> but that ſuſpition proved unneceſſary: he was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied hither by his Brother the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> (who was lately come to him out of <hi>Holland</hi>) and many other Nobles &amp; Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen; the Iſlanders immediately upon his arrival moſt joyfully proclaimed him King; and the Lord <hi>Iermyn</hi> Earle of <hi>Yar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth</hi> was made Governour of that Iſland, who conſtituted Sir <hi>George Cartwright</hi> his deputy Governour.</p>
            <p>The King ſends from hence his Royal command to the Governour of <hi>Gernſey</hi> Iſland, which was then wholly ſubjected (<hi>Cornet</hi> Caſtle only excepted) to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments ſorces requiring him to ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſaid Iſland to him, and that his good Subjects there might have liberty to return to their due obedience: but his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand proved ineffectual.</p>
            <p>Many affirm, but how true I know not, that the reaſon of the Kings removal to this Iſland was out of deſign to ſurprize <hi>Dartmouth</hi> and ſome other places in the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:204891:14"/>Weſt, by the Levellers help, who having then made a defection from the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Army in <hi>England</hi> were (ſay they) to have joyned with the Royaliſts for the intents and purpoſes a foreſaid, but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo or no I cannot affirm; though I can certainly tell this, that were it ſo, it proved uneffectual, for the Levellers were ſoon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verpowred and quell'd.</p>
            <p>Whilſt King <hi>Charles</hi> was hear expecting a Meſſenger from the States of <hi>Scotland,</hi> came news of the unfortunate overthrow of the Marqueſs of <hi>Ormond</hi> his Army, by Lieu. General <hi>Iones</hi> before <hi>Dublin,</hi> which cauſed a generall ſorrow among all his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, for there had been great hopes &amp; expectations of that Army, it amounting to no leſſe then twenty two thouſand men, &amp; was eſteemed able not onely to have taken <hi>Dublin,</hi> but likewiſe to have reſiſted <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi>'s then new comming Army in the field: yet whether by the carleſſneſs of the Commanders, or ſecurity of the Souldiers, I am loath to judge: this mighty Army. then beleaguring <hi>Dublin,</hi> was beat from
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:204891:14"/>before it by the beſieged, and utterly rou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the third part of its Number.</p>
            <p>This overthrow, the repulſe of Sir <hi>Robert Stuart</hi> and Col. <hi>Mervin</hi> from <hi>London-Derry</hi> by Sir <hi>Charles Coot</hi> and <hi>Cromwell</hi>'s ſuddain landing in <hi>Ireland,</hi> whoſe motion now there was no field Army either to attend or oppoſe, made his Majeſties affairs grow almoſt as deſperate in <hi>Ireland,</hi> as they were before in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the <hi>Scots</hi> Kirk who had ſold their King into the hands of the <hi>Independant Engliſh</hi> Army, after they heard that they had condemned him to death, repent them of their Wickedneſs, waſh their hands from any guilt in his bloud; Expoſtulate with the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſiting in Parliament, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout their ſo ſevere proceedings, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt againſt having any hand in his Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and to make the world believe they had yet ſome touch of loyalty within them, they had juſt after his death pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed <hi>Charles</hi> Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> eldeſt Son to the late murthered King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt, and his lawfull and undoubted Heir, King
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:204891:15"/>of Great <hi>Britain, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> and had immediately reſolved in the Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee of Eſtates then ſitting to ſend ſome fitting perſons to treat with his Majeſty about ſundry Articles; before his recepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Crown, but long debates and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murs there were in the buſineſſe before they could reſolve what &amp; whom to ſend.</p>
            <p>For ſome there were in this <hi>Grand Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of Eſtates,</hi> who, fee'd or ſeduced by the Sectaries in <hi>England,</hi> impeaded to the utmoſt of their power and endeavours all proceedings in the buſineſſe, ſo that once in ſtead of debating what or whom they ſhould ſend to his Majeſty, it came to be a debate whether they ſhould ſend or no, but at length a Letter and Propoſitions was by the prevailing part concluded on, and Mr. <hi>Windram</hi> Laird of <hi>Libberton,</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to be the Meſſenger, who on the 25. of <hi>September</hi> 1649. received his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patches, and ſome time after arrived be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Majeſty at <hi>Ierſey.</hi> The chief of their deſires was to this effect.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:204891:15"/>
            <p>
               <hi>That his Majeſty would gratiouſly be pleaſed himſelfe to ſign the Solemn League &amp; Covenant, and that he would paſſe an Act in Parliament that every perſon in that Kingdome might takeit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That he would paſſe divers Acts of the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament of</hi> Scotland, <hi>which was concluded on the two laſt Seſſions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>For approving of their diſclaiming Duke</hi> Hamilton<hi>'s laſt return.</hi> 2. <hi>For receiving ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Acts made by</hi> Engliſh <hi>for the Militia.</hi> 3. <hi>That the Kings</hi> of Scotland <hi>may have no negative voice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That his Majeſty would recall the late Commiſſions given to</hi> Montroſſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>That he would put away all</hi> Papiſts <hi>from about him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>That he would appoint ſome place about</hi> Holland <hi>to treat with their Commiſſioners. An honourable Company of the moſt noble Lords in</hi> Scotland, <hi>being to be appointed to attend his Majeſty, to whom likewiſe they would ſend a ſufficient proviſion to maintain him, a train ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to his birth and deſerved greatneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>That he would be gratiouſly pleaſed to give a ſpeedy anſwer to their deſires.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:204891:16"/>
            <p>Theſe Propoſitions were very ſtifly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated <hi>Pro</hi> and <hi>Con,</hi> ſome were ſo firce that they would have his Majeſty utterly reject the <hi>Scots</hi> Propoſitions as diſhonourable &amp; diſadvantagious to his affaires. Others were of opinion, that it would more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to the Kings intereſt to accept of ſuch Conditions as he could agree with the <hi>Scotch</hi> Commiſſioners, which would be a readier way to attain the Crown then by <hi>Montroſſe</hi> his deſigns (who had lately re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Commiſſions from the King to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault the North of <hi>Scotland</hi> with what force he could raiſe, however the buſineſs was ſtill demurred and delayed, and no anſwer for a good while given to the Lord <hi>Libberton,</hi> who earneſtly preſt it, till ſuch time as anſwer could come from <hi>Montroſs,</hi> then in <hi>Holland:</hi> and out of <hi>France,</hi> touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their opinions concerning theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, concerning which <hi>Montroſs</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned anſwer to his Majeſty, deſiring him <hi>to harken to the</hi> Scotch <hi>Commiſſioners whilſt they would propoſe &amp; agree to any thing which might ſtand with his Majeſties honour for the reſtoring
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:204891:16"/>him to his Rights and Dignities. That for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe he ſhould rather be content to endure baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from his highneſſe ſight and perſon, then in the leaſt prejudice his affaires.</hi> Thus this faithfull and loyall ſervant courted baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, (as the late famous Earle of <hi>Strafford</hi> had done death) for his Maſters good &amp; ſervice, but too generous was he, and had too great a ſence of goodneſſe &amp; gratitude to grant his requeſt, but returned him this anſwer, <hi>That he had ſo high a ſence of his fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and loyalty all along, and that he had per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed ſo many ſignal ſervices both for his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and himſelfe, that he could not in honour leave him, and therefore deſired him to preſs him no farther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Queen Mother likewiſe earneſtly preſſes her ſon to the acceptance of the <hi>Scotch</hi> Propoſitions for a Treaty, as the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and readieſt way for the eſtabliſhing him in his Kingdoms. Theſe reſolves of his Mother and the Marqueſs of <hi>Montroſs,</hi> wrought ſtrongly with his Majeſty; yet notwithſtanding they are as ſtoutly oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the Lord. <hi>Cleveland, Byron, Gerard,</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:204891:17"/>&amp; others; whoſe chief oppoſition proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the alledged Treachery of the <hi>Scots</hi> to his Father, That they were <hi>Scots</hi> ſtill, and might practice the ſame upon him. But the majority of voices carrying it for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a Treaty, it was reſolved on, yet in regard it would require ſome time to frame an anſwer, Sir <hi>William Fleming</hi> was ſent Agent to the Committee of Eſtates in <hi>Scotland,</hi> 'till ſuch time as the Laird <hi>Libberton</hi> could be diſpatc't.</p>
            <p>Short time after Mr. <hi>Windram</hi> returned into <hi>Scotland</hi> with a Letter and inſtructions by word of mouth, whereby he gave the Committee of Eſtates (who having long expected were therefore more deſirous to hear what he now brought) an account how much he found his Majeſty compliant to their Propoſitions, <hi>viz That as to what acted to the two laſt Seſſions of Parliament he was content a Generall Act of Oblivion ſhould be paſſed, but could not approve it. That neither thoſe of</hi> Montroſſes <hi>nor Duke</hi> Hamilton<hi>'s party in his laſt engagement ſhould bear Office in State without conſent of Parliament. That he had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:204891:17"/>Breda <hi>in</hi> Holland <hi>for the place of a ſolemn Treaty, for the making a full accomoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and agreement between him and his loving Subjects of</hi> Scotland.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Contents of his Letter were as followeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head type="sub">For the Committee of Eſtates of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <signed>CHARLES, <hi>R.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VVE have received your Letters lately preſented to us, by Mr.</hi> Windram <hi>of</hi> Libberton, <hi>and we accept gratiouſly all the expreſſions of affection and fidelity therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained towards us, with your tender reſentment of our preſent Condition, and the juſt indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which you profeſs to have againſt the execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Murther of our Father: and we believe that your intentions are full of Candor towards us, as we are, and always really have been deſirous to ſettle a clear and right intelligence between us and our Subjects of our ancient Kingdome of</hi> Scotland, <hi>which may be an aſſured foundation of their happineſs and peace for the time to come,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:204891:18"/>and an effectual means to root out all the ſeeds of animoſity &amp; diviſions cauſed by theſe late trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles; and alſo to unite the hearts and affections of our Subjects one to another, and of them all to us their King and lawfull Soveraign; to the end that by their Obedience to our Royal and juſt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, we may be put in a condition to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain them in peace and proſperity, &amp; to protect them in their Religion &amp; Liberty, as it appar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains to us according to our charge &amp; office of a King. And as we have alwayes reſolved to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute whatever is to be done by us to obtain theſe good effects, &amp; for the juſt ſatisfaction of all our Subjects in this Kingdome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We have now thought fit upon the Return of Mr.</hi> Windram, <hi>to command &amp; deſire you to ſend unto us Commiſſioners, ſufficiently authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed to treat &amp; agree with us, both in relation to the Intereſt &amp; juſt ſatisfaction of our Subjects there, as alſo concerning the aid &amp; aſſiſtance, which in all reaſon we may expect from them to bring and reduce the murtherers of our late moſt dear Father of happy memory to condign puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp; to recover our juſt rights in all our King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes. And we will that they attend us on the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:204891:18"/>fifteenth of</hi> March <hi>at the Town of</hi> Breda, <hi>where we intend to be in Order thereunto. And in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of a Treaty, as alſo to make known to you &amp; all the World, that we ſincerely deſire to be agreed, We have reſolved to Addreſſe theſe unto you under the Name &amp; Title of a Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee of Eſtates of our Kingdome of</hi> Scotland, <hi>and will and expect that you uſe this grace no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes for any advantage to the prejudice of us, or our Affairs, beyond what we have given this Qualification and Title for, namely, for the Treaty and in order to it. Although we have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations ſufficient, and very important to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade and oblige us to doe nothing in this kind antecedently at this time. Alſo we hope the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence which we declare to have in your clear and candid intentions towards us, will furniſh you with strong Arguments to form in your ſelves a mutual confidence in us, which by the bleſſing of God Almighty by your just &amp; prudent moderation, and by that great deſire we have to oblige all our Subjects of that Kingdome, and by the means of the Treaty which we attend &amp; hope for may be a good foundation of a full and happy peace, and an aſſured ſecurity to this Nation
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:204891:19"/>for the time to come, which we aſſure you is wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of us with paſſion, and which we ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour by all means in our power to effect.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This is the full of his Majeſties Letter to the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mittee of Eſtates in <hi>Scotland,</hi> &amp; much to this effect was there another writ by him to the <hi>Committee of the Kirk.</hi> But this I the rather fully inſert in regard of the many Calumnies caſt upon it, and by it upon his Majeſty: His enemies here by taking occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to carp at him, by pretending his inveterate deſire of revenge, which was ſo contrary to the laſt precepts given him by his dying father. I think, I need not anſwer his enemies objection, they by thoſe carps, only condemning themſelves of a ſelf-guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe, but to the more ſober ſort of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple I ſhall refer it, and let them ſeriouſly conſider whether the begining, progreſſe and end of the Latter, demonſtrate him not a man more addicted to peace &amp; qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſſe, then to revenge and deſtruction.</p>
            <p>The principall Objection which his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies have againſt him, is, that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires the aid of his <hi>Scotch</hi> Subjects, to bring
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:204891:19"/>the Murderers of his Father to condigne puniſhment; does this ſhew him a lover of Revenge or of Juſtice? I would fain know which of his enemies or of his Fathers Murderers, would not, ſhould I have done the ſame to any of their ſo near Relations, have endeavoured to have brought me un<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der the utmoſt cenſure of the Law.</p>
            <p>But to proceed, theſe Letters are ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly debated both in the Committee of Eſtates and <hi>Kirk</hi> the firſt order its conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration to a ſelect ſub Committee of their own, conſiſting of nine Lords and others, who preſent their opinions upon it to the grand Committee, and theſe provide rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy a ſtate of the Caſe to be preſented to the Parliament of <hi>Scotland</hi> which was ſhortly after to aſſemble. But mean while a ſelect number of the <hi>Kirk</hi> and State made up a Committee, who by common conſent were to conſider what was to be done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſending Commiſſioners and Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to his Majeſty; theſe had ſtrong and ſerious debates; for the arrogant <hi>Kirkmen</hi> would not have his Majeſty admitted into
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:204891:20"/>
               <hi>Scotland,</hi> but upon Conditions which ſhould make him wholly ſubſervient to their commands: but the State would have ſuch tart Conditions wholly waved; and (though their own were rough enough, yet) at length a mediation is concluded on between theirs and the <hi>Kirk.</hi> And the Earl of <hi>Caſtles,</hi> the Lord <hi>Louthian, Burley,</hi> &amp; <hi>Lib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berton,</hi> Sir <hi>Iohn Smith</hi> and Mr. <hi>Jeoffreys</hi> for the <hi>Eſtates.</hi> Mr. <hi>Broady, Lawſon</hi> and <hi>Wood</hi> are appointed Commiſſioners for the <hi>Kirk.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe having received their Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Inſtructions, took their journy for <hi>Holland</hi> and arrived at <hi>Breda,</hi> ſome few dayes before his Majeſty got thither. On the 16. <hi>March</hi> 1649. he alſo arrived there, and on the 19. the Lord <hi>Wentworth</hi> Maſter of the Ceremonies conducted them to Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, being come before his Majeſty, who in a large Chamber purpoſely provid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, expected them, The Lord <hi>Caſtles</hi> in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of the <hi>Eſtates,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Lawſon</hi> in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of the <hi>Kirk,</hi> having made their Spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, declared the occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their coming,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:204891:20"/>and ſhewing their Commiſſions, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered the enſuing Propoſitions in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe both of the <hi>Kirk</hi> &amp; State of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p n="1">1. That all thoſe who had been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated by the Church, and ſtill continued ſo, ſhould be forbid acceſſe to the Court.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That all Acts of the Parliament of <hi>Scotland</hi> ſhould be by him ratified and approved of. That the ſolemn League and Covenant, the Presbyterian Church-government, The Directory, Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Catechiſm ſhould be enjoyned in <hi>Scotland;</hi> and the ſame uſed and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in his family, and an Oath to be tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en by him, that he would never oppoſe it, or endeavour to alter it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That he would by ſolemne Oath, &amp; under his hand &amp; ſeal declare and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge his allowance of the ſolemne League and Covenant, &amp; the National Covenant of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. That he would conſent and agree that all civil matters might be determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by ſubſequent Parliaments in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:204891:21"/>and all Eccleſiaſtical matters by the General <hi>Kirk</hi> aſſembly, as was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly granted by his Royal father.</p> 
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>To theſe Propoſitions his Majeſty demanded,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Whether this were fully and wholly all that the Committee of Eſtates and Kirk in <hi>Scotland</hi> had to deſire or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound? &amp; whether theſe Commiſſioners had power to remit or recede from any of theſe particulars; and further, what they had to propound concerning his affairs in <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>To whch the Commiſſioners replied,</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>That they had acquainted him with their full power, according to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions they had received from the Committees of Eſtates and Kirk in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon which his Majeſty made an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; that he would conſider of their
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:204891:21"/>Propoſitions, and doubted not but to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn them ſuch an Anſwer as might give his Kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> ſatisfaction:</p>
            </q>
            <p> and ſo diſmiſſed them for the preſent.</p>
            <p>But let us thus leave his Majeſty and Councel debating about the <hi>Scotch</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners propoſitions, and diſcourſe a little about his affairs under the conduct of the thrice noble and Illuſtrious Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs of <hi>Montroſſe,</hi> who having (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the oppoſition which <hi>Hamilton</hi> gave to the deſign) obtained Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners from his Majeſty to leavy what force he could on that ſide the ſea, endeavoured to the utmoſt of his power to effect it, but chiefly among the Princes of the <hi>German</hi> Empire, where he found large and fair promiſes, but very little real aſſiſtance, onely the Duke of <hi>Holſtein</hi> ſupplied him with four ſhips well arm'd and mann'd, though theſe were likewiſe by ſome ſtrange neglect delayed a long time at <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam,</hi> which much retarded the ſervice. Colonel <hi>Cochram</hi> likewiſe who had been ſent agent into <hi>Poland</hi> to the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:204891:22"/>there for aſſiſtance of men and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, having received a conſiderable quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of money, and good ſupply of corn, diſpoſed of the firſt to his own uſe, ſold the other, and himſelfe revolted from the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. General <hi>King,</hi> who was expected out of <hi>Sweden</hi> with a party of Horſe, came not at all; ſo many croſſes there were in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining of the buſineſs as had Omens to it's future ill ſucceſſe. But at length the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe fearing leaſt if the King ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with the <hi>Scots</hi> before he had attempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed any thing, his Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſions would be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called, fatally reſolved to depart <hi>Scotland</hi> as he was. So with four ſhips indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly well armed, (but with not above ſix or ſeaven hundred men, &amp; thoſe moſt ſtangers) beſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des a ſmall Frigat of ſixteen Guns, &amp; one thouſand five hundred good Armes given him by the Queen of <hi>Sweden;</hi> he ſet ſail, &amp; this was all the ſtrength he carried with him from <hi>Hamburgh</hi> to aſſault that potent Kingdom. Two of theſe ſhips, and thoſe the biggeſt; were ſent before, &amp; directed to ſteer their courſe for the <hi>Orcades,</hi> but
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:204891:22"/>theſe unfortunately met with a ſtorm; and where amongſt thoſe rocky Iſlands, their men, arms &amp; amunition was caſt away, ſo that a third part of the Forces raiſed for this expedition was loſt.</p>
            <p>But notwithſtanding theſe fatal diſaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, the ſad preſages of his ruine, the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Marqueſs proceeds, and with the ſmall number that was left him, lands amongſt the Iſlands where he gets together a pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty conſiderable number which had almoſt the face of an Army, but was for the moſt part compoſed of raw and unskilfull fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, a party of theſe he ſends out, who without reſiſtance enters the Iſle of <hi>Orkney,</hi> there being no Garriſon there; from thence he diſpatches Commiſſioners to <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and the Iſland adjacent, for the levy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Horſe and Foot, which becauſe the inhabitants of thoſe places to which they were ſent could not reſiſt, obeyed; and not long after the ſending of thoſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions, <hi>Montroſſe</hi> himſelf; with thoſe forces he had, and thoſe Gentlemen, reſolved to engage in partaking of his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:204891:23"/>landed in <hi>Scotland.</hi> at the point of <hi>Cathanes,</hi> the very fartheſt land to the <hi>North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſt</hi> of that Kingdom.</p>
            <p>The people here whom he expected to have joyned with him (were ſo ſenſible of the miſeries of the former war, and now more terrified with the name of Forraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,) deſerted their dwellings, and fled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, ſome never ſtopping till they came to <hi>Edenbrough.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Parliament of <hi>Scotland</hi> who were now aſſembled, though they had former ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Marqueſs's deſignes, yet could not tell the place of his landing, but now alarm'd by the flying Countrey: <hi>David Leſley</hi> is commanded with the body of the Army to march directly towards them for feare <hi>Montroſs</hi> ſhould grow too numerous: and Colonel <hi>Straughan,</hi> whoſe valour the States highly approved, is ordered with a party of ſelect Horſe to advance before, to hinder the Marqueſs's levyes, and if he ſaw oportunity to fight him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Montroſſe</hi> in the mean time to ſatisfie the World, and becauſe the people ſhould not
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:204891:23"/>be ſtartled at his Invaſion, whilſt the King was upon Treaty, publiſhes a very pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theticall Declaration,
<q> declaring the juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his cauſe, and to clear himſelfe from the aſpertion of ſiniſter ends, and that his intention was only againſt ſome particular perſons, who had againſt the Laws of the Kingdome, raiſed and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained a war againſt his Majeſties father. and did now by their wiles and ſubtile practices endeavour to deſtroy the Son alſo; &amp; therefore exhorting all Subjects of that Nation to endeavour to free them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from the Tyranny of thoſe who then by an uſurped power ruled over them.</q> But notwithſtanding this Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, the Countrey came very ſlowly in.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Straughan</hi> in the mean time advances with all poſſible ſpeed towards the Royall party, whileſt <hi>Montroſs</hi> had not (for indeed he could not effect) any thing Material be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the fortifying of <hi>Dunbath</hi> Caſtle: but the Marqueſs hearing of the enemies ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, made his whole Forces march at a great rate to recover a paſs; yet neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:204891:24"/>before they could come at it, the front of the Army diſcovered <hi>Straughan</hi>'s forlorn hope, who marching with haſt upon the Marqueſſes Army, found them both almoſt tired, &amp; out of breath &amp; Order; howevera forlorn hope of a 100. foot are drawn out to meet them, who giving them a reſolute Charge forced them to an Orderly Retreat, but being ſeconded by <hi>Straughan's</hi> whole body of Horſe they again maintained their ground reſolutely Charging upon the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſes main body: the Iſlanders immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately threw down their Arms and cryed for quarter, but the <hi>Holſteiners</hi> and <hi>Hamburgers</hi> made an Orderly retreat for the preſent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſome buſhes, which having a ſhort time defended, they were at laſt enforced to yeild.</p>
            <p>This was a ſad blow to his Majeſties af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs in <hi>Scotland,</hi> there being great hopes, that had <hi>Montroſs</hi> ſucceeded and kept them in play, both <hi>Kirk</hi> and <hi>State</hi> would have come to milder Conditions with him: Yet the Marqueſs himſelfe eſcaped for the preſent out of this Battel, Though there
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:204891:24"/>were hear two hundred ſlain, and twelve hundred taken in the field (for the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey coming in upon them, few eſcaped, (Amongſt the Priſoners of note, there were taken Col. <hi>Hurry,</hi> the Lord <hi>Frenderick,</hi> Sir <hi>Francis Hay</hi> of <hi>Dalgettey,</hi> Col. <hi>Hay</hi> of <hi>Nough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> Col. <hi>Gray</hi> and ſeveral other Officers; together with the Kings Standard, which contained this Emphaticall Motto, <hi>JUDGE AND REVENG MY CAUSE O LORD;</hi> and whereon was pourtrayed to the life the Effigies of his Majeſties Father beheaded.</p>
            <p>But long it was not ere this thrice Heroick Marqueſs fell into the hands of theſe cruel, Obdurate &amp; inveterate enemies; for though when he ſaw the Battell at a loſſe, he had ſaved himſelfe by eſcaping out of the field, and had afterwards to diſguiſe himſelfe changed his habit with an <hi>Highlander,</hi> yet all could not prevail to his Eſcape, for the whole Country was raiſed up in armes in ſearch after him, and a price ſet upon his head by the States, but eſpetially the <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian</hi> Miniſters exhorted the people to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:204891:25"/>endeavour his atachment, as a thing ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to their Salvation.</p>
            <p>At length the whole Countrey being up in armes about him, and no way left for this diſtreſſed Marqueſs to eſcape, he thought it better to throw himſelfe upon the Lord <hi>Aſton,</hi> formerly a friend of his, and now out in the ſearch with ſome of his Tennants, then fall into the hands of his more inveterate and implacable enemies. But this Lord, notwithſtanding he had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly been <hi>Montroſs</hi>'s follower, either out of fear or covetouſneſs durſt not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal him; but ſent him with a ſtrong guard to <hi>David Leſly;</hi> by whom he was directly ſent to <hi>Edenbrough,</hi> &amp; ſhortly after brought to his Tryall before the Parliamant of <hi>Scotland:</hi> where all the while notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding thoſe many ignominious affronts and diſgraces thrown upon him (as his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing intriumphant manner brought through <hi>Edenbrough</hi> bound in a Cart) yet he carried himſelf with ſo much Magnanimity and Courrage, That thoſe of his Enemies, who did not pity him, yet were almoſt aſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:204891:25"/>of their vilainies towards him.</p>
            <p>The Parliament of <hi>Scotland</hi> upon the firſt newes of this Noble Marqueſs being made a Priſoner, met, and reſolved to paſs a ſentence upon him before either he was come up, or had at all anſwered for himſelf, &amp; though, when they allowed him to ſpeak ſomwhat for himſelf, (which he pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with gravity void of paſſion,) yet he had as good have held his peace; for the ſentence being agreed upon, it was paſt to this effect.</p>
            <p>
               <q>That he ſhould be carried to the place from whence he came, and from thence (to morrow being the 21. day of <hi>May</hi> 1650.) be carried to the high Croſs in <hi>Edinbruogh</hi> and be hanged upon a Gib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be thirty foot high, and there hang for the ſpace of three hours in the ſight and view of all people, with his Hiſtory and Declaration hanging about his Neck; after which he ſhould be taken down, beheaded and quartered; his head to be placed upon, he <hi>Talbooth</hi> or priſon houſe in <hi>Edenbrough,</hi> and his legs &amp; arms over
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:204891:26"/>the gates of the Cities of <hi>Sterling, Glaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cow, S. Iohns town</hi> and <hi>Aberdeen.</hi> And in caſe he repented (by which means his ſentence of Excomunication might be taken off by the <hi>Kirk</hi>) the bulk of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy might be buried in <hi>Grayfriers,</hi> if not, to be buried in the Common burying place for thieves and robbers.</q> Thus far did their unparallel'd hatred and malice extend even to his dead Corps.</p>
            <p>This Sentence being aggravated by the Chancellour in the utmoſt terms of hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour that his ſpleen could invent, was yet mildly and unpaſſionately received by this Illuſtrious Marqueſs, who anſwered no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to it. But,
<q>That he took it for a greater honour to have his head ſtand on the priſon gate for this quarrel, then to have his picture in the Kings Bed-cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers; and leaſt his loyalty ſhould be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, they had highly honoured him, in deſigning laſting Monuments to four of the chiefeſt Cities to bear up his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial to all poſterity; wiſhing he had fleſh enough to have ſent a piece to every
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:204891:26"/>City in Chriſtendome, to witneſs his loyalty to his King and Countrey.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The next day being the day appointed for his execution, richly habited, in a ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let Cloak laced with gold, but his ſoul a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned with conſtant Loyalty the far rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Ornament of the two, he marched along the ſtreet with ſo compoſed a Courrage &amp; Gravity, that moſt of his Enemies either pityed or admired him: being come to the place of execution, he was ſome time de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained with many frivolous queſtions of the flea-bitten Clergy, being ready to mount up the lader, he ſaid it was Jacob<hi>'s Lader by which he ſhould mount to Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Speech to the people was ſhort and much to this effect.
<q>That he was ſory if his end ſhould be ſcandalous to any good Chriſtian: but that it often happened to the Righteous according to the wayes of the wicked, that they who knew him ſhould not diſeſteem him for his ignomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious death. That he confeſſed it was the judgement of God upon him for his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vat ſins; but as for his condemners, they
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:204891:27"/>were but inſtruments. That they had perverted judgement and juſtice and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed the poor: yet he deſired God to forgive them, for he heartily forgave them. That what he did in that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, he did it in obedience to the juſt commands of his Sovereign, to aſſiſt him againſt thoſe which roſe up againſt him. That it was not his fault that he lay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſenſure of the Church, ſince 'twas only for doing his duty. That for what was ſaid of him that he ſhould blame the King, he ſaid, 'twas moſt falſe, for (ſaies he) the late King lived a Saint, and died a Martyr. That if ever he ſhould wiſh his ſoul in any mans place, it ſhould be in his. That for the King now living, he was a Prince under whom any people might live moſt happily, his commands were righteous, his promiſes ſaithfull, and his dealings juſt. Finally, that he commended his ſoul to God, his ſervice to his Prince, his good will to his friends, and his name &amp; charity to all good peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:204891:27"/>
            <p>This was the ſum of his ſpeech on the ladder, which, and ſome private prayers being finiſhed: he mounted up the top of that prodigious Gibbet, where his Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Declaration being tied about his neck, and his hands bound by the Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner, he turned about and gave him ſome gold, asking; <hi>If they had any more diſhonour, as they conceived it, to put upon him, he was ready to accept it,</hi> and then with a great deal of magnanimity, biding the Executioner turn him off when he ſhould hold up his hands, it was accordingly performed.</p>
            <p>Thus nobly lived, and thus ignomini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly &amp; yet <hi>nobly</hi> died: the trueſt of friends, the loyalleſt of Subjects, the faithfulleſt of Servants, the beſt of Maſters, and the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lianteſt of Captains. <hi>Iames Graham,</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs of <hi>Montroſs</hi> Earl of <hi>Rindardin,</hi> Lord of <hi>Groaem</hi> and Baron of <hi>Montdieu,</hi> whoſe death was not only lamented as a private but rather as publick loſs: moſt of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in <hi>Europe</hi> deploring the unfortunate fall of ſo Noble and Heroick a perſon; for he was endowed with ſuch winning graces,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:204891:28"/>that whereever he came he was both ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured and eſteemed, and whereever he Commanded, both feared and loved.</p>
            <p>His enemies Mallicce, though he was dead, kept ſtill alive; for after they had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed him and cut off his quarters, they would not permit that bulk of his body which remained to be buried in any other place then the <hi>Borough Moor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this Noble Marqueſs ſuffered not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, for ſoon after Col. <hi>Hurrie</hi> (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding he pleaded the benefit of Quarter, young <hi>Spotſwood</hi> of <hi>Daerſie,</hi> A moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Gentleman) Sir <hi>Francis Hay,</hi> &amp; Col. <hi>Sibbalds,</hi> two moſt accompliſhed perſons, though they had all the favour to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed.</p>
            <p>There was likewiſe one Captain <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> who being put in hopes of life by the perfidious <hi>Kirk,</hi> upon his recantation, made a long ſpeech upon the Scaffold, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging his Apoſtacy from the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and deſiring to be reconciled to the <hi>Kirk</hi> but had notwithſtanding his head ſtruck off,</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:204891:28"/>
            <p>This was the fatall and Tragicall Event of his Majeſties affairs in <hi>Scotland</hi> under <hi>Montroſſe</hi>'s Conduct: let us now turn to ſee how the treaty at <hi>Breda</hi> went on in the mean time.</p>
            <p>But before I proceed any further, give me leave to ſpeak a word or two, concerning the Magnanimous Col. <hi>Will. Sibbalds,</hi> who (ſay ſome) confeſſed himſelfe guilty of the Murther of D. <hi>Doriſlaus</hi> the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Agent at the <hi>Hague,</hi> which I muſt ingeniouſly confeſſe I believe upon good ground to be only a Calumny and ſcandal raiſed from the ſo far extended Marice of his enemies; for I can find nothing either in his ſpeech at Death, or in any Records of credit tending to ſuch a confeſſion, though much againſt any likelyhood of it: nor can I ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that any man could with ſo much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution as he dyed with, part from this world, and have ſo great a load and blot upon Conſcience. But to proceed, Great debates there were in the mean time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween his Majeſty and the <hi>Scotch</hi> Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners concerning the Treaty, and great
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:204891:29"/>demurs there were upon it; for beſides the ſtriving of ſome Lords who had a kind of a ſerious Antipathy to the <hi>Scots</hi> perfidiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and endeavoured to perſwade his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty not to truſt them who had betrayed his Father. The King himſelfe ſtuck high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as he had reaſon, about the buſineſs of of taking the <hi>Covenant;</hi> For, 1. <hi>There was no reaſon why he ſhould be enforced to relinquiſh the Religion of his Fathers, and whilſt he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to his Subjects Liberty of Conſcience, it would be very inconſiſtent with their ſo earneſtly pretended deſires of a peace and agreement, to deny him the ſame priviledge which he gave them.</hi> 2. <hi>That Covenant tendered, and ſo earneſtly preſt upon him by them, was an Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Covenant to bind the Subjects to him, and not for him to ſwear to; and therefore he judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it ſufficiently ſatisfactory to paſs an act for the peoples taking it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whilſt theſe demurs and delayes were in the Treaty, the <hi>Scotch</hi> Commiſſioners give a viſit to the Illuſtrious Prince of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range,</hi> whom they intreat to be a Mediator between them and their King. His Majeſty
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:204891:29"/>likewiſe withdrawes himſelfe for ſome time from <hi>Breda</hi> to the <hi>Hague,</hi> there to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe with his Aunt the Queen of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> and other friends, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout what he were beſt to reſolve on, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Eſtates</hi> of <hi>Scotland</hi> though their propoſed Conditions were already unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, yet reſolve to add more weight to the ſcale: the Earl of <hi>Carnworth</hi> and Mr. <hi>Murrey</hi> are ſent over to the Commiſſioners at <hi>Breda</hi> with new inſtructions and propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions; As, 1. <hi>That his Maieſty ſhould confirm all Acts done in ſome late Seſſions of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, without any exception.</hi> 2. <hi>That neither</hi> Montroſs <hi>nor any of his adherents be admitted to come into the Kingdome of</hi> Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</p>
            <p>But notwithſtanding the harſhneſs of the Conditions, the King is earneſtly preſſed to come to a full concluſion with the <hi>Scots,</hi> Though many Lords of the contrary facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on pleaded for an utter rejection of their propoſitions, alleadging to his Majeſty, <hi>That the Covenanters horid perfidouſneſs to his
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:204891:30"/>Father might be a ſufficient motive and induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for him not to truſt them; That the more willing he was to condiſcend to their Propoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, the more impudent they were ſtill in propoſing things moſt unreaſonable; That ſhould he accept of their Conditions, they would ſo tye up his hands that he would be then but a King only in Title, which he was without them.</hi> On the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, the Earl of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> the Lord <hi>Wilmot, Piercy,</hi> and others of his Majeſties Council who ſtood for an accomodation with the <hi>Scots,</hi> urged, <hi>That his Majeſties affairs both in</hi> Ireland, <hi>under the Marqueſs of</hi> Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troſs, <hi>and in the Navy under Prince</hi> Pupert, <hi>were in ſo weak and tottering a Condition, that no helpe could be expected from them; That all the Princes in</hi> Europe <hi>were ſo imbroyled in Wars of their own, that it was in vain to crave any Forreign aid; &amp; that therefore there was no way left for his Majeſty to regain his loſt Rights and Kingdoms but by complying with his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of</hi> Scotland, <hi>and though it were upon ſuch Conditions as would at firſt ſeem harſh, thoſe Curbs might in time (poſſeſſion got) be thrown off by degrees;</hi> theſe reaſons ſwayed with his
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:204891:30"/>Majeſty, &amp; the Treay went on with a clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er face then formerly.</p>
            <p>But now there happens a ſtrong demur, or as moſt ſuppoſed, a buſineſs that would wholly break off the Treaty, for the newes of <hi>Montroſſe</hi>'s ignominious death being come to <hi>Breda,</hi> extreamly incenſed the whole Court, and thoſe who were againſt the Treaty, beſtirred themſelves ſtrongly, ſtill endeavouring to avert the King wholly from it, by telling him,
<q>That they had by thus murthering his Leiutennant, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated to the World what they would do to him if they had him in their power; That it was an act of raſhneſſe and deſperation to truſt them, or to have any more to do with ſuch a perfidious generation; That they only cunningly and ſubtilly endeavoured to entrap him that they might deſtroy him.</q> But notwithſtanding their heat, his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty conceals his anger, (which doubtleſs could not but be great, for the death and the ſo Ignominious death of ſo good and loyal a ſubject and Servant; and that too in
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:204891:31"/>his quarrel, and for obeying his juſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands (only he expreſſes his reſentment of their ſo ſtrange proceedings to the Committee of Eſtates by a Meſſage ſent by Mr. <hi>Murrey</hi> to this effect.</p>
            <p>
               <q>That it could not but grieve and perplex him to hear, that whilſt they pretended to conclude a peace, they proceeded in the way of War; and that whilſt they treated of an accord with him, they ſhed the bloud of his beſt Subjects, and that in ſuch a manner, that if true as report<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, they could not imagine but it muſt extreamly incenſe him, he therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired them to give him an account of their buſineſſe.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>To this they return Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>That their affections were ſtill reall to him, &amp; that it rejoyced their very ſoules, to hear that he would be willing to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur with them in a peace and agreement, That as for the Death of <hi>Montroſs,</hi> they deſired it might be no obſtacle in the way, for that they did nothing in it but with a reall intention to promote his intereſt.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:204891:31"/>
            <p>Thus they endeavoured to excuſe them ſelves, but it was not their excuſe, nor their ſo many reiterated Proteſtations of fidelity, but the neceſſity of the Kings af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, which drew him not long after to conclude the Treaty at <hi>Breda</hi> (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the violent oppoſers of it) by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcending to moſt of their deſires</p>
            <p>The concluſion of the Treaty was ſoon carried to <hi>Edenbrough,</hi> where the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment being met, it was yet by ſome of thoſe who favoured the Secterian party in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> made a debate, <hi>whether they ſhould make any more addreſſes to the King.</hi> So impudent were they even after the treaty was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded with him, but there were found but thirty of theſe malevolent perſons; ſo the major part of the Votes carrying it in the affirmative, it was reſolved that ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meſſage ſhould be ſent unto him, to invite him to make all poſſible ſpeed to his Kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> proteſting that they would venture Lives and Fortunes in aſſiſting him to regain his Rights &amp; King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms; but they not only debar him from
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:204891:32"/>having thoſe whom he chiefly favoured to wait upon him, but likewiſe prohibit the Duke <hi>Hamilton,</hi> the Earls of <hi>Lauderdale</hi> &amp; <hi>Seaforth,</hi> and many other perſons of quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties return to <hi>Scotland,</hi> and they nominate ſuch perſons as they thought fit out of their own Gang to be officers of his houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold there.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Juncto</hi> then ſiting and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>England,</hi> had certain intelligence all along of the proceeds of the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty between his Majeſty and the <hi>Scots,</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with their Propoſitions to aſſiſt him in the recovery of his Rights in <hi>England</hi> by ſome who ſate in the Parliament of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> betrayed their counſells, and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly ſolicited the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to aſſault <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> before they were themſelves aſſault<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and invaded, to which effect they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare an Army without any juſt pretence, which they give to <hi>Oliver Cromwell</hi> to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, making him Generaliſſimo of all the Forces of that Commonwealth in the room of Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> whoſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion was between taken away and laid down.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:204891:32"/>
            <p>Some time before his Majeſtie's depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from <hi>Holland</hi> into <hi>Scotland,</hi> newes was brought of the unfortunate loſs of all Prince <hi>Rupert's</hi> Fleet, moſt of his ſhips be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing either taken, ſunk or burnt by General <hi>Blake,</hi> Admiral to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Navy; ſo though the Treaty was concluded with <hi>Scotland,</hi> his Majeſtie's affairs went every where elſe to wrack.</p>
            <p>At length all things being in a readineſs, his Majeſty about the beginning of <hi>Iune</hi> 1650. took ſhipping at <hi>Sheveling</hi> in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and after a tedious ſtorm, and nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row eſcape of ſome <hi>Engliſh</hi> Veſſels which lay in wait for him, arrived at <hi>Spey</hi> in the <hi>North</hi> of <hi>Scotland.</hi> Some Lords are ſent down to receive him, and to accompany him to <hi>Edenbrough,</hi> where two ſtately hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are richly provided and furniſh't to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain him.</p>
            <p>He was all along the Countrey enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained with the General joy of all the people, ſeverall preſents being given him by the Towns as he came along. <hi>Aberdeen</hi> preſented him with 1500. <hi>l</hi> but the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:204891:33"/>of <hi>Eſtates</hi> and <hi>Kirk</hi> fearing that ſuch diet would prove too unwieldy to their pleaſures, ſent an injunction to ſeveral places, requiring them that what ever moneys they had to beſtow, they ſhould bring it to ſuch treaſuries as ſhould be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by them. Thus they permit not the Subjects to ſhew their good will to their Soveraign, nor him to receive it.</p>
            <p>Nor were the <hi>States</hi> &amp; <hi>Kirk</hi> as yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with thoſe hard conditions: but they ſend him new propoſitions to <hi>Dundee</hi> to ſign, which after ſome reluctancy he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed; for indeed he could do no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, being now in their clutches.</p>
            <p>The Parliament and Committee of <hi>Estates</hi> in <hi>Scotland</hi> had while they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected his Majeſties arrivall been conſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about the framing of an Army, every fourth man in the Kingdome is ordered to be trained; and ſixteen thouſand foot, and ſix thouſand horſe to be raiſed for his Majeſties preſent ſervice. Of this Army the Earle of <hi>Leven</hi> is made General of the Foot, and <hi>Holborn</hi> Major General, <hi>David
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:204891:33"/>Leſley</hi> Lieutenant General of the Horſe, and <hi>Montgomery</hi> Major General: the place of <hi>Generaliſſimo</hi> was reſerved for the King, though he never went into the field with the Army.</p>
            <p>His Majeſty being come to <hi>Edenbrough,</hi> is received by the Parliament and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of <hi>Eſtates</hi> &amp; <hi>Kirk,</hi> with infinite complements and expreſſions of fidelity &amp; affection, and with great acclamations of joy from the people, and on the 15. of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> is again ſolemnly proclaimed King at <hi>Edenbrough</hi> Croſſe, but his coronation yet defer'd by reaſon of the then troubles.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army, notwithſtanding the <hi>Scots</hi> had expoſtulated them the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtneſs of invading their Countrey, was advanced upon the borders, &amp; at <hi>Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleborough</hi> the <hi>Scots</hi> under <hi>Montgomery</hi> with a ſmall party, ſet upon the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army, but were worſted, and ſo the two Armies moved at a diſtance one from the other, till they came as far as <hi>Dunbar,</hi> where the <hi>Scots</hi> had got a conſiderable advantage, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of a paſſe, and brag'd they had got the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:204891:34"/>
               <hi>Engliſh</hi> in a pound: but whether by their own careleſneſſe and over ſecurity; or the over-reaching, courage and valour of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> I cannot tell, a totall loſſe they had there, the paſſe gain'd from them, &amp; themſelves wholly routed and diſperſed.</p>
            <p>I am the ſhorter in relating the paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges between theſe two Armies, in regard that though the King was made <hi>Generaliſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo;</hi> yet he had no influence upon the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, which might rather be called the <hi>States</hi> or <hi>Kirks</hi> then the Kings; for though he was there preſent; and bore the title of <hi>King,</hi> yet they had the whole power, and made and revoked Lawes and Orders.</p>
            <p>The King was then with the States at Saint <hi>Iohnſtons,</hi> when the newes of this loſſe, and that of the Death of his Siſter the Princeſſe <hi>Elizabeth</hi> arriv'd much about the ſame time, and ſome have been bold to affirm that the latter grieved him more then the former, in regard of the imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs which 'twas probable the States of <hi>Scotland</hi> would have uſurped, had the ſucceſſe anſwered their minds.</p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:204891:34"/>
            <p>And ſufficiently imperious were both they and the <hi>Kirk</hi> already, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ill fortune of their affairs; for, ſo great was their inſolency towards his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, in their earneſtneſs to purge his houſe, in extorting Declarations from him againſt his own party and proceedings, &amp; in uſurping the whole government of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs to themſelves, in placing guards of their own creatures upon his Perſon, &amp;c. That his ſacred Majeſty no longer able to ſuffer ſuch intollerable affronts &amp; abuſes, went ſecretly away, accompanied only with four horſe towards the <hi>North</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> where the Marqueſs of <hi>Hunt ley,</hi> the Earls of <hi>Seaforth</hi> and <hi>Atholl,</hi> the Lords <hi>Ogilby</hi> and <hi>Newburgh,</hi> with the <hi>Gourdons</hi> were ready to appear for him with a conſiderable party.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Scotland</hi> was at this time not only perple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xed with a forreign enemy in her bowels, but with civill diſtempers &amp; diviſions; for in the <hi>Weſt</hi> there was a party under the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of <hi>Straughan</hi> &amp; <hi>Kerr;</hi> who declar'd againſt the actions of the Committee of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:204891:35"/>
               <q>for their too much haſt and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitation in the Treaty with the King for their receiving him before he had given any evidence of a real change. That they believed his profeſſion of the cauſe and covenant was counterfeit, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore refuſed to ſubmit to his power;</q> Theſe men were purely for the <hi>Kirk</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King's Authority.</p>
            <p>Another party there was in the <hi>North</hi> under the Command of <hi>Huntley, Atholl, Seaforth,</hi> &amp;c. who declared purely for the Kingly Authority diſclaiming and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owning all power or order of the <hi>Kirk,</hi> Parliament or Committee of Eſtates. Theſe having gotten together a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble party, it was ſuppoſed by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of Eſtates that his Majeſty was gon to them, whereupon to quiet &amp; alay them if poſſible, an Act of Indempnity was paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by <hi>Parliament</hi> for what they had done; but they ſleighted it, fell upon Sir <hi>Iohn Brown</hi>'s Regiment, and ſlew and took pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners many of his men; Whereupon Lieut. Generall <hi>David Laſley</hi> was ſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt;
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:204891:35"/>him; but the whole buſineſs after the Kings return to St. <hi>Iohnſton</hi>'s ended in a Treaty.</p>
            <p>The third &amp; greateſt party were the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> &amp; <hi>Committee</hi> of <hi>Eſtates</hi> &amp; <hi>Kirk,</hi> who were equally for King &amp; <hi>Kirk;</hi> theſe were highly perplexed and diſcontented at the King's going away from S. <hi>Iohnſton</hi>'s and the more becauſe they feared he was gon to the <hi>Athol men,</hi> many con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies &amp; conſultations were had about it; ſome were ſo ridged as to propoſe, that ſince he had deſerted them, they ſhould look no more after him, but let him take his own wayes: Others were more mild, and would yet have him underſtand their reſentment for his leaving them; nor wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted there ſome ſticklers for his Majeſty; at length it was concluded that Major Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <hi>Montgomery</hi> ſhould ſpeedily march af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him, and earneſtly intreat him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to <hi>S. Iohnſtons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Montgomery</hi> according to his order went, and having had ſecret information that his Majeſty was at the Lord <hi>Dedup</hi>'s houſe
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:204891:36"/>in the <hi>North</hi> confines of <hi>Fife,</hi> he firſt ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounds the houſe, and then ſends in a Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger to acquaint the King with the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt deſires of the Committee of Eſtates; that he would gratiouſly be pleaſed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn with him to St. <hi>Johnſton</hi>'s; but his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty at firſt abſolutely refuſed, as ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to endure that ſlavery which they had ſubjected him to, he was in the mean time earneſtly ſolicited by <hi>Huntley,</hi> and the <hi>Gordons</hi> to adhere ſolely to them, which he ſo much ſeemed to incline to, that he had almoſt made the breach implacable between that party and the <hi>Kirk;</hi> but at length upon ſeverall propoſitions granted him, he returned with <hi>Montgomery</hi> to St. <hi>Johnſton</hi>'s.</p>
            <p>The King being thus returned, and <hi>Huntley's</hi> party come in by admitting thoſe with him to bear publick Offices, a general Meeting was reſolved on to be held at St. <hi>Johnſtons,</hi> which ſhould conſiſt of King, Lords, Barons, Burgeſſes and the aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of Miniſters; whereupon the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of the <hi>Kirk</hi> are ſummoned to meet,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:204891:36"/>but ſtand off, alledging that <hi>Sterling</hi> was the more convenient place to meet in; To which the <hi>States</hi> anſwer'd, that they e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed S. <hi>Johnſtons</hi> the fitter, that if they would not meet, they ſhould conſult for their own ſecurities, but at length they conſent; The grand Aſſembly meets, &amp; all parties ſeem now agreed. Severall Lords formerly in disfavour with the <hi>Kirk,</hi> are received into Command in the Army, or have liberty to ſit in Parliament, ſuch as <hi>Hamilton, Lauderdale, Lieth, Bucheim, Dedup,</hi> and <hi>Crawford,</hi> Major Generall <hi>Maſſey</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> was admitted to a command in the Army. Thus did their diviſions begin to be cemented, which elſe muſt neceſſarily have haſtened their Ruine.</p>
            <p>About this time the King received the ſad newes of the death of the thrice illuſtrious Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> Brother-in-law to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, &amp; who had demonſtrated himſelfe a true &amp; faithfull friend to him in his neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities; his Lady the Royall Princeſs <hi>Mary</hi> was by him left great with Child, and ſoon after his death was delivered of a <hi>Poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hume</hi>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:204891:37"/>ſon.</p>
            <p>And now on the firſt of <hi>January</hi> the day appointed by the Grand Convention at S. <hi>Johnſtan's</hi> the ſolemnity having been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved to <hi>Scone</hi> the uſuall place for the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronation of the Kings of <hi>Scotland;</hi> Firſt his Maieſty in a Princes Robe, was conducted from his Bed-chamber by the <hi>Conſtable</hi> and <hi>Marſhal</hi> to the Chamber of preſence, where he was by the Lord <hi>Angus</hi> Chamberlin placed in a Chair under a cloth of Eſtate; Then the Nobles and Commiſſioners of Baronyes &amp; Burroughs entred the Room, and having ſhown themſelves to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, the Chancellor ſpake to this effect.
<q>Sir, your good Subjects deſire you may be crowned, as righteous and lawfull Heir of the Crown of this Kingdom, that you would maintain the preſent profeſſed Religion the Nationall Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and Solemn League and Covenant. That you would gratiouſly be pleaſed to receive them under your protection, to govern them according to law, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend them in their rights and priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:204891:37"/>by your Royal power, they offering themſelves in humble manner to your Majeſty with their vowes to beſtow Land, Life &amp; what elſe is in their power for the maintenance of Religion, for the ſafety of your Majeſties ſacred perſon, and maintenance of your Crown, which they entreat your Majeſty to accept, and pray Almighty God that for many years you may enjoy the ſame.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The King to this made Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>I do eſteem the affections of my good people more then the <hi>Crowns</hi> of many Kingdomes, &amp; ſhall be ready by Gods aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance to beſtow my life in their Defence; wiſhing to live no longer then I may ſee Religion and the Kingdom flouriſh in all happineſs.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This ceremony performed, the Nobles and Commiſſioners of Baroneys and Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs accompanied his Majeſty to the Church of <hi>Scone;</hi> the Spurs being carried before him by the Earl of <hi>Eglinton,</hi> the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:204891:38"/>ſword by the Earl <hi>Rothes,</hi> the ſcepter by the Earls of <hi>Craford</hi> &amp; <hi>Lindſey;</hi> the Crown by the Marqueſs of <hi>Argyle;</hi> immediatly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Kings Majeſty; who followed ſupported by the Conſtable &amp; Marſhall; his train born up by the Lords <hi>Montgomery, Ereskin, Newbottle,</hi> and <hi>Machelene;</hi> under a Canopy of crimſon Velvet, ſupported by the Lords <hi>Drummond, Carnegie, Ramſey, Iohnſon, Brechin,</hi> and <hi>Yſter;</hi> which ſix were ſupported by ſix Noble men's ſons.</p>
            <p>Thus they went to the Church, which being fitted for the purpoſe, the Honours were laid upon a table provided for them, and his Majeſty aſcended on a ſtage 24. foot ſquare, &amp; ſeated himſelfe in a Chair to heare the ſermon; upon this ſtage there was another ſmaller ſtage erected whereon the Throne ſtood. His Majeſty being ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on the Chair, a Sermon was preached by <hi>Robert Douglas</hi> moderater of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of the General aſſembly: Sermon being ended, the National Covenant of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the ſolemn League and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant were diſtinctly read, which done,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:204891:38"/>the Oath was miniſtred in theſe Words.</p>
            <p>
               <q>I <hi>CHARLES</hi> King of <hi>Britain, Frence</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> doe aſſure and declare by my Solemn Oath, in the preſence of Amighty God the Searcher of all hearts, my allowance and approbation of the Nationall Covenant, and of the ſolemn League and Covenant; and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully Oblige my ſelfe to proſecute the ends thereof in my ſtation and calling; and that I for my ſelfe &amp; ſucceſſurs ſhall conſent &amp; agree to all acts of Parliaments enjoyning the Nationall Covenant, and the ſolemn League and Covenant: and fully eſtabliſh Presbyterian Government, the Directory of Worſhip, Confeſſion of Faith, and Catechiſmes in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> as they are approved by the General aſſemblies of this <hi>Kirk,</hi> and Parliament of this Kingdome, and that I ſhall give my Royall aſſent to acts &amp; Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of this Parliament paſſed, or to be paſſed, enjoyning the ſame in my other Dominions. And that I ſhall obſerve theſe in mine own practice &amp; Family, &amp; ſhall
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:204891:39"/>never make oppoſition to any of thoſe, or endeavour any change thereof.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The King having thus ſolemnly ſworn, the Nationall covenant, the ſolemn League and Covenant, with the oath ſubjoined, was by him under written in the preſence of them all; which done, the King aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the other Stage, and ſat down in the Throne. Then the Lords great Conſtable and Marſhall went to the four corners of the Stage, <hi>Lyon</hi> king at Arms going before them, who ſpake theſe words to the people, <hi>Sirs, I do preſent unto you the King,</hi> CHARLES, <hi>the Rightfull and undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Heir of the Crown &amp; Dignitie of this Realm; this day is by the Parliament of this Kingdom appointed for his Coronation. And are you not willing to have him for your King, and become ſubject to his commandements?</hi> At this Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the King ſtood up, and ſhewed himſelfe to the people round about, who expreſſed their conſent by their joyfull acclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, crying, <hi>God ſave King</hi> CHARLES <hi>the</hi> Second.</p>
            <p>Then his Majeſty deſcended from his
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:204891:39"/>Throne into the Chair, where he ſat to hear the Sermon, of whom the Miniſter accompanied with ſome others of his tribe, demand if he were willing to take the Coronation Oath, according as it was contained in the eight Act of the firſt Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of King <hi>James</hi> the VI. his Royall Grandfather. The King anſwered he was moſt willing. Then was the oath read a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loud by <hi>Lyon</hi> king at Armes, in theſe words.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Becauſe that the increaſe of Virtue, &amp; ſuppreſſing Idolatry craveth that the <hi>Prince</hi> and people be of one perfect Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, which of GOD'S mercy is now preſently profeſſed within this Realm: Therefore it is ſtatuted and ordained by our Soveraigne Lord, the Lord Regent, and three Eſtates of this preſent <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> that all Kings, Princes, and Magiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates whatſoever, holding their place, which hereafter at any time ſhall happen to reign &amp; bear rule over this Realm, at the time of their Coronation, and receit of their Princely Authority make their faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:204891:40"/>promiſe in the preſence of the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall God. That enduring the whole courſe of their lives, they ſhall ſerve the ſame Eternall God, to the utmoſt of their power, according as he hath required in his moſt holy Word, revealed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the new and old Teſtaments, &amp; according to the ſame words ſhall main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the true Religion of Chriſt Jeſus, the preaching of his holy Word, and the due and right miniſtration of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, now received and preached with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this Realm, and ſhall aboliſh &amp; gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand all falſe Religions contrary to the ſame, and ſhall rule the people commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to their charge according to the will &amp; command of God revealed in his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Word, and according to the lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Laws and Conſtitutions received in this Realm, no wayes repugnant to the ſaid Word of the Eternal GOD, and ſhall procure to the utmoſt of their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, to the <hi>Kirk</hi> of GOD, &amp; whole Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian people, true and perfect peace in time coming: The rights and rents, with
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:204891:40"/>all juſt Priviledges of the Crown of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> to preſerve and keep inviolated, neither ſhall they transfer or alienate the the ſame. They ſhall forbid and repreſs all in all eſtates and Degrees, Leaſes, Oppreſſion, and all kind of Wrong in all Judgement. They ſhall command and procure that Juſtice and Equity be kept to all Creatures without excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as the Lord and Father of mercies be merciful unto them. And out of their Lands and Empire they ſhall be careful to root out all Hereticks and enemies to the true worſhip of God, that ſhall be convict by the true <hi>Kirk</hi> of GOD of the aforeſaid Crimes; &amp; that he ſhall faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully affirm the things above written by the ſolemn Oath.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The Oath thus read, the Miniſter ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred it to the King, who kneeling &amp; hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up his right hand, ſware thus: By the Eternal and Almighty GOD who liveth and reigneth for ever, I ſhall obſerve and keep all that is contained in this Oath.</p>
            <p>Then was the King diſrobed by the Lo. Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlain
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:204891:41"/>berlain of the Princely Robe, with which he entred the Church, and veſted with his Royal Robes; and ſo ſupported as before, he removed to the Chair placed on the North ſide of the <hi>Kirk,</hi> whither the ſword was firſt brought from the table by Sir <hi>William Cockburn</hi> of <hi>Langtown</hi> Gentleman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſher, who delivers it to the great Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlain, and he making a ſhort ſpeech, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livers it to his Majeſty, by whom it was given into the great Conſtable's hands and by him girt to the King's ſide.</p>
            <p>Then his Majeſty ſitting down in the Chair, the ſpurs are put on him by the Earl Marſhall. After which <hi>Archibald</hi> Marqueſſe of <hi>Argyle</hi> takes the Crown into his hands, and after a ſhort prayer made by the Miniſter, put it upon his Majeſties head,</p>
            <p>which done, <hi>Lyon</hi> King at Arms, the great Conſtable ſtanding by him, called the Nobility one by one, who came all, and kneeling, and touching the Crown upon the Kings head with their right hand, Swore thus: <hi>By the Eternall and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:204891:41"/>God, who liveth and raigneth for ever, I ſhall ſupport thee to the uttermoſt.</hi> The obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory Oath was likewiſe read to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, they holding up their hands.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, after the Earls of <hi>Craford</hi> &amp; <hi>Lind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey</hi> had deliver'd his <hi>Majeſty</hi> the Scepter, he returned again to the Stage, where he was inſtalled in the Throne by the Marqueſs of <hi>Argyle;</hi> and after a ſhort exhortation of Maſter <hi>Robert Douglaſs,</hi> returned to the Pallas with the Crown upon his head in the ſame manner as he came.</p>
            <p>This is a full relation of the ceremonies performed at his Majeſties Coronation at <hi>Scone,</hi> on the firſt of <hi>January</hi> 1650, which I the rather fully inſert, becauſe the World may take notice of thoſe hard Covenant Pills which the <hi>Kirk</hi>-men made him ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</p>
            <p>Preſently after the coronation, the King &amp; Nobles return'd in a moſt ſolemn man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to S. <hi>Iohns</hi> town; the Kings Majeſty having a guard to attend him, confiſting of moſt Lords and Gentlemens ſons, and the Lord <hi>Lorne</hi> ſon to the Marqueſſe of
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:204891:42"/>
               <hi>Argyle</hi> was made Captaine of it.</p>
            <p>And now his Majeſty intends with all poſſible ſpeed the raiſing of an Army (for the <hi>Scots</hi> having had all this while no Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my on the other ſide the <hi>Fife</hi> to oppoſe the <hi>Engliſh</hi> proceedings, they had reduc'd all places there under their force, even <hi>Eden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough</hi> Caſtle it ſelfe) to which effect he orders his Standard to be ſet up at <hi>Aber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deen,</hi> himſelfe nobly reſolving to be <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raliſſimo</hi> of this army; the other general commands were now given as well to the Royalliſts as Presbyterians; For Duke <hi>Hamilton</hi> was made Lieut. General of the Army, and <hi>Middleton</hi> Lieut. General of the Horſe.</p>
            <p>The Levies came in a pace to the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Randezvouze, which was appointed on the <hi>Eaſt</hi> part of <hi>Fife,</hi> whither his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty in perſon went to encourage his Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, whom he found both increaſing in their numbers, and much rejoyced at his preſence.</p>
            <p>The Parliament of <hi>Scotland,</hi> which had adjourned to give time for his Majeſties
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:204891:42"/>nation; being met again, there were ſtrong endeavors of the King, that ſeveral Lords of the Royal party ſhould be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to their ſeats in Parliament; but, the aſſemblies of the <hi>Kirk</hi> at <hi>Sterling</hi> &amp; <hi>Aber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deen</hi> as ſtrongly oppoſe it, and ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves diſcontented both at this propoſal, and likewiſe at the new levies, in regard they were there admitted to commands in the Army: as they now deſired to have place in Parliament; yet notwithſtanding theſe murmurings, they were upon their reconciliation to the Church; and paſſing the ſtool of Repentance, re-admitted to their places in Parliament; ſuch were Duke <hi>Hamilton,</hi> the Marqueſs of <hi>Huntley,</hi> the Earls of <hi>Calendare, Crawford,</hi> &amp; others.</p>
            <p>But ſtil not only many of the Miniſters (notwithſtanding there was a ſelect Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee appointed to examine and punniſh ſuch perſons who any way confronted and murmured againſt any deſigns or acts of State) rail againſt theſe proceedings; but ſome of the Nobles too are diſcontented, inſomuch that the Earl of <hi>Sutherland</hi> utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:204891:43"/>refuſed to concur with them, and if he could poſſibly, would have oppoſed them by force.</p>
            <p>And indeed very many or moſt of the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> were diſcontented; For the Royal party by the Admiſſion of thoſe Lords and others, was grown ſtronger then the <hi>Kirk's,</hi> and now bore all the ſway; which made the proud Marqueſſe <hi>Argyle</hi> and other Covenantier Lords, murmur at: being afraid leaſt in time they ſhould wholly be laid aſide, they having already ſeen one of their party begun with; for the Earl of <hi>Louden</hi> who cuſtomarily had the Lord Chancellorſhip of the Kingdome, was removed from his place, and the Lord <hi>Burleigh</hi> conſtituted Chancellor in his ſtead.</p>
            <p>Yet on the Covenanters ſide there want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not ſome Miniſters, ſuch were Mr. <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Bert Douglaſs,</hi> and Mr. <hi>David Dicks,</hi> who endeavoured to beget a right underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in both parties, that theſe ſparks of diſcontent might not at laſt burſt out into a flame, as 'twas very much feared
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:204891:43"/>they would; but rather that in this time of danger they might lay a ſide all animoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and unite together againſt the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Enemy, who elſe would be the Ruine of them both.</p>
            <p>And now his Maieſty to keep a coreſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency abroad, ſends the Earl of <hi>Dumferlin</hi> Ambaſſador to the <hi>States</hi> of <hi>Holland,</hi> he had likewiſe at the ſame time ſeveral other Ambaſſadors oragents abroad in the courts of ſeveral Princes, to require aid; but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver found more, then what fair and ſugar'd promiſes produced</p>
            <p>And about this time, Sir <hi>Henry Hide,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſent ouer to <hi>England</hi> from <hi>Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> (whither he had been ſent as Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor from his Majeſty to the <hi>Grand Seigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or</hi>) by Sir <hi>Thomas Bendyſh</hi> his means, who was then Ambaſſador for the republick in <hi>England</hi> (but yet deem'd a perſon of more loyalty to his Prince, then to have ſent his Ambaſſador to be murder'd, if he could have avoided it) after ſomewhat a formall tryall, he ſuffered death on a Scaffold be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Royal Exchange in <hi>London,</hi> for
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:204891:44"/>having taken Commiſſions from his So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign.</p>
            <p>And not long after him Captain <hi>Brown-Buſhell,</hi> who though he had formerly been an enemy to his Majeſties father, yet now ſuffer'd death upon the Tower-hill <hi>London,</hi> for having done ſome ſignal ſervices by ſea for his preſent Majeſty.</p>
            <p>But to return to the Kings affairs in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> where the ſpecial buſineſſes in hand were, the compleating the Levies to 15000 foot, and 6000 horſe, which went on a pace; and the fortifying the town of <hi>Ster<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> which his Majeſty intended for the place of his chief reſidence; to the haſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the which his Majeſty went often in Progreſs to view the Works, &amp; encourage the Pioneers.</p>
            <p>And time it was to haſten thoſe Works, for the Engliſh drew every day nigher and nigher towards them having already taken the Fort of <hi>Blackneſs,</hi> which lay btween <hi>Sterling</hi> and <hi>Edenbrough;</hi> which was never theleſs not accounted ſo great a loſs, as the ſurprizſal of the Earl of <hi>Eglinton</hi> and one
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:204891:44"/>of his Sons by a party of <hi>Engliſh</hi> horſe at <hi>Dumbarton;</hi> for this Earl was a perſon of a great deal of power in that Nation, and his taking very much obſtructed the going for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of the Levies.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Sterling</hi> being almoſt fortified ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently, his Majeſty removed his Court hither; where whilſt he was, his birth day being the 29 of <hi>May,</hi> was kept through <hi>Scotland,</hi> with ſuch tokens of joy as are uſuall upon ſuch occaſions; but the town of <hi>Dundee</hi> exceeded all the reſt, for beſides their equal expreſſions of joy, they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented his Majeſty with a rich Tent, ſix pieces of Field Ordinance, and ſet out a Regiment of horſe towards his aſſiſtance at their own charge.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Sterling</hi> likewiſe were the head Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters kept; moſt of the <hi>Scotch</hi> Army Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering about it, whither <hi>Middleton</hi>'s levies from the North being come, and amoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to about 8000 men, it came to be a diſpute whether theſe ſhould be a diſtinct Army by themſelves, or be joined with <hi>Leſley's</hi> Southern levies; but at length it
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:204891:45"/>was thought moſt convenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to joyn them: and his Majeſty to prevent thoſe animoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which might ariſe between <hi>Middleton</hi> and <hi>Leſley</hi> for the General-ſhip, tooke up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on himſelfe the Command of the whole.</p>
            <p>From hence his Majeſty ſent a meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to the Parliamet ſtill ſitting at S. <hi>John<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton's</hi> with theſe demands.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Act about the Claſſis of malignants ſhould be revok'd &amp; diſannul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l'd, and that an Act paſs for its repeal.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That there may be no more any mention of the name of malignants among them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That Duke <hi>Hamilton,</hi> the Earls of <hi>Seaforth,</hi> and <hi>Callendare,</hi> &amp;c. might have as full comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in the Army as any others.</p>
            <p>The demands were ſtrongly debated <hi>pro &amp; con</hi> in the Parliament; the Marqueſs of <hi>Argyle</hi> and others of the Covenanted ſtrain, endeavouring by all means poſſible to oppoſe them; yet at length, though with much difficulty, they were carried in the affirmative, it being urged by the more mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate ſort too, that the granting of theſe
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:204891:45"/>would be the only way to take away all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimoſities, between thoſe parties which they intended to unite.</p>
            <p>The Parliament having granted theſe things to his Majeſty, &amp; given large com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions &amp; inſtructions for the compleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Levies, about the begining of <hi>Iune</hi> diſſolved, leaving all things (in rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to civil and inteſtine diſtempers in a calm &amp; quiet) all parties ſeeming to be pleaſed, and their actions united towards the oppoſing of their common Enemy <hi>Cromwell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whilſt theſe things were thus tranſact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in <hi>Scotland,</hi> a great and terrible plot was diſcovered againſt the <hi>Juncto</hi> then ruling in <hi>England,</hi> and their government in aſſiſtance of his Majeſty to his juſt Rights. This deſign was chiefly laid by thoſe Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians who had been ſuch dire Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents of his Majeſty's bleſſed father of happy (yet unhappy) memory, <hi>viz</hi> the greateſt part Presbyterian Miniſters, who had moſt of them formerly belcht out ſuch fire-brands from their Pulpits as had ſet
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:204891:46"/>both Church and State in a combuſtion; but now whether out of a reall ſence of their Errour (which I have the charity to believe it was) they had a deſire to return to their Allegiance to his Son their law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and native Sovereign; or out of an am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, by joining with their <hi>Scotiſh</hi> Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren (which I am loath to judge) to get the Power again into their hands, which was ſnatch'd from them by the Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendant <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army, and the <hi>Juncto</hi> of Sectaries in <hi>England,</hi> they had laid a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne to raiſe both a contribution of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; and levy men for his Majeſty's aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance here; but their Plot was betrayed by the intercepting of Letters in a ſhip forced by foul weather into <hi>Ayre</hi> in <hi>Scotland;</hi> but bound with proviſions for the Iſle of <hi>Man,</hi> whereupon the chief undertakers in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> were apprehended, <hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>Cook,</hi> Mr. <hi>Gibbons,</hi> Mr. <hi>Chriſtopher Love,</hi> Mr. <hi>Jen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins,</hi> D. <hi>Drake</hi> and others, of which two. <hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>Gibbons</hi> and Mr. <hi>Love</hi> was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by a high Court of Juſtice; and ſuffered death on the Tower hill, for that
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:204891:46"/>cauſe againſt which they had once ſo ſtrongly declar'd.</p>
            <p>But to return again to the cheif Scene in <hi>Scotland.</hi> The <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army had long had a deſire to bring the <hi>Scots</hi> to a field battel, which his Majeſty upon ſundry good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons &amp; ſerious advice declin'd; ſo <hi>Cromwell</hi> endeavoured to the utmoſt of his power to force them to it, &amp; therefore ſeveral times fac'd his Majeſty's Army which lay en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camped at <hi>Torwood,</hi> within three miles of <hi>Sterling,</hi> but could not yet draw them out of their trenches, the chief reaſon being imagin'd to proceed from their ſtay for <hi>Argyle, Huntley,</hi> and <hi>Seaforth,</hi> who were gon into their ſeveral Territories to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat the King's Levies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cromwell</hi> perceiving that he could not draw the <hi>Scots</hi> to a field-battel, upon a ſudden draws off his Army, and tranſports fixteen hundred Foot; and foure Troopes of Horſe over unto <hi>Fife</hi> on ſuch a ſudden, that it ſtartled his Majeſties whole Army; And <hi>Cromwell</hi> with an unparallel'd expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, faces again the Royal Army with a reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:204891:47"/>to fall upon their <hi>rear</hi> if they ſhould attempt a motion thetherwards; but they offered not to ſtir, for already order had been given to Sir <hi>Iohn Brown</hi> Governour of <hi>Sterling</hi> to march with four thouſand Horſe and Foot to drive out that party of <hi>Cromwell's</hi> which were already landed in <hi>Fife;</hi> of which, intelligence being brought <hi>Lambart</hi> and <hi>Okye</hi> with two Regiments of Horſe and two of Foot, are with all poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble haſte wafted over to reinforce the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty already there; with which additionall ſupply of men they routed Sir <hi>Iohn Brown,</hi> who expected none but the firſt landed party, taking himſelf and ſeveral other officers of quality priſoners, and killing two thouſand upon the place, and taking near 1200. priſoners: and ſhortly after <hi>Cromwell</hi> tranſports moſt of his Army over the <hi>Fife,</hi> and reſolving to ſtop the paſſage which the <hi>Scots</hi> had over by <hi>Sterling,</hi> mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to S. <hi>Iohnſtons</hi> and takes it almoſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſummons.</p>
            <p>Hs Majeſty ſeeing the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army was advanced ſo far Northward, thought it
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:204891:47"/>in vain to attempt the forcing them back; &amp; knowing that the <hi>Scots</hi> naturally fights better in anothers then in their own Conn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, reſolves toadvanc with all poſſible ſp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eed into <hi>England,</hi> where he yet hoped, not withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding the diſcovery of the deſign, to find ſome Loyal ſouls to joyn with him for the Recovery of his right and Kingdomes.</p>
            <p>Many were there who oppoſed this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of his Majeſty, and among thoſe Duke <hi>Hamilton</hi> was one of the chiefeſt; whoſe diſlike may ſufficiently appear by his Letter to Mr. <hi>Crofts</hi> after their Advance to this effect;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We are now laughing,</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>at the rediculouſneſs of our preſent State; We have quit</hi> Scotland <hi>being ſcarce able to maintain it: and yet we graſp at all, and nothing but all will ſatisfie us, or to loſe all. I confeſs I cannot tell whether our hopes or fears are greateſt? but we have one ſtout argument Deſpair: for we muſt now either ſtoutely fight or dye: all the Rogues have left us, I ſhall not ſay whether out of fear or diſloyalty; but all now with his Majeſty are ſuch as will not diſpute his Commands.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:204891:48"/>
            <p>But notwithſtanding his diſlike: &amp; his &amp; other oppoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, yet the Kings reſove takes place, and on <hi>July</hi> the 31. 1651. his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Army began to advance from <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood</hi> near <hi>Sterling</hi> ſteering their courſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rirectly for <hi>England,</hi> which they entred ſix dayes after by way of <hi>Carliſle;</hi> This march of the Royall Army made <hi>Cromwell</hi> with the greateſt part of his forces immediately recroſſe the <hi>Frith,</hi> and forth with ſend Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor General <hi>Lambert</hi> with a ſelect party of Horſe and Dragoons to fall upon the Rear of his Majeſties Army, whilſt they hop'd that Major General <hi>Harriſon,</hi> then lying neer the borders with about three thouſand Horſe and Dragoons, would attach them in the Front; ſhortly after himſelfe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed with the reſt of the Army which could be ſpar'd, amounting to about eight compleat Regiments of Foot, and two of Horſe.</p>
            <p>But then this greater preparation is made againſt him in <hi>England,</hi> for the <hi>Juncto</hi> then fitting at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> not onely interdicted all aid or aſſiſtance either of
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:204891:48"/>men or moneys, to be given to his Majeſty under the penalty of High Treaſon; but alſo in all or moſt of the Countrys had cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a numerous force to be raiſed, the <hi>Church-Militia</hi> of the City of <hi>London</hi> being likewiſe ſent out againſt him; and for the preſent impeading of his march, two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand of the Country-<hi>Militia</hi> of <hi>Stafford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> and four thouſand out of <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> and <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> under the command of Col. <hi>Birch,</hi> had joyned with <hi>Harriſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But be ſides all this, many of the Royal Army had in their march deſerted their co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, &amp; neer a fourth part of the army was wanting; but theſe were moſt of them ſuch, as were not very well affected to the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, nor cauſe they went about; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there was but little miſs of them, for the reſt of the Army marched on chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and continued to the utmoſt puſh ſtedfaſt and loyal; &amp; were ſo contentedly obedient to all Military Diſcipline, that 'tis believ'd that in al their march through all that part of <hi>England</hi> they hardly took the value of ſix pence forcibly.</p>
            <pb n="82" facs="tcp:204891:49"/>
            <p>But notwithſtanding this unwonted evility of the <hi>Scottſh</hi> Army, and his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties earneſt invitations, the Country came very ſlowly in, whether beſotted, dulled and contented with that ſlavery they then lay under, or over-aw'd by an armed power, I cannot tell, but ſuch was their backwardneſs, that few or none be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Lord <hi>Howard</hi> of <hi>Eſtriche's</hi> ſon with a Troop of Horſe came to him, during his long tedious march through <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor did his Majeſty with his Army take that courſe which was expected by moſt he ſhould; for the great fear of his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and greateſt hopes of his Friends were, that he would march directly for <hi>London,</hi> but he contrary to their <hi>expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> being come into <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> ſtruck off at <hi>Warrington,</hi> either doubting the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize for <hi>London</hi> too hazardous, or out of the hopes had of the Forces, it was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected Major General <hi>Maſſey</hi> might raiſe in <hi>Gloſterſhire</hi> which was the then general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly voagu'd reaſon.</p>
            <p>But before his Majeſty could paſs over <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rington</hi>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:204891:49"/>Bridge, he had occaſion to try the ſtoutneſs of his Souldiers; for there <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon</hi> was reſolved if poſſible to ſtop him, and was endeavouring to that purpoſe to have broken down the Bridge; but his Majeſties forces by a ſwift march from <hi>Charley,</hi> prevented his deſign, and forced him to an engagement, The diſpute was ſomewhat hot and long, but at length his Majeſty got the better; for he gained a free paſſage over the Bridge, though with the loſs of ſome men.</p>
            <p>This Bridge gained, his Majeſty march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on towards the <hi>Weſt,</hi> without any op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition: &amp; indeed with as little aſſiſtance or increaſe of numbers: yet being all along as he came proclaimed King of <hi>Great Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> by an <hi>Engliſh</hi>-man whom he had created King at Armes.</p>
            <p>Being come to <hi>Tong-Norton,</hi> his Majeſty ſent a Trumpet with his Royall ſummons to Colonell <hi>Mackworth</hi> Governour of <hi>Shrewsbury,</hi> which ran thus.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:204891:50"/>
                  <head>C. R. Col. <hi>MACKWORTH,</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>BEing Deſirous to attempt all fair wayes for the recovery of our own, before we proceed to force and extremity, and (where the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie is with Subjects) accounting that a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble victory which is obtained without effuſion of bloud, and where the hearts that of right belong to us are gained as well as their ſtrengths. We do hereby ſummon you to ſurrender unto us our Town, with the Caſtle of</hi> Shrewsbury <hi>as in du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Allegiance by the Laws of God and the Land you are bound to doe, thereby not onely preventing the miſchief which you may otherwiſe draw upon your ſelf and that place, but alſo opening the foredoore to peace and quietneſs, and the enjoyment of every one both King and people, that which pertains to them under cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and known Laws, the end for which we are come. Given at our </hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Campe of</hi> Tong-Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton
<date>
                           <hi>this</hi> 20. Auguſt 1651.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This ſummons was accompanyed with a Letter from his Majeſty exhorting him as he was a Gentleman to return to his du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:204891:50"/>and Alleigance, upon promiſes of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and reward.</p>
            <p>To both which Col. <hi>Mackworth</hi> return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed anſwer thus;</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>For the Commander in Chief of the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Army.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>BY <hi>your Trumpeter I received two Papers, the one containing a propoſition, and the other a direct Summons for the Rendition of the Town and Caſtle of</hi> Shrewsbury, <hi>the Cuſtody whereof I have recieved by Authority of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament; and if you believe me a Gentleman (as you ſay you do) you may believe I will be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to my truſt, to the violation whereof neither Allurements can perſwade me, nor threatnings offorce; eſpetially when but paper ones compell me? what principles I am judged to be of, I know not; but I hope they are ſuch as ſhall ever declare me honest, and no way differing herein (as I know) from thoſe engaged in the ſame em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment with me; who ſhould they deſert that cauſe they are embarqued in, I reſolve to be
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:204891:51"/>found as I am, unmoveable,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>The faithfull Servant of the Commonwealth of <hi>England. H. Mackworth.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Thus flat a denyall did his Majeſties Royal ſummons receive here; nor did his Commands to Sir <hi>Thomas Middleton</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of <hi>Chirk</hi> Caſtle in <hi>Flintſhire,</hi> for the levying of men for his ſervice, find better ſucceſs.</p>
            <p>But from hence his Majeſty directs his courſe for <hi>Worceſter,</hi> where he arrives on the twenty ſecond of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> and notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſome reſiſtance made by the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments ſouldiers, quickly enters by the help of the towns men, who joyfully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to their Aleigance &amp; Duty; here 'twas again ſolemnly debated whether they ſhould remain here or march for <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> and was at length concluded that in regard of the long and tedious marches that the Souldiery had had, it would be much better to tarry hear: that after ſome
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:204891:51"/>refreſhment they might be able with more vigor and courage to endure the brunt.</p>
            <p>The Earl of <hi>Derby</hi> who had ſome few dayes before his Majeſties Arrivall at <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester,</hi> brought him a ſupply of two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and fifty foot and ſixty Horſe, which he had brought with him out of the Iſle of <hi>Man,</hi> and was returned back into <hi>Lanca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> out of hopes that by his influence upon that County he might get a more nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous Force there, having got together a conſiderable party, was routed by Col. <hi>Lilburn,</hi> who was there with a party to watch his motions; and was firſt engag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Earl, out of a deſign he had to hinder <hi>Lilburn</hi>'s joyning with a Regiment of <hi>Cromwells;</hi> which was ſent for the ſame purpoſe towards <hi>Manchester,</hi> but the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagers themſelves were defeated; &amp; moſt of the Earls chief Commanders and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen of note with him taken priſoners, ſuch were the Lord <hi>Witherington,</hi> Sir <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Tilſly,</hi> Sir <hi>William Throgmorton,</hi> Col. <hi>Boynton,</hi> and ſundry others.</p>
            <p>His Majeſty being now at <hi>Worcester</hi> and
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:204891:52"/>ſolving there to ſtay and endure the utmoſt brunt, all preparations poſſible are made, for the fortifying the place and gaining all advantages poſſible; to which purpoſe a Line and ſeveral Mounts were quickly rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the Pioneers, and all paſſes about the Town and towards it ſecured.</p>
            <p>But Major General <hi>Lambert</hi> on the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulick's ſide, ſending ſuddenly a party of Horſe to diſcover the difficulty of the paſſe at <hi>Upton,</hi> (where Major General <hi>Maſſey</hi> (for his Majeſty) lay with a party about 300. Horſe and Dragoons) thoſe deſperate fellows being not above fifty in number, adventured over upon one piece of Timber, which had been careleſly left, from arch to arch.</p>
            <p>And though <hi>Maſſey's</hi> men took the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larm, yet was <hi>Lambert</hi> ſo quick in ſending over relief to his Souldiers (whom the Royal party had beleagured in a Church) that the paſs was clearly gain'd, &amp; Major General <hi>Maſſey</hi> forced to retreat (though as honourably as ever man did) for him ſelf ſtill brought up the, Rear in which
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:204891:52"/>ſervice (though his Horſe was ſlain under him, and himſelfe ſhot in the arm) yet he got off with a very inconſiderable loſs.</p>
            <p>And now <hi>Cromwells</hi> Army began to joyn with all thoſe parties, which had conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red there to ruine his Majeſty, whom they accounted already like a bird in a Cage; for this Royall Army conſiſting (at the moſt) of not above 10000 fighting men, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Army that then beleagur'd and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſſed them, was one of the greateſt that had (during the whole time of the late War) been rayſed in <hi>England,</hi> amount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (according to common computation (to ſome 50. or 60. thouſand Horſe and Foot, ſo that (as I have been well inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) this Army, though in a more ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied ſtrain brag'd and inſulted more over his Majeſty, then the <hi>French</hi> Army at <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gincourt</hi> did over the thrice Illuſtrious King <hi>Henry</hi> 5. Yet notwithſtanding their aſſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of making him their prize: it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God (though not to give him the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs that <hi>Henry</hi> the 5. had) yet to deliver him out of their bloud thirſty hands.</p>
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:204891:53"/>
            <p>When I ſpeak of the Armies inſulting o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his Majeſties miſery; I hope the <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> wil underſtand me in the generality; for though many and perhaps the major part were glad of theſe his ſtraits; yet many no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and candid loyal ſouls there were, whom nothing but a tyrannicall impulſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on could have forced to have born Armes againſt their lawfull Soveraign. It being well known that thouſands were forced out of ſeveral Countreys to ſerve againſt their wills, &amp; them too put into the brunt of the battle, as though deſtined for the ſlaughter.</p>
            <p>But for all theſe numerous forces which encompaſſed the Royal Army, they were chearfull &amp; reſolved to ſell their lives at a noble rate, his Majeſty by the Example of his undaunted courage, principally en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courageing them: ſo that many vigorous ſallies were made upon their Enemies, &amp; though their ſupernumeraries forc't them to a retreat, yet was it very ſeldom and never ignobly.</p>
            <p>But now the fatal day draws nigh, a day
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:204891:53"/>before ſo eminently auſpitious to <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi> and as unfortunate to the <hi>Scots, viz.</hi> the third day of <hi>September.</hi> The fight was occaſioned thus, <hi>Cromwell, Fleetwood,</hi> &amp; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the <hi>Republick</hi> party, had, after the gaining the paſs at <hi>Upton,</hi> endeavoured to make themſelves a clear paſſage to the City, that their Army might joyn in the Leagure, to which end and purpoſe they ordered the making of two Bridges, the one over the <hi>Severn,</hi> the other over <hi>Thame,</hi> over the laſt of which paſſes Lievt. Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <hi>Fleetwood</hi> went to attach the <hi>West</hi> ſide of the Town, which ſo allarm'd the Royall Army (who then lay within their Leagure at St. <hi>Jones</hi>) that to prevent their drawing nigher, they ſalyed out with the greateſt part of their Horſe and Foot and a ſtiff en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter there was, till over powred by numbers more then by valor, which they demonſtrated to the utmoſt of mens ſtrength, they were forced to retire again into the Leagure, leaving more of their Enemies dead bodies in the field then of their own.</p>
            <pb n="92" facs="tcp:204891:54"/>
            <p>But whilſt the encounter was on the <hi>Weſt</hi> ſide of the Town. <hi>Cromwell</hi> having paſs't his Army over <hi>Severn,</hi> he march't direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Town on that ſide, whereupon his Majeſty in perſon, and in the head of the Horſe, ſallied out upon him, and that with ſo much valour and courage, that <hi>Cromwel's</hi> own life-guard, and the beſt of his old Souldiers, who were thought al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt invincible) were forc't to retire, 'till ſeconded by thoſe numerous ſupplies of freſh Souldiers, who ſerved only like the <hi>Turkiſh Aſapi,</hi> to blunt the Royal ſwords, ſo that their wearied arms no longer able to hold out, were forced to retreat, and at Length (notwithſtanding the generous ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of his Majeſty who performed things worth wonder) to a diſorderly flight, and notwithſtanding his Majeſties earneſt endeavours (in which he had his horſe twice ſhot under him) to bring them again to a rally, yet it proved fruitleſs, for the <hi>Cromwellian</hi> Army pouring forth their numbers upon them, permitted them not ſo much time, but following them
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:204891:54"/>cloſe at the heels to the Town, towards which they fled, entred pelmel with them.</p>
            <p>And now notwithſtanding their flight, and the danger of their own lives; yet had they ſo much care of their ſoveraign, that the whole cry throughout both Town and Army was nothing elſe but <hi>Save the King, Save the King;</hi> for him they knew it was that the <hi>Junctoes</hi> army chiefly looked after, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed in great danger he was; for notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the earneſt deſires of many of his friends, &amp; particularly Duke <hi>Hamilton,</hi> who preſſed him to have a care of his ſafety, &amp; reſerve his perſon to a more fortunate day; yet his Majeſty was hardly induced to quit the field, nor would he till he ſaw all abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely loſt; for <hi>Cromwell</hi>'s Army having as I ſaid followed the Royaliſts into the Town, and got poſſeſſion of one ſide of it, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by two or three ſtrong aſſaults upon the fort Royal where the <hi>Cheſhire</hi> men (never before found ſo diſloyall to their Prince; &amp; therefore found now their due,) who out of three thouſand men ſacrificed the lives of 1600 to the Ghoſts of thoſe
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:204891:55"/>new Royalliſts which were all put to the ſword in it, it was taken by ſtorm; and now when it was almoſt too late, his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Majeſty thought it high time to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for his ſafety; and ſo with ſome No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and Servants not without a great deal of difficulty, (for how could it be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe where there was ſuch hard ſearch made for him,) he quit the field, and by the moſt unfrequented roades that they could poſſibly find out, rode to the Farme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe of a noble Gentleman on the borders of <hi>Staffordſhire,</hi> where they no ſooner ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived but his Majeſty diſroabed himſelfe of his Princely Ornament &amp; accoutrements; and particularly of a Chain of Gold or ſpannar-ſtring worth three hundred pounds ſterling; the Preſent of a <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh</hi> Lord, which he beſtow'd upon a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of his there preſent: which done for his farther diſguiſe, he proceeded to the cutting of his hair, and the Cote affording neither ſhears nor ſciſſars to perform it, it was by the Lord <hi>Wilmot</hi> cut off with a Knife.</p>
            <pb n="95" facs="tcp:204891:55"/>
            <p>And now every one is commanded to ſhift for himſelfe, &amp; this poor Prince left alone to the ſole protection of the Almighty, he chooſing none but one friend to accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny him, with whom he wandred into a Wood, within four miles (ſay ſome) of <hi>Wolverhampton,</hi> where finding a hollow Oak, he was now content to make it his Pallas; for here he for ſome daies conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelfe, his Friend ſtill towards night going out to provide him ſome refreſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t dureing this his ſolitary confinement.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the Lord <hi>Wilmot</hi> who was commanded with the reſt to ſeeke his fortune, was by chance purſued by ſome Souldiers, but meeting with a Country fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low for merly a Souldier in the old King's Army, he was by him ſecured though ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ſtrangly, for he carries him into a Malt-houſe belonging to Mrs <hi>Jane Lane,</hi> &amp; having no other convenient place to hide him in, clapt him under the Kilne, though there were then ſome fire in it, &amp; the Malt ſmoaking on the top. In the mean time the Souldiers then in purſuit of him, entred
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:204891:56"/>the houſe, and having made about three quarters of an houres ſearch every where elſe, but not at all ſuſpecting the Kilne, where they ſaw the fire they departed, &amp; the Lord <hi>Wilmot</hi> was taken out of the Kilne almoſt ready to faint with the extreamity of the heat.</p>
            <p>The country fellow having thus ſecured this Lord, acquaints Mrs. <hi>Lane</hi> with what he had done, and ſhe extreamly glad of it, gets him to her houſe, where in conference ſhe enquires of the Kings ſafety. The Lord <hi>Wilmot</hi> gives her the former relation of his miſeries and diſtreſs, which forces tears from the tender hearted Gentlewoman, ſhe earneſtly entreats him to take ſome courſe for the finding out of his Majeſtie, and conducting him to her houſe, ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reſolved to venture her life, had ſhe ten thouſand, for the ſaveing of his Royal Majeſties.</p>
            <p>The Lord <hi>Wilmot</hi> glad of ſo happy an opportunity to ſerve his Majeſty, and ſo great a ptobability of ſecureing him, the next night finds him out, &amp; conducts him
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:204891:56"/>from the Royal Oak to the Houſe of Mrs. <hi>Jane Lane,</hi> where after a large condoling of his hard fortune, conſultation was had for a conveniency for his Eſcape beyond ſea, at length it was concluded, that <hi>Briſtoll</hi> would be the moſt convenient place to take ſhipping, That his Majeſty ſhould ride before Mrs. <hi>Lane</hi> by the name of <hi>William,</hi> ſervant to Mr. <hi>Laſtel</hi> her father in Law, who was likewiſe to go with them; &amp; thus it was immediately given out, that Mr. <hi>Laſtel</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Lane</hi> were to take a journey into the <hi>Weſt,</hi> to viſit ſome friends, and ſhortly after they ſet forward.</p>
            <p>In this journey there happned many ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents worthy commemoration, and firſt the Kings Majeſty riding now as a ſervant to one of the faithfulleſt of his ſubjects, in a Livery cloak, though not without that reſpect that durſt be given to him; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines to Mrs. <hi>Lane</hi> that the Cloak wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried him, whereupon ſhe deſires Mr. <hi>Laſtel</hi> to carry it, &amp; long they had not rid ſo, but they met upon the road her Brother in law, who amongſt other queſtions demanded
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:204891:57"/>of her, if her Father muſt carry her mans Cloak, to which ſhe readily anſwered, that it was ſo big that it often endangered the throwing her off the Horſe, and that ſhe had therefore deſir'd him to carry it.</p>
            <p>The next and moſt important accident of all was, that coming into a Town which they were to paſs through, there was a Troop of horſe there to be quartered, drawn up, which at a diſtance cauſed ſome fear, but at length with a reſolution they paſſed on, and the Captain taking them for honeſt Travellers, made his Troop o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to the right and left, and ſo permitted them to paſs.</p>
            <p>Another accident there hapned, which one may ſay was almoſt comical in this Tragedy; Mrs. <hi>Lane</hi> coming into the Inne, leaves his Majeſty under the name of <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am</hi> her ſervant, in the Kitchin, with whom the Maid enters into diſcourſe, ſhe asks him where he was born, and what trade he was; he anſwered at <hi>Brummingham,</hi> &amp; a Naylor's Son; and after a great deal of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſcourſe, the Jack being down, the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:204891:57"/>Maid deſires him to wind it up; which he willingly undertakes, but goes the wrong way about it, and ſomwhat prejudices it; at which the Maid grew angry, asking him where he was bred, and telling him he was the veryeſt clowniſh booby that ever ſhe ſaw in all her life; which railing of hers made his Majeſty notwithſtanding his preſent miſery, go out of the room ſmil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>Mrs. <hi>Lane</hi> notwithſtanding his Majeſty went as her <hi>Servant,</hi> yet had a greater re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect for him before others, pretending him her Tennant's ſon; but on the Road ſhe would alwayes ask what he would have to dinner or ſupper; &amp; what piece of that he liked, which ſhe would always be ſure to get made ready, and give him, he ſtill ſitting at the lower end of the Table.</p>
            <p>But to come to the end of their journey; being arrived at <hi>Briſtol,</hi> they lodged at the houſe of a noble Gentleman there, and Kinſman to Mr. <hi>Laſtles:</hi> the King finding it to be a houſe of great reſort, feigns him ſelfe ſick of an Ague, and ſo keeps his
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:204891:58"/>Chamber all the day, coming down only at nights; but one night coming down, &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſomewhat cold, he craves a glaſs of wine of the Butler, This Butler having before ſerved his Majeſties Father in the Wars, looking earneſtly upon him, ſuſpected him to be the King; ſo eaſily will Majeſty ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, though vail'd in the utmoſt diſguiſes; and thereupon pulling off his Hat, told him very ceremoniouſly, That he might command what wine he pleaſed; of which the King tooke no notice, but drinking of his wine went out: Yet the Butler could not ſatisfie his ſuſpition, but went up to Mr. <hi>Laſtell</hi>'s, and demanded of him how long he had had that ſervant? Whereupon Mr. <hi>Laſtell's</hi> was very angry at his boldneſs in dareing to aske him ſuch a Queſtion, But the Butler ſtill perſiſted, and whiſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing told him, that he believed it was the King: Whereupon Mr. <hi>Laſtell's</hi> ſeeing he was diſcover'd, ſends immediatly up for his Majeſty, whom he acquaints with the Butler's diſcovery of him, with whom the King was ſomwhat angry, in regard he
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:204891:58"/>did not firſt acquaint himſelf with his ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition, it not being impoſſible, but Mr. <hi>Lastles</hi> might not have known him to be the King: but upon pardon asked by the Butler, it was granted him by the King, and he afterwards proved very inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal in his Majeſties conveyance through the Countrey.</p>
            <p>But here at <hi>Bristol;</hi> the chief deſign they had in hand failed them; for though there were a little Bark lay there, judged moſt convenient for the buſineſs; yet the Maſter would for no reward tranſport a ſingle perſon, though he was ſo honeſt as only to deny it, and made no farther ſearch or inquiry concerning the Perſon, which might perhaps have tended to a diſcovery.</p>
            <p>This deſign here failing, his Majeſty deſired to be brought ſome miles weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, to the houſe of a worthy Gentleman, whom he knew to be a truſty friend; where coming, he findes the Gentleman in the Field with his Servants: having diſcovered himſelf to him, he was by him conveyed to a convenient ſtand 'till night, (having
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:204891:59"/>firſt taken leave of his true friends, who had thus far conducted him with the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of their Lives &amp; Eſtates) from whence he was in the dusk conveyed into the houſe, and there carefully concealed for a week, till ſuch time as preparation could be made in ſome <hi>Western</hi> Port of a paſſage for him; but coming afterwards there where it was provided, chancing to dine with a Parliament Colonel then there, he thought it the ſafer to loſe the benefit of that paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, then adventure to imbarque himſelf ſingly, which might breed ſuſpition, &amp; perhaps have been the means after ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny deliverances, to have betrayed him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of his Enemies.</p>
            <p>This paſſage then likewiſe failing him, he returned back to the place from whence he came, &amp; there concealed himſelf three weeks longer, till in the end it being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved on, he by the aſſiſtance of Mr. <hi>Ph.</hi> was convey'd through the moſt by wayes they could imagine, to a Gentlewomans houſe in <hi>Suſſex,</hi> where he lay ſome few daies, til a perſon of true worth &amp; honour
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:204891:59"/>made proviſion of a faithfull maſter, who with a ſmall veſſel wafted him to a ſmall Creeke in <hi>Normandy,</hi> to the great content of the Kings ſacred Majeſty, and all his loyal Subjects, and to the honour of the maſter with due reward, as in time may appear.</p>
            <p>Perhaps the reader may think it tedious that I have given ſo large a relation of his Majeſties eſcape from the fight at <hi>Werceſter;</hi> but it was a work ſo full of wonder &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, and ſo many falſe relations there are abroad, that I could do no leſs then recount all thoſe miſeries and hardſhips which this poor Prince endured for the ſakes of us his Subjects, and more would he willingly have endured, even death it ſelf, to the redeeming of us from the tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and oppreſſion which we then groan'd under.</p>
            <p>But let him that ſhall looke upon the ſeveral paſſages of his, read them over &amp; over, conſider the ſeveral difficulties he paſſed, the many dangers he was in to be betrayed, the countrey being up round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:204891:60"/>the ſumme of mony ſet upon his head, for which many hundreds out of covetouſnes made it their buſineſs to ſearch for him; &amp; they will confeſs ingeniouſly, that God was never ſo merciful to any people, as to us, in delivering his ſacred Majeſty ſo wonderfully out of the hands of his Enemies, who breathed out nothing but his death and deſtruction, that we may yet have hopes to be a happy Nation.</p>
            <p>But let us now returne to give a full ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of this diſmal loſs at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> in which moſt of his Majeſties foot were ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther made a prize, or a ſacrifice to their enemies ſwords; of the horſe there eſcap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed 300. out of the field, but were moſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards either taken or kil'd by the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try people in their flight; three thouſand were judged ſlain in the Field, and about ſeaven thouſand taken priſoners; whereof the chief were, the Earles <hi>Derby, Lauder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale, Cleveland, Shrewsburge,</hi> &amp; the Lord <hi>Wentworth,</hi> and many other noble perſons taken in the purſuit. And the chief of thoſe taken in the battel were, the Earles of
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:204891:60"/>
               <hi>Carnworth and Kelly,</hi> the Lord <hi>Synclare,</hi> Sir <hi>John Packington;</hi> the Major Generals, <hi>mont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gomery</hi> and <hi>Piſcotty;</hi> and the <hi>Virgil</hi> of this Age, that thrice worthy Mr. <hi>Richard Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaw,</hi> Tranſlator of the renowned <hi>Paſter Fido,</hi> and Secretary to his Majeſty. As for the thrice noble Duke <hi>Hamilton,</hi> he was taken, but not overcome; overpowred, but not vanquiſht. For after having made a moſt Heroick reſiſtance, he was reduced under his enemies power, more for want of ſtrength then valour: but death entring in at thoſe wounds which he ſo gallantly received in defence of his Soveraign, ſoon after releaſed him. Major General <hi>Maſſey,</hi> though he eſcaped the field; yet his wounds being deſperate, he was forced to ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der himſelf to the Counteſs of <hi>Stamford,</hi> &amp; was by her Son, the Lord <hi>Grey</hi> of <hi>Grooby,</hi> after the recovery of his wounds, ſent up priſoner to the Parliament, and by them committed to the Tower, from whence he not long after eſcaped, and went to his Majeſty beyond ſea.</p>
            <p>This ſtrange and wonderfull Victory
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:204891:61"/>(as the <hi>Juncto</hi> at <hi>Weſtminster</hi> gave it out to be, though they had ſix to one in the field) made that Sectarian party cock-a-hoop; &amp; to make it the greater, publick days of Thanksgiving are appointed to make God the patronizer of their villanies, murders, tyrannyes and treaſons; and now they boaſt in all their diſcourſes how clearly it might appear that God owned their cauſe, and diſowned their adverſaries.</p>
            <p>I think a modern writer hath ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confuted that commonly received <hi>tenent</hi> of <hi>Politicians,</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">See Modern Policy.</note> 
               <hi>That ſucceſſe denotes actions to be either just or unjust.</hi> I ſhall therefore leave the ſober Reader here to ſatisfie himſelf, &amp; refer it to him, whether ſuch do not juſtly deſerve <hi>Ovid's</hi> wiſh:
<q>
                  <l>— Careat ſucceſſibus opto,</l>
                  <l> Quiſquis ab eventu facta notanda putat.</l>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <l>Let him for ever in ſucceſſe be poor;</l>
                  <l>That thinks it juſtifies his cauſe the more.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb n="107" facs="tcp:204891:61"/>
            <p>But this Nation is ſo highly ſenſible of the injuſtice put upon them by thoſe who pretend ſo much right in their Cauſe, that there's no loyal Subject but will thinke ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to reaſon, that it was not the juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ice of their cauſe, but our own and the Nations ſinnes which cauſed God to raiſe up theſe men as ſcourges both to Prince &amp; People; &amp; to the prince only for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ſake.</p>
            <p>Some I have heard, which out of a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit which I cannot well define, have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to brand his Royal Majeſty with Cowardize in this battel; which from whence it could proceed, unleſs from their own coward nature, which would inſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late another in that of which themſelves are guilty, I cannot imagine; ſince <hi>Cromwell</hi> the greateſt of his Enemies (becauſe the moſt deſirous of his Kingdomes) yet had ſo much of truth in him, as to give a high and noble Character of his valour.</p>
            <p>But to proceed, we have now ſaid enough of this fatall battel, the ſeeming ruine of the Royal Intereſt in <hi>England,</hi> unleſs God
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:204891:62"/>of his mercy be pleaſed to reſtore it for the good, peace and quiet of theſe Nations, ſince without it we cannot hope to enjoy any.</p>
            <p>His ſacred Majeſty being landed in <hi>France</hi> near <hi>Havre de Grace;</hi> from thence with a Noble Lord in his Company, poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed directly for <hi>Roan,</hi> where they ſtayed to alter their diſguiſes, and furniſh them with habits anſwerable to their qualities; his Majeſty from thence having diſpach't Letters to the <hi>French</hi> Court to acquaint his friends there of his ſafe Arrival, which doubtleſs cauſed no little joy in thoſe who were real to him, and almoſt deſpaired e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver again to have ſeen him. The Duke of <hi>Orleans</hi> ſends his own Coach to fetch him, and ſeveral perſons of quality go to meet him; by whom he was attended to <hi>Paris,</hi> and there received with all poſſible expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of joy, lodgings and attendants be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forthwith provided for him in the <hi>Lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ure;</hi> where, at his firſt arrival he was viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Queen his Mother, &amp; the Duke of <hi>Orleans,</hi> who of all perſons in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:204891:62"/>expreſt himſelfe the moſt ready to do him ſervice; and the next day viſits him again, accompanied with his Daughter <hi>Madamoiſelle.</hi> he is likewiſe courted by the Dukes of <hi>Beaufort, Langueville. Guize,</hi> the Marſhall <hi>Thurine,</hi> and many other Peers &amp; Nobles of <hi>France,</hi> who all congratulate his ſafe deliverance.</p>
            <p>And now his Majeſty having loſt all hopes of any furthermeans of attaining his Dominions by force, leads here a retired life; yet living in regard of his high al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance and extraction, in great eſteem with all the <hi>French</hi> Nobility: Inſomuch that notwithſtanding his preſent low conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, there was very great talk of a match to be made up between him &amp; the <hi>Madamoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelle de Orlians,</hi> the richeſt princeſs in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome; yet by ſome means or other it came to no effect, though the Queen of <hi>England</hi> his Mother, was an earneſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moter of it, and alſo the Duke of <hi>York</hi> to <hi>Longuevelle's</hi> Daughter.</p>
            <p>Whilſt theſe things were tranſacting, hapned that lately reconciled Fracture be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:204891:63"/>the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> and Cardinal <hi>Mazarine,</hi> moſt of the Prince of the Bloud ſiding with the firſt; &amp; the King of <hi>France</hi> (who was newly declared of age to ſway the Scpter himſelfe) with the laſt. The cauſe of the quarrel was that extravagant power which <hi>Mazarine</hi> a ſtranger had u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurped in the government of the Kingdome, both depriving the Princes of the bloud of their Right, and oppreſſing the people; whoſe daily murmurings more encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the Princes againſt him: this power he had got into his hands in the Regency of the Queen Mother, whoſe grand Favourite he only was.</p>
            <p>The Princes therefore, though they could not dureing her Regency who ſo much loved him, yet hoped they might effect ſomthing now the King himſelfe is come to govern; to which intent they charge him with ſeveral miſcarriages of State, which the Cardinal defends, &amp; the King alſo enclines to his ſide by the inſtigation of the Queen his Mother; yet nothing but the Cardinals baniſhment will ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:204891:63"/>the Princes, who join the Duke of <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain</hi> to them, then in the ſervice of the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> with an Army of ten thouſand men; ſo that they intend with his aſſiſtance (if they could not obtain their deſires by fair means) to have forc't it.</p>
            <p>Thus theſe differences were arrived to ſuch a height, that nothing but a Civil war was like to enſue; which made his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Majeſty of <hi>England</hi> uſe his utmoſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to compoſe &amp; ſtay this breach be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it came to an utter overflow; to which effect he dayly went to &amp; fro be twixt the King &amp; the Princes; endeavouring to bring them to a reconciliatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, urging by his own example the miſeries and calamities that muſt neceſſarily fall upon every mans head by a Civil War, telling the King that the late example of his Royall Father of happy memory, might be an inducement to him to be at peace with his Subjects, rather then embroil his Kingdomes in a bloudywar, by which though he might for the preſent gaine the better; yet in the end he would ſtil be ſure to have the worſe.</p>
            <pb n="112" facs="tcp:204891:64"/>
            <p>Yet theſe Arguments, and his Majeſties earneſt endeavours for peace and reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, produced nothing, but only contract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an unjuſt <hi>odium</hi> upon him from both parties for his good will; the Princes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving that he counſelled the King againſt them, and the <hi>Cardinal</hi> againſt him: So that he loſt the love of both by endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to mak them love one another; yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the ill ſucceſſe he had, this Noble Prince ſtill purſues his pacifick in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, til ſuch time as he gains a confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence between the King Cardinall &amp; Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; but this proves ineffectuall; For the Princes heightned with the aid they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from the Duke of <hi>Lorain,</hi> inſtead of coming to an accord, only exaſperate dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences.</p>
            <p>Yet his Sacred Majeſty ceaſes not, but endeavours to bring them yet to a peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble compliance; &amp; in order threunto pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures another Conference, where he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf would be Moderatour; but this proves as ineffectuall as the former; For the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> was above all others outragious,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:204891:64"/>and would come to no agreement, except <hi>Mazarine</hi> were firſt baniſhed <hi>France,</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> King as violently perſiſted in his reſolution againſt it, alledging, <hi>That he had approved himſelf both a faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, and an able Miniſter of State.</hi> So in ſtead of agreement, both ſides prepare for War, yet are both ſides equally angry, &amp; exaſperated againſt his ſacred Majeſty for his good will toward them and the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the one and other party imagining that both he and his Mother had given counſels oppoſite to their deſignes.</p>
            <p>But that which above all exaſperated the Princes againſt his Majeſty of <hi>England,</hi> was the ſudden luke-warmneſs of the Duke of <hi>Lorain</hi> in the buſineſs. For though he had drawn off his Army, as though he had complied with their reſolutions to come to a battel; yet being ſent for by the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to advance towards <hi>Paris,</hi> he refuſed to come; which made the Princes believe there had been ſome underhand dealing with him; and that which moſt of all en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed their jealouſies that King <hi>Charles</hi>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:204891:65"/>had a hand in it, was this; The Duke of <hi>Beaufort</hi> coming to the Camp of <hi>Lorain</hi> to deſire him in the name of the Princes to come up and fight, found there his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty &amp; his brother the Duke of <hi>York</hi> in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate conference with <hi>Lorain,</hi> who with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing when <hi>Beaufort</hi> appeared; &amp; <hi>Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort</hi> finding the Duke's averſneſs to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize confirmed him, and he confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Princes of the King of <hi>England's</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, whereby he had withdrawn <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain</hi> from their party: This coming to the peoples ears who were abſolute favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of the Princes, and inveterate enemies to <hi>Mazarine,</hi> ſo extreamly incenſed them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Princes, that they threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en violence and indignities to their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, &amp; are not afraid to affront the Queen their Mother in her Coach; which made his Majeſty to avoid the popular fury, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire himſelf from the <hi>Lovure</hi> to St. <hi>Germane.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor is the <hi>Cardinal</hi> leſs incenſed, though under a more politick vail; For though both Princes and People might imagine &amp; believe that his Majeſty had counſel'd
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:204891:65"/>things oppoſite to their intentions, yet the <hi>Cardinal</hi> very well knew that he had advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the King as the beſt courſe, to conſent to his departure out of the Kingdome; and that if he had endeavoured to draw <hi>Lorain</hi> from their party, 'twas only out of a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire he had to expedite their agreement; he therefore reſolves to thwart him in all his deſigns.</p>
            <p>And ſo he did to the utmoſt of his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours: For his Majeſty though ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Prince, in his ſeveral confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences with <hi>Lorain</hi> to have endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to divert him from them, was only tranſacting with him for the recovery of his Kingdome of <hi>Ireland</hi> out of the hands of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Republick; to which effect ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Articles were drawn up between the Duke of <hi>Lorain,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Taaff;</hi> two of which were: 1. <hi>That the Duke of</hi> Lorain <hi>ſhould tranſport an Army of</hi> 10000. <hi>men at his own charge into</hi> Ireland, <hi>there to joyn with ſuch as ſhould be found Loyal, for the Recovery of his Majeſties Rights in that Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That the Duke of</hi> Lorain <hi>ſhould by his
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:204891:66"/>Majeſty be inveſted with the power and Title of</hi> Protector Royall of Ireland.</p>
            <p>Theſe Articles though drawn up, never came to be ſigned; the cauſe of which ſome have imagined to be the diſability of the <hi>Duke</hi> to performe the Enterpriſe without the Aid of ſome other Prince; but we may in more reaſon gueſs, it proceeded from the ſtrenuous endeavours of <hi>Mazarine</hi> (his Majeſties ſo lately made-enemy) to divert the Duke's Army, then from any other cauſe.</p>
            <p>Many in <hi>England</hi> upon hearing of theſe Propoſitions made to the Duke of <hi>Lorain,</hi> (which I muſt confeſs ſome believe to have never proceeded any farther then diſcourſe of the Duks) feared his Majeſties too great inclination to the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion, which fear his after retirement at St. <hi>Germain's,</hi> convinced there was no need of: For here he ſpent his time wholly in Piety and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions, according to the beſt worſhip of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> never forgeting to pray for thoſe his Enemies who were not only content to have deprived him of his Kingdoms,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:204891:66"/>but continually belched forth both ſlanders and maledictions againſt him.</p>
            <p>His Majeſty having ſtaid at S. <hi>Germains</hi> till ſuch time as the heate of the popular fury was over, which decreaſed ſtill to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them as they found <hi>Mazarine</hi> more averſe to him, returned again to the <hi>Lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ure;</hi> where during his abode, his brother the Duke of <hi>Glouceſter</hi> (who had a long time been detained by the <hi>Juncto</hi> of <hi>England</hi> in the Iſle of <hi>Wight,</hi> and was lately permitted by them to go to his Siſter the Princeſs Royal in <hi>Holland,</hi> came to him accompanied from the <hi>Hague</hi> by Sir <hi>Marmaduke Langdale</hi> and Sir <hi>Richard Greenvile;</hi> he was at his arrivall at <hi>Paris</hi> honourably received by the King of <hi>France,</hi> and Queen Mother; and courted according to his birth by the reſt of the Grandees and Peers of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe during his Majeſties abode here, arrived his <hi>Quondam</hi> Preſerver Mrs. <hi>Jane Lane,</hi> who after ſhe had taken leave of his Majeſty at <hi>Bristol,</hi> return'd home; and lived for ſome ſpace in a great deale of
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:204891:67"/>ſecurity, not doubting ſhe could be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray'd: Yet at length by what means I know not, (though indeed I have heard of many relations that I dare not relate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny) it came to light; yet ſhe had ſome time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly notice of it, whereupon ſhe who had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly diſguiſed his Majeſty in a Serving<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans habit, now diſguiſes her ſelf in that of a Country <hi>Wench;</hi> and trots on foot (to ſave her life which ſhe was like to loſe for having formerly ſaved his ſacred Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties,) quite croſſe the Countrey to <hi>Yar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth,</hi> where ſhe found ſhipping which conveyed her ſafe into <hi>France;</hi> great ſearch after her departure there was made for her but in vain; which ſo incenſed the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers that they burnt down to the ground that poor Cottage where his Majeſty firſt took ſhelter after his eſcape from <hi>Worceſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>She being arrived in <hi>France,</hi> ſends a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the Court, whereupon his Majeſty almoſt over-joy'd at her Eſcape who had been the cauſe of his, immediatly ſends ſome perſons of quality in Coaches to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct her to <hi>Paris,</hi> whither he being near
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:204891:67"/>come himſelf with the Queen his Mother, the Duke of <hi>York, Glouceſter,</hi> went out to meet this Preſerver of the life of their <hi>Son, Soveraign</hi> and <hi>Brother;</hi> the Coaches meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſhe being deſcended from her Coach, his Majeſty likewiſe deſcends, &amp; taking her by the hand, ſalutes her with this gratefull expreſſion, <hi>Welcome my life,</hi> &amp; ſo putting her into his own Coach, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducts her to <hi>Paris,</hi> where ſhe was entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the applauſe and wonder of the whole Court: and ſhe could indeed deſerve no leſs; for I believe neither paſt or future Ages can or will ever parallell ſo great a pattern of female Loyalty and Generoſity.</p>
            <p>Whilſt his Majeſty was thus paſſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his time in <hi>France,</hi> more in contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation then action, <hi>Oliver Cromwell</hi> made General of all the <hi>Juncto's</hi> Forces in <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Jreland,</hi> finding now a fit opportunity to put his long-laid am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious deſigns in execution, had diſſolved that <hi>Juncto</hi> which had uſurped the Kingly power or more, over <hi>England,</hi> and taken upon himſelf (though not the title) yet
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:204891:68"/>the Royall power and authority over theſe Nations, which the people, though un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing, yet were forced to ſubmit to; &amp; though he had not at firſt any <hi>baſis</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to ground his new uſurped Regality; yet in ſtead of one <hi>Juncto</hi> he pluckt down, he eaſily ſets up another, which I may the more juſtly call ſo, in regard there was not one of them choſen by the free Votes of the People, but by his own arbitrary E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, and thoſe ſuch perſons who knew well enough what they had to doe before they met: theſe after a ſhort time ſitting (without doing any thing beſides the mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſome impertinent laws which were forceably impoſed on the people) ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their power (as dying men do their ſouls to God) into his hands that gave it, who by the help of the Officers of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and <hi>Lamberts</hi> inſtrument, makes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf immediatly king of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> (which government he had of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſworn againſt) though under the title of <hi>Protector.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This (I muſt needs ſay) Noble Tyrant,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:204891:68"/>having got the Dominion of three ſuch Kingdoms into his poſſeſſion, made it now as much his ſtudy to preſerve himſelf ſafe in his Eſtate and <hi>Grandure,</hi> as he did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to acquire it; to which purpoſe he thought it moſt ſuitable to that deſign, to make ſome remarkable diſturbance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the neighbouring Princes; then to continue that War (begun by the <hi>Juncto</hi> of <hi>Parliament</hi>) with the <hi>Dutch,</hi> to which purpoſe ſeverall motions of a Treaty paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
            <p>His ſacred Majeſty, though he had ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry times before ſolicited the aſſiſtance of thoſe United Provinces for the regaining of his Right in his Kingdoms, now more earneſtly upon ſecret intelligence of the firſt motions of this Treaty, ſends the Lord <hi>Gerard</hi> his Embaſſadour to the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted States more earneſtly intreating them to own his Intereſt then before, proffering, that if they would ſet out a good ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron of ſhips under his Flag, he would command them himſelf in perſon.</p>
            <p>His Siſter, the princeſs of <hi>Orange</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:204891:69"/>of his friends in the Low Countries, addicted to his Intereſt, earneſtly proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutes his deſires, and uſe their utmoſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence on the States of the United provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for the performance of his propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Nor are there five of theſe Provinces, nor <hi>Van Trump</hi> himſelf their Admiral un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to comply with him. Only the Province of <hi>Holland,</hi> the moſt potent at ſea, ſtands out, chiefly out of the diſguſt they had lately taken to the family of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range,</hi> whoſe intereſt and command they were fearfull might bee reſtored, ſhould his Majeſty, who was Uncle to the young Prince, be inveſted in his Territories.</p>
            <p>His Majeſty likewiſe to advance his hopes of their aſſiſtance, when Monſieur <hi>Bortell</hi> came from thoſe United States to negotiate a League with the King of <hi>France,</hi> uſed his utmoſt Intereſt to promote the Treaty, and in fine, brought it to a deſired period: notwithſtanding the United States ſent no other anſwer to his Embaſſey then a cold Letter of Complements.</p>
            <p>His deſigns thus failing him here, he
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:204891:69"/>directed himſelf to a more hopefull courſe, by interpoſing himſelf a Mediator with the <hi>Pope</hi> and other <hi>Catholick</hi> Princes for an accord and peace between the two mighty Crowns of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain.</hi> And indeed two ſuch potent <hi>Monarchs</hi> had been in bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter capacity with their joynt forces to have aſſiſted him (had the peace gon forward, as there was great hopes) then the United States of the <hi>Netherlands;</hi> but Cardinal <hi>Mazarine</hi> by a piece of ſecret ſtate-policy, endeavoured to obſtruct all proceedings which might tend to a Treaty or accord.</p>
            <p>Nor was this Cardinal's ſpleen to his Royall Majeſty yet allayed; for his ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Council againſt him in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned difference between the King &amp; Princes; but farther to prejudice him and his affairs, he endeavours the promotion of a peace between the <hi>Protector</hi> of <hi>England</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> King his Maſter, which, though oppoſed by all the force and Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt that either himſelfe or the Queen his Mother had in the <hi>French</hi> Court; yet was by the Cardinall (whoſe will was a law,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:204891:70"/>all other Government in that Kingdome being but a meer ſhadow) vigorouſly car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on, and an Embaſſadour ſent over to treat of an accord: where having been ſometime in <hi>England,</hi> his Majeſty was by ſecret intelligence informed that the chief Article inſiſted upon in the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty (by the <hi>Protector</hi> of <hi>England</hi>) was the excluding himſelf, relations and followers out of the Kingdome of <hi>France</hi> and it's Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories; wherefore leaſt the treaty ſhould be ſuddenly concluded upon thoſe tearms, &amp; he ceremoniouſly excluded, he thought it more honourable himſelf to leave that Kingdome of his own accord; and having taken his leave of the King of <hi>France,</hi> and the reſt of the Nobility accompanied with his Coufin Prince Rupert, he departed for <hi>Germany,</hi> where the Lord <hi>Wilmot</hi> had long been Embaſſadour for him to ſolicite aid and aſſiſtance.</p>
            <p>Yet notwithſtanding his Brothers, the Duke of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> ſtaid ſtill in <hi>France.</hi> The firſt having under the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Marſhall of <hi>Turine</hi> againſt the
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:204891:70"/>
               <hi>Spaniards</hi> performed ſuch eminent ſervices as had made him deſervedly eſteemed a moſt valerous and prudent Prince; in ſo much that notwithſtanding his Youth he was made Lieu. Generall of the <hi>French</hi> Army, and thought ſo well worthy that Command, that when <hi>Turine</hi> (the moſt eſteemed Generall the <hi>French</hi> have for a long time had) lay deſperatly ſick, and it was expected that he ſhould breath his laſt; he was by the King of <hi>France</hi> ſent to, to deſire him, that ſeeing there were ſo little hopes of his life he would nominate ſuch a Generall of his Army as he might judge fit to ſucceed him. To which <hi>Turine</hi> anſwered; that if his Majeſty would have his affairs proſper, he ſhould make choice of a Noble, Valorous, and fortunate Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall; which if he did, he could make choice of no fitter perſon then the thrice Heroick Duke of <hi>York.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for his Brother the Duke of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> he remained at the Palace Royall in <hi>Paris</hi> with the Queen his Mother; who ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after the departure of his Royall
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:204891:71"/>Majeſty, endeavoured by all the bonds of filiall obedience and the moſt prevailing Arguments could be uſed, to perſwade him to become Roman Catholick: (nor did ſhe alone) but the Queen Mother of <hi>France,</hi> and the prime Nobility of that Kingdome, attempt the ſame: when the Retorique of the Court could not prevail, the moſt eminent for learning ſet upon him with that depth of reaſon, as long acquir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſtudy and their own intereſt, could ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige them to uſe, or furniſh them withall: nor were Arguments and Reaſons only u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, but the higheſt temptations this world could preſent, to a Prince in adverſity; ſuch were a Cardinals Hatt, and a Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue ſuitable to his Dignity: when theſe could not prevail, the indignation of a Royal Mother was poured forth upon him, which wrought him the deprivation of his Tutor, his Servants, and all Comforters in theſe temptations: But that Noble Prince was ſo far indowed (dureing this afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) with the Principles of the Religion of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> beſides that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:204891:71"/>piety and conſtancy, flowing from his moſt religious Father of bleſſed Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, that by the depth of truth and Reaſon, he defended himſelfe againſt theſe attempts. After this he is committed to the care of one Mr <hi>Walter Montague</hi> Abbot of <hi>Nantueil</hi> living at <hi>Pontoiſe,</hi> who keeps him in very cloſely, and works, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts ſtill in endeavouring to pervert him, uſing the Argument of Duty and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to his Mothers Commands, which ſhe did enjoyn him to doe or never more to ſee her face, (which from that day to this he hath not ſeen.) This noble ſoul replyed with a ſorrowfull heart, <hi>That as the Queens Majeſty was his Mother, he ought her duty; but as his Brother was his King and Soveraign, he ought him duty and Allegiance, which he could not diſpute.</hi> Whilſt he is at <hi>Pontoiſe</hi> the moſt noble and religious Lord <hi>Hatton,</hi> takes occaſion to go wait upon the Duke, according to private iuſtructions received from his Majeſty (who to his great ſorrow had adviſe of theſe particulers) he is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted with much trouble to the preſence
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:204891:72"/>of the Duke, who embraces him as his Deliverer, and with ſome difficulty, urg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Commands of his Majeſty, &amp; his own arguments; he is delivered to his care, who conducts him with a ſpetiall reſpect and diligence to his houſe in <hi>Paris,</hi> where he is entertained divers dayes with all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and confirmed wih all diligence, by that Learned Lord, in his ſo well imbued Principles, untill the arrivall of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs of <hi>Ormond,</hi> who by the Kings Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, receivs, and conducts him to his Majeſties Court.</p>
            <p>His Majeſty in his journy towards <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> came firſt to <hi>Catillon</hi> a Caſtle belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> whither he was accompanied by his Brother the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> and his Couſins prince <hi>Rupert</hi> and <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> Palatines; here Prince <hi>Edward</hi> &amp; the Duke of <hi>York</hi> left them; the one going to <hi>Bourbon,</hi> the other returning to the Army: (where he continued a good while after) his Majeſty &amp; Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> continued for ſome few daies their journy together, 'till the Prince parted from him to go viſit his
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:204891:72"/>Brother <hi>Frederick</hi> at <hi>Hidelberg;</hi> his Majeſty paſſing through <hi>Cambray</hi> and <hi>Leige</hi> to the <hi>Spaw;</hi> where he tooke up the firſt place of his Reſidence in <hi>Germany,</hi> whither his Siſter the Royall Princeſs of <hi>Orange</hi> came to viſit him; and they no doubt during the time of their being there, were as merry as two ſuch afflicted Princes could.</p>
            <p>But let us a little leave his Majeſty at the <hi>Spaw,</hi> and look into his Kingdomes, where <hi>Cromwell</hi> that he might ſecure him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, in his ill-gotten Eſtate, endeavours by all means poſſible either to take away the lives or wholly impoveriſh &amp; diſable his Majeſties loyall Subjects; who are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually charged with ſomthing, which he by his uſurped power takes hold of to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them: ſeverall perſons are apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and charged with a deſign to have ſeized on the Tower, and Proclaimed his Majeſty King of thoſe Kingdoms which by right were his: for tryall of which perſons, a High Court of Juſtice, (a thing we now in <hi>England</hi> know very well) was erected for the tryal of thoſe perſons,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:204891:73"/>Col. <hi>John Gerard,</hi> Mr. <hi>Peter Vowell,</hi> and <hi>Sommerſet Fox</hi> were condemned to be hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, drawn, &amp; quartered: (for no leſs then high Treaſon for-ſooth, though there were then no Act in being making it Treaſon to conſpire againſt the power then in being in <hi>England</hi>) but ſomwhat of the ſentence was remitted, Col. <hi>Gerard</hi> was beheaded, Mr <hi>Vowell</hi> only Hanged, &amp; Mr. <hi>Fox</hi> reprived.</p>
            <p>I have alwayes obſerved that in all the tryals made by thoſe high Courts of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice for plots (as they call them) there hath ſtill been ſome one perſon, who though brought to tryal, have either not been condemned though look't upon by the people as eminent in the buſineſs as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny) and though condemned, yet have been reprived; what others gueſs of it, I will not determine, I know what I do.</p>
            <p>The truth is, that his Majeſty had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies the ill fortune to have ſuch falſe ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants about him as have for the Lucre of money either betrayed any enterprize of his for the gaining of his right, (the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector</hi> eſpecially being very prodigal in
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:204891:73"/>ſuch expences: his intelligence as moſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, ſtanding him in no leſs then two hun dred thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d pound <hi>per annum</hi>) or elſe thoſe perſons engag'd for him, being many of them deboiſt fellows, (and who often ran upon deſignes uncommiſſioned) have in a Tavern both lay'd and betray'd their own undertakings; or elſe ſome here in <hi>England,</hi> who have undertaken in ſuch buſineſſes, have either for fear or gain betrayed both their Prince friends and Countrey.</p>
            <p>Thus much for <hi>England;</hi> let us now take a viwe of his Majeſties affaires in <hi>Scotland;</hi> which Kingdome was not yet wholly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered, for the Lords <hi>Seaforth, Atholl, Glen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carne, Kenmore,</hi> and <hi>Glengary,</hi> and ſeverall others who had ſome of them been for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly followers of the noble Marqueſs of <hi>Montroſſe,</hi> by Commiſſions to the Earle of <hi>Glencarne</hi> had levied ſundry ſmall parties in their ſeverall Territories; which all joyned, would have made up a conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Army, beſides the help which they expected <hi>Middleton</hi> ſhould bring them out of the Low-Countries they therefore made
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:204891:74"/>all poſſible ſpeed to joyn; but in their march the Earl of <hi>Glencarne</hi> is ſet upon by Col. <hi>Morgan,</hi> his party routed, himſelfe hardly eſcaping.</p>
            <p>This defeat of <hi>Glancarn's</hi> who was the chief, though it diſcouraged the reſt, yet made them not wholly deſiſt; for they had yet hopes of thoſe ſupplies which they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected <hi>Middleton</hi> to bring out of the Low-Countries, who at length arrives &amp; brings with him <hi>Monroe</hi> to be his Lieu. General, he being Commiſſionated General, which highly diſpleaſed <hi>Glancarne,</hi> who had been the greateſt inſtrument of his Armies raiſing (which was now joyn'd and made up a conſiderable body) who proteſted that he would not raiſe an Army for others to Command, ſo high a diſpute there was between <hi>Glancarne</hi> and <hi>Monroe;</hi> in ſomuch that many affirm, though ſom ſay the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, that it came to a Duell, in which <hi>Monroe</hi> was worſted &amp; diſarmed by <hi>Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carne;</hi> however the diſſention ſtill conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues, for <hi>Middleton</hi> pretended that he had not power to tak away <hi>Monro</hi>'s Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:204891:74"/>which was given him by his Majeſty, and <hi>Glancarne</hi> ſcorning to be under him, being of Noble bloud, &amp; accounting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as good a Souldier, deſerts the Army with five hundred Horſe in his company, and goes in to General <hi>Monck</hi> with whom he makes his Compoſition.</p>
            <p>Yet notwithſtanding his deſertion (cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by thoſe differences amongſt them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves for Superiority, the only way to ruine any deſigne) <hi>Middleton</hi> purſues his buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and Commiſſion; and had made up a pritty Conſiderable Number, when Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <hi>Monck</hi> engaging him at <hi>Laugherry</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a not diſpute totally routed him, ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered his party and had almoſt taken him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Priſoner, but he eſcaping returned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain into <hi>Holland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus his Majeſties ill fortune ſtill at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends his affaires, God ſtill permiting his Enemies to taper up in the World &amp; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance themſelves, not that he in the want of us, but that we in the want of ſo Noble a Prince might be yet farther Miſerable.</p>
            <p>But let us return again to his Majeſty at
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:204891:75"/>the <hi>Spaw</hi> where he having ſtaid a while, courted by all the adjacent Grandees, at length takes his journey in company of the Princeſs Royall his Siſter towards <hi>Colen,</hi> where being arrived, they were recieved with all poſſible honour and demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of joy &amp; affection, the great Guns dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging at their entrance, and the Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the City coming out to meet them in ſolemn maner, and conducting them in great pomp to the pallas provided for them by the chief Magiſtrate of the City.</p>
            <p>Shortly after their Arrivall, the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees of the Place entertain'd his Majeſty and his Royall Siſter at a ſumptuous Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet or Collation, where they expreſs in many ceremonious complements, the high reſentment they had of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties condition, and the great honour which he did them, in being pleaſed to come and viſit their City.</p>
            <p>After a ſhort time of abode here, his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty was invited by the Duke of <hi>Newburgh</hi> to his pallace at <hi>Donzell-dorf,</hi> where he &amp; his Siſter were moſt ſumptuouſly &amp; Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:204891:75"/>entertained for ſome dayes; and here the Royall Princes took her leave of her Brother his ſacred Majeſty, and returned for <hi>Holland,</hi> the King accompanying her on her way as far as <hi>Redinguen,</hi> and from thence returned back again to <hi>Colen,</hi> where he was joyfully receiv'd.</p>
            <p>And now more of his Majeſties loyal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects are put to wrack in <hi>England</hi> by ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannizing <hi>Cromwell;</hi> a generall deſign muſt needs be laid over all <hi>England,</hi> and perhaps might be ſo, though <hi>Cromwell</hi> Knew it well enough before it was like to take any ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, which apeared by his ſetling the <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don Militia</hi> in the hands of his own <hi>Criado's,</hi> his apprehending of Sir <hi>Henry Littleton,</hi> Sir <hi>John Packington,</hi> and many other of the Royall party; yet he lets it ſtill go on, that he might have the better colour for keeping his Scaffold in uſe; whilſt he hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing certain Intelligence of all proceedings from his hired Agents, had care to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent them when they juſt came to the height, that he might then lay the ſurer hold on the undertakers: ſo now, though he was
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:204891:76"/>ſure to prevent all riſings which might be near <hi>London,</hi> yet he lets others in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries more remote to go on ſo farre, as they might only raiſe to a head, but not have any ſecure place of ſtrength to retreat to, in caſe of a defeat, where they might a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain have made a head. The ſurprizal of <hi>Shrewsberry</hi> and <hi>Chirk</hi> Caſtles are to that effect now prevented. But a party in <hi>Dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet</hi> and <hi>Wiltſhier</hi> made a body, conſiſting moſt of Gentlemen who ſurprized <hi>Saliz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> took away all the Horſes, and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched towards <hi>Cornwall,</hi> where they expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted a greater force to riſe with them; but being eagerly purſued by Captain <hi>Crook</hi> with a party of Horſe, were over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken at <hi>Southmolton</hi> in <hi>Devon ſhire,</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a hot diſpute, moſt of them either ſlain or taken; but Sir <hi>Joſeph Wagstaffe,</hi> the chief Commander of this ſmall loyal party e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcaped. The Captains, <hi>Penruddock, Grove</hi> and <hi>Jones</hi> were taken, and afterwards be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tri'd by a Commiſſion of <hi>Oyer</hi> &amp; <hi>Termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> were condemned to death: Captaine <hi>Jones</hi> was reprived, but <hi>Grove</hi> &amp; <hi>Penrud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dock</hi>
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:204891:76"/>were beheaded at <hi>Exeter,</hi> The laſt of which parted nobly with his life, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a reſolution, worthy of the cauſe for which he ſuffered. Many others like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe were hanged for his enterprize.</p>
            <p>Yet theſe and their fellows might have come off better, had the Countries as they promiſed, riſen to their aſſiſtance; for all the Countries in <hi>England</hi> had deſigned (as they ſay) to riſe; but whether beſotted, dull'd and fearful, or elſe prevented by a force upon them, I cannot tell; but ſure I am they fail'd. Yet in <hi>Yorkſhire</hi> there were two parties up in ſeverall places, but diſſipated by their own feares; at <hi>Hexam</hi> Moor the Gentry in that <hi>ſhire</hi> had a Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dezvouz, of whom Sir <hi>Henry Slingsby</hi> was taken, and remained priſoner in <hi>Hull,</hi> till ſuch time as he was brought up to <hi>London,</hi> where he ſuffered death under pretence of another deſign; as ſhall in due time be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared.</p>
            <p>But now the <hi>Protector</hi> findes another courſe to rid himſelfe of all ſuch <hi>Engliſh</hi> men as were loyall to their King &amp; Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey.
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:204891:77"/>Several of thoſe who were active in the late deſign and had been taken, are out of the Priſons hurried aboard ſhips; and though they were free-born <hi>Engliſh</hi> men, and many of them Gentlemen, ſent to be Slaves in the Forraign Plantations; nor were they alone ſerved ſo, but many who though they had not actually ſtir'd, yet being by the Protector known as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons not very well affected to his Tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Government, were privately taken out of their houſes and ſhipt away in like manner; it not being enough for him when he had impoveriſhed them by taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way their Eſtates to look upon, and inſult on their miſery at home, but to make them as much as in him lay the ſcorne and deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the world, by ſelling them to thoſe Plantations (a puniſhment inflicted uſually on none but thieves and vagabonds.) Yet I hope thoſe Noble ſoules who were thus dealt withall, account thoſe miſeries and hardſhips they have endured but little in reſpect of the cauſe for which they ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered them.</p>
            <pb n="139" facs="tcp:204891:77"/>
            <p>But to return to our Princes abroad. The Duke of <hi>Gloceſter</hi> in his journy from <hi>Paris</hi> with the Marqueſs of <hi>Ormond</hi> touched at the <hi>Hague,</hi> where he found his Siſter newly returned from her journey with his Majeſty; and having ſtaid with her ſome time there, ſhe accompanied him to viſit their Brother the King, again at <hi>Colen,</hi> with whom ſhe ſtaid till after the fair at <hi>Frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> whither his Majeſty accompanied with his Royal Siſter, the Duke of <hi>Gloceſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> the Marqueſs of <hi>Ormond,</hi> the Earle of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich,</hi> the Lord <hi>Newburg,</hi> and ſeveral La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and perſons of Quality went in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs; part of the way they went by Land, and the other part by water; being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plemented in all Princes countries through which they paſſed, by their chief Miniſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of State, and ſaluted with the great Guns from their Towns &amp; Caſtles, but par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly being come into the Territories of the Elector of <hi>Mentz</hi> they were ſaluted by his grand Marſhall, who in the name of his Maſter the Elector, invited his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty the Princeſs Royall &amp; the Duke of <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter</hi>
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:204891:78"/>to his Court; but in regard that the intent of their progreſs was to ſee that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Fair at <hi>Franckford</hi> which now drew nigh, his Majeſty ſent the Lord <hi>Newburgh</hi> back with the grand Marſhal, returning thanks to the Elector for his civilities; but deſiring to be excuſed till their return, when his Majeſty with his Royal Siſter &amp; Brother would not Faile to come, and give him thanks in perſon, and ſo his Majeſty with his Noble company continued their journy.</p>
            <p>Being arrived at <hi>Frankford,</hi> advice was brought to his Majeſty that the Queen of <hi>Swethland</hi> (who had ſome time before Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily ſurrendered her Kingdom into the hands of <hi>Carolus Guſtavus</hi> her Kinſman) was paſſing that way in her intended Journey for <hi>Italy,</hi> whereupon his Majeſty ſent a Noble Lord to acquaint her Royall Highneſs the Queen <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> that he was ready to wait upon her at what place ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhe ſhould be pleaſed to appoint for an interview; her Majeſty received the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage with a great deal of affection, telling
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:204891:78"/>the Meſſenger That ſhe was highly oblig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to his Majeſty of <hi>England</hi> for ſo great an honour, and that if he pleaſed, ſhe would not fail to meet him at <hi>Conningſtein</hi> a village not far from <hi>Frankford</hi> where his Majeſty for the time reſided.</p>
            <p>And accordingly there theſe two Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentates, (both equally deprived of their Kingdomes, only with this diſtinction, the one Voluntary, the other by force and Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny) met; the Queen of <hi>Sweden</hi> being there, firſt attended his Majeſty: &amp; he being come, was immediately admitted in a room there purpoſely provided; and having had neer halfe an hours private diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with her, the Duke of <hi>Gloceſter</hi> was admitted, and preſently after the Lords that attended his Majeſty; there paſſing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween their two Majeſties many ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious complements; &amp; ſo after a little long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er diſcourſe they took their leaves. The Princeſſe Royal being a little indiſpoſed went not to this interview.</p>
            <p>His Majeſty having tarried at <hi>Franck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> as long as ſeem'd convenient to that
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:204891:79"/>Royall Company, in his departure thence according to the promiſe he had before made by the Lord <hi>Newburgh;</hi> paſſed through the Elector of <hi>Mentz</hi> his Country, reſolving to give him a viſit, but that No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Prince had ſo much of honour in him that he met his Majeſty a great part of the way, and conducted him with his Royall Company to a Pallace of his, where he ſumptuouſly entertained them for three or four dayes; and then himſelf in perſon ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied them a good part of their way to <hi>Colen,</hi> from whence ſhortly after his Majeſties arrival there, the Princeſs Royal departed for <hi>Holland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the mean time the Protector of <hi>England,</hi> having made a peace with the <hi>Hollander,</hi> fearing that the Nation ſhould grow re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious to him, if they lay free from wars, which would fill their purſes; reſolves to keep them low, at a diet; to which effect he begins a war with <hi>Spain,</hi> at firſt in his Weſtern Territories, but ſoon after (that buſineſs not ſucceeding) in his <hi>Europaean</hi> Quarters, which made <hi>Mazarine</hi> with all
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:204891:79"/>haſt poſſible endeavour the concluding the Leageu Offenſive and Defenſive with the Protector, which being by him conſidered to be as beneficiall for his own intereſt as for the <hi>French,</hi> was eaſily and willingly aſſented to; but the chief Articles of this Peace was that his Majeſty, the Duke of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Gloceſter</hi> with all their relations and friends ſhould be expelled out of, and no more admitted into the Kingdom of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Certainly had the <hi>French</hi> King had but the leaſt touch or ſenſe of honour, he would have counted this the hardeſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition in the world, or indeed he would never at all have treated with the protect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or, but that he ſhould yeild to ſuch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, as to baniſh out of his Kingdome thoſe who came to him for ſuccour and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief in the utmoſt extreamity that ever Princes were put too, and theſe too his neareſt relations, being Brothers &amp; Siſters children: And this to make a league offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive with him who had murdered, their Father, &amp; expelled them out of their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions.
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:204891:80"/>What was this? but the owning of that murder, and aggravating their op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions inſtead of relieving them. But nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther honour nor relation can ſtand in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition with ſelf-Intereſt.</p>
            <p>His Maieſty had before fore-ſaw what the event of this treaty would be, and had therefore wiſely wihdrawn himſelfe from <hi>France</hi> to prevent a complemental expulſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> who in regard of the great command which he had in the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, had ſtaid there til the concluſion of the League, was now warned to depart with al his retinnue (conſiſting of a gallant num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of young <hi>Engliſh</hi> gentlemen bred up un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his valour &amp; conduct) notwithſtanding thoſe many great ſervices which he had performed for that Kingdom, in requitall of which he had only a complemental A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pology made him for the neceſſity of his departure, and a ſmall time reſpited for his ſtay, during which he was viſited by the Duke of <hi>Modena,</hi> then in <hi>France,</hi> and other <hi>French</hi> Grandees; but more eſpeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally by the Marſhal of <hi>Turine,</hi> who extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:204891:80"/>loved him and above all others expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a ſorrow for his diſmiſment; but at length the day perfixed being come, his grace having ſolemnly taken his leave of the King of <hi>France,</hi> the Queen his Mother, &amp; the reſt of his Friends at the French Court, he takes his journey towards <hi>Flanders,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied by the Earl of <hi>Yarmouth,</hi> &amp; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall other <hi>Engliſh</hi> Lords.</p>
            <p>For upon the rupture of the Peace between <hi>Oliver Cromwell</hi> and the King of <hi>Spain, Don John de Auſtria,</hi> Governour Royall of the Low Countries, for his Catholick Majeſty (commiſerating our Kings unfortunate Condition, now that his Intereſt might ſtand them in ſome ſtead) had ſent the Count <hi>D' Fuenſaldaigne,</hi> his Embaſſadour to his Majeſty of Great <hi>Britain,</hi> then reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent (as I ſaid before) at <hi>Colen,</hi> inviting him into the Low Countries, and aſſuring him in the name of his Catholick Majeſty all poſſible ſervice and aſſiſtance: which invitation his Majeſty gratiouſly accepted, and ſoon after took his journey from <hi>Colen</hi> towards <hi>Flanders,</hi> &amp; being come to <hi>Bruges,</hi>
               <pb n="146" facs="tcp:204891:81"/>the place appointed for his reception, he was received with all honours imaginable, and conducted to a Pallace purpoſely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for him, where he hath for the moſt part ever ſince remained.</p>
            <p>Hither the Duke of <hi>York</hi> came, accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied as aforeſaid, having firſt in his way touched at <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> where he was magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficently entertained, and complemented by <hi>Don John,</hi> to whom he freely proferd his ſervice in the Wars, which was accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a great deal of thanks; and though he had not at firſt a command given him coreſpondent to that which he left in the <hi>French</hi> Army, yet was his prudence, cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, valour, &amp; conduct in no leſs reſpect, as afterwards by the <hi>Spaniards</hi> eſteem of him appeared. From thence he went to wait on his Majeſty at <hi>Bruges,</hi> where he was received with an affection correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to the near Alliance with his ſacred Majeſty.</p>
            <p>Before his Majeſties departure from <hi>Colen,</hi> there hapned a diſcovery of one of thoſe perſons, who under pretence of
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:204891:81"/>waiting upon him. (Captain <hi>Manning</hi> by name) diſcovered unto the Protector all his Deſignes and Counſels, who being found out was by his Majeſties Command ſent to a ſtrong Caſtle adjacent to <hi>Colen,</hi> there to be kept cloſe priſoner: But all the Court being highly incenſed againſt him for his perfidiouſneſs, one of his Majeſties Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants (though contrary to order) piſtol'd him as he was lighting out of the Coach at the Caſtle gate, giving him leſs then the due reward of his ſo abominable treachery.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>York</hi> being arrived (as I ſaid) at <hi>Bruges,</hi> was highly carreſſed by all the perſons of quality there reſident; and his Majeſty, who notwithſtanding <hi>Cromwells</hi> earneſt endeavours, either to diſpatch, diſable, or make ſlaves of his loyal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, had nevertheleſs ſome true friends in <hi>England,</hi> who were ſtill ready to ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture lives and eſtates for his ſo juſt cauſe) had got together a conſiderable number of ſuch <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Scotch,</hi> whoſe Loyalty had baniſhed them from their habitations, &amp; who were ready at all occaſions to aſſiſt
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:204891:82"/>both his Majeſty and themſelves for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of his &amp; their juſt rights &amp; eſtates; but the continuall advice which <hi>Cromwell</hi> alwaies had from thoſe treacherous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which he maintained about his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, made all enterprizes tending to the regaining of his Kingdoms, and redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his ſubjects liberty ineffectuall.</p>
            <p>This Army which his Majeſty had quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered near the ſea ſide to be ready on all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions for tranſport, was afterwards (ſince there was no apparent hopes that his Majeſty might make any ſucceſsfull uſe of them) imployed in the ſervice of the King of <hi>Spain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For his Majeſty of <hi>Spain</hi> had then great need of men in <hi>Flanders,</hi> the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector having according to Articles agreed upon between him and the <hi>French</hi> King, ſent over ſixthouſand foot for his aſſiſtance in his wars againſt <hi>Flanders,</hi> in conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of which help the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were to have <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> which was agreed on to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaguer'd by the joynt-forces of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="149" facs="tcp:204891:82"/>
            <p>Whilſt in the mean time the Protector <hi>Cromwell</hi> is by a parcell of a Parliament, of which Sir <hi>Thomas Withrington</hi> was Speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, inveſted with his power, and inſtalled in <hi>Weſtminſter</hi>-Hall, and now he conferrs thoſe dignities which were formerly the Kingly rewards of loyalty, upon his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partners and followers, and whether in mockery of that Government which he had ſo violently endeavoured to abolliſh, or out of perjured intention to ſetle it in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, which he ſwore not to endure in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he eſtabliſhed a Pageant Houſe of Lords; who though then made to rule and domineer over the Nation, yet were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly moſt of them perſons not fit to be Servants to ſome mean Mechanicks. This was that Government which he had ſo So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly ſworn againſt; but when men have once forgot their Loyalty to their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign, what vices will they not run into.</p>
            <p>But to return again to <hi>Flanders,</hi> The <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>French</hi> Armies had according to the articles concluded on betwixt them beleagure'd <hi>Dunkirk</hi> which <hi>Don Iohn</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:204891:83"/>to be a place of great importance, and an inlet into <hi>Flanders</hi> by ſea for <hi>Engliſh</hi> Forces, uſed his utmoſt endeavours to raiſe the ſieges; to which effect he levied what Forces he could, either by his own or his Majeſties influence, and having made up a conſiderable Army himſelfe in perſon, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Dukes of <hi>York</hi> &amp; <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> together with thoſe Forces for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly addicted to his Majeſties Service, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced towards the joynt-force of the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi> then beleaguring the Town, who underſtanding by their ſcouts of his approach, left ſuch Forces in the leagure as might ſecure them within from a ſally, and drew up towards <hi>Don Iohn,</hi> who had encamped near <hi>Evernes:</hi> the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi> were (notwithſtanding thoſe forces they had left in the trenches) much more numerous then the <hi>Spaniards</hi> both in horſe and foot, which made them the more reſolved in the Encounter; for though the others came to raiſe the ſiege, yet the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiegers were the firſt Aſſaulters.</p>
            <p>The firſt bruſh began with a Forlorn
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:204891:83"/>hope of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Infantry, conſiſting of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove three hundred, who deſperatly charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon a party of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Foot (which had advantagiouſly drawn themſelves up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a riſing ground, and ſeconded by <hi>Loc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kart's</hi> Regiment, commanded by Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Colonell <hi>Fenwick,</hi> and ſome other ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional ſupplies of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Infantry,) rou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not only them, but the other bodies of <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Foot drawn up on the ſame manner. In this charge Lieutenant Colonell <hi>Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick</hi> received his mortall wound, &amp; ſome other <hi>Engliſh</hi> Commanders were ſlain out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Cavalry ſeeing their foot ſo eaſily put to a rout, began likewiſe to flie, nor could by any endeavours be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to ſtand; whereupon the <hi>French</hi> Horſe who had all that while ſtood ſtill, and ſeen the <hi>Engliſh</hi> do execution on the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies foot, with a full career purſue their flying Enemies, of whom they found lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle oppoſition, but only what was made by the thrice valiant Duke of <hi>York</hi>'s Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, who for a time made the whole
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:204891:84"/>
               <hi>French</hi> Army to ſtand, and ſaved the lives of many of their flying Friends, which elſe had been ſacrificed to the Enemies fury, whilſt in the mean time they dedicated their own lives or perſons to their ſafeties.</p>
            <p>For after they had made a very noble &amp; gallant reſiſtance, over powred by numbers, &amp; having no ſupplies to refreſh their wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried bodies, they were forced to yeild to their Enemies numbers, or truſt to the ſwiftneſs of their horſes heels; but very few of them eſcaped, among which were the Dukes of <hi>York</hi> &amp; <hi>Glocester,</hi> though the firſt was not heard of till three daies after, which made ſome ſuſpect that he was tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en by the <hi>French</hi> Forces but by <hi>Turine</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter at a fit opportunity nobly releaſt.</p>
            <p>I may particularly take occaſion here to commend the valour of the Duke of <hi>Yorks</hi> own Troop, who indeed bore the brunt of the whole Battell though I cannot deny but they were ſeconded by ſome very noble Spirits of the <hi>Spaniards;</hi> but the perſonall Valour of Mr. <hi>Henry Bendiſh</hi> ſon to Sir <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Bendiſh</hi> Embaſſadour for the <hi>Engliſh</hi>
               <pb n="153" facs="tcp:204891:84"/>Nation in <hi>Turky</hi> (who had the ill fortune to be taken priſoner) muſt not be forgotten.</p>
            <p>Let us now change the Scence a little to <hi>England,</hi> where the Protector begins to die the Scaffold in as deep a purple as the Veſt given him at his late inſtallment bore; &amp; that not only with the Bloud of thoſe ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars that were loyal to their ſoveraign, but having as he thought now ſecured to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the Government, his hand reaches to the ſacred Clergy, nor will he ſtrike at a reed or a ſhrub amongſt them, but imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating the Ancient fable of the <hi>Jubitrian</hi> Thunder, ſtrikes at the <hi>Olympus</hi> the <hi>Atlas,</hi> the maineſt piller and ſupport of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion; for no leſſe then the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Doctor <hi>Hewet's</hi> Bloud will now ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie his inſatiate Cruelty; a man whoſe vertues and piety as they were beyond ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, ſo I think was the manner of his death beyond example.</p>
            <p>This Doctor and Sir <hi>Henry Slingsby</hi> (who had ever ſince the forementioned riſing in <hi>Yorkſhire</hi> lain priſoners in <hi>Hull</hi> Caſtle) with many others are accuſed of a deſign
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:204891:85"/>to have ſeized on the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> &amp; the Magazine at <hi>Hull</hi> both in one day, the one by a Divine, the other by a Priſoner; but theſe perſons muſt have ſeverall others to be their aſſiſtants, and that eſpetially in <hi>London,</hi> who while the Doctor was ſecur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Tower, muſt fire the City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> in ſeverall places.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that make plots may as eaſily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover them, and with as much eaſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent them; the Protector could do both: but to make ſome ſhew of a great deal of fear in the buſineſs; Worthy Alderman <hi>Tichburn</hi> then Lord Mayor of <hi>London</hi> is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately commanded to ſettle the <hi>Militia,</hi> the Protector telling him (as he eaſily might) that there was a grand deſign in hand (probably of his own contriving) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Government, that the Marqueſs <hi>of Ormond</hi> had lately been in <hi>England</hi> tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acting about it; that the Common Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my (for ſo was his Sacred Majeſty then ſtyled) lay ready with a potent Army, &amp; ſhips hired to tranſport them on the Sea coaſts of <hi>England,</hi> and that therefore the
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:204891:85"/>
               <hi>Militia</hi> ſhould be ſetled in confiding hands, meaning ſuch either whoſe intereſt or fear muſt render them faithfull to the <hi>Protector;</hi> ſhortly after, according to the common courſe, the perſons to be accuſed are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, the chief of which were Dr. <hi>Hewet,</hi> Mr. <hi>John Mordant,</hi> brother to the Earle of <hi>Peterborough,</hi> Col. <hi>Aſhton,</hi> Capt. <hi>Henry Mallory,</hi> Mr. <hi>Woodcock, John Betteley, Edmund Stacy, Henry Fryer, John Sumner,</hi> &amp; <hi>Olliver Allen;</hi> who were all accuſed to be complices of this grand deſign.</p>
            <p>And becauſe no <hi>Engliſh</hi> Law could take away theſe mens Lives, the ordinary Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannicall way of a high Court of Juſtice muſt do it; Sir <hi>Henry Slingsby</hi> (who was brought priſoner from <hi>Hull</hi> Caſtle) was the firſt who came before them, and is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed for having endeavoured to draw the Governour of that Caſte from his Alleigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance <hi>(excellently good!)</hi> to the Protector, and pleading not guilty, yet was, by two Witneſſes found ready, convicted, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Hewet</hi> being come before them (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:204891:86"/>to the Example of his Royall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt) refuſed to plead or to own the juriſdiction of the Court, for which contempt (as they were pleaſed to interpret it) he had the ſame ſentence pronounced againſt him, and was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards together with Sir <hi>Henry Slingsby</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted on Tower hill.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Mordant</hi> brother to the Earl of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terborough</hi> diſavowed likewiſe the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Court; but at laſt being indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to plead, was acquitted, ſo was Mr. <hi>Woodcock, Mallory, Fryer, Sumner,</hi> &amp; <hi>Allen</hi> were ſentenced but reprived; <hi>Aſhton, Stacy,</hi> and <hi>Bettely</hi> were hanged, drawn, and quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, in ſeveral places of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here we muſt not forget the mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimous death of <hi>John Betteley,</hi> who hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made a Speech, clearing his Innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and the juſtneſs of his Cauſe, undaunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly leapt off the Ladder, and died a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Sufferer for the Royall Intereſt.</p>
            <p>His ſacred Majeſty (during theſe ſtrange Murders and Oppreſſions of his Subjects in <hi>England,</hi> by a power which had uſurpt
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:204891:86"/>the Regality) is forced to ſit ſtill; his ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent neceſſities not giving him leave either to revenge their deaths or redeem the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving, who heavily groaned under the yoke, his only remedy now was his pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to God (which he purſues with an earneſt devotion) that he would be pleas'd in his good time to deliver his faithful Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects from thoſe miſeries and burdens they then ſtrugl'd under, and without doubt God hath heard, and will perform his pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous defires.</p>
            <p>As an introduction to which, it pleaſed the DIVINE MAJESTY to take out of the world the grandeſt oppoſer of his Majeſties Right: <hi>OLIVER CROM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>WELL,</hi> who from a mean beginning had raiſed himſelf by force to be the arbitrary Governour of theſe Nations, who is by the Almighty called to give an account of his actions before the High Tribunall of Heaven, where are neither falſe witneſſes nor intereſed Judges, and that on the ſame day on which he had gained two ſuch ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall victories over his Majeſties forces at
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:204891:87"/>
               <hi>Dunbar</hi> and <hi>Worceſter, viz.</hi> on the third day of <hi>September.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet he thought he had certainly ſecur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Government of theſe three Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for himſelf, and nominates his ſon <hi>Richard</hi> for his Succeſſour, a perſon, to ſpeak the truth, as not at all endowed with his fathers courage, ſo not at all inclined to his ambition: one, whom if fame lies not of him, could have willingly been content to have ſurrendred his Protectorſhip to the King the lawfull heir, and (by law) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Succeſſour of his royal Father. But thoſe Officers of the Army, whoſe am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, (though not in ſo high a degree,) had ſo engaged them as Complices to <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Cromwell</hi> in his high late deſignes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his King and Countrey, had ſo great a load of guilt upon their conſciences, that they could not hear of, much leſs agree to the admiſſion of his Sacred Majeſty.</p>
            <p>Nor was it indeed only thus, but ſome ambitious ſpirits there were, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly Maj. General <hi>Lambert,</hi> whoſe high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flown thoughts made him fancy Idea's in
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:204891:87"/>his brain, &amp; forc't him to attempt the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſing to make himſelf Commander of theſe three Nations, as <hi>Oliver</hi> (by his means) had done before, which deſignes of his in the ſequell, ruin'd him, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered thoſe grand cheats &amp; abuſes which that par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> had put upon the Nation, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to enſlave them to their own arbitrary power, whilſt they pretended thoſe ſtrangely miſtaken names of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Liberty as hereafter will appear.</p>
            <p>And theſe paſſages I ſhall the more fully inſert, as tending ſo much to his Majeſties intereſt here, and to the undeceiving of his good Subjects, who are not blinded with Intereſt, which the Uſurpers had endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to make the moſt potent men in the Nation, <hi>i. e.</hi> ſuch as had the greateſt ſums of money, by ſelling ſuch cheap penni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worths of the Kings, Queens, Biſhops, Deans and Chapters lands, which toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the purchaſes of the eſtates of ſuch loyal ſubjects to his Majeſty, as thoſe in power were pleaſed to ſtile Delinquents had near infatuated a good part of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <pb n="160" facs="tcp:204891:88"/>
            <p>But to proceed, let us now begin with theſe diſtinctions. 'Tis an old Proverb in Engliſh, <hi>When theives fall out, then honeſt men come by their Goods;</hi> may it now prove as true as old, (which God be praiſd) we have ſome reaſon to hope.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oliver Cromwell,</hi> the greate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, though moſt heroick enemy of his King &amp; Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey being dead, his ſon <hi>Richard</hi> is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed Protector, and for ſome times ſeemingly complyed with; but <hi>Lambert's</hi> ambition which had long lain hid, begins now to appear, and ſomething he whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers into the ears of the Army, which mixt with the great love they had former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for him, eaſily creates a diſlike of <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chards</hi> Government, which afterward wrought to ſuch a height, that by a joynt-Conſpiracy the Protectorſhip is diſjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and <hi>Richard</hi> deprived of his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the taking away of which he as willingly conſents to, as they are ready to deprive him of it.</p>
            <p>This was the firſt jarring which this Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration had amongſt themſelves, which
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:204891:88"/>withſtanding was compoſed by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector's eaſie conſent, without the ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of one drop of bloud. But there yet remained to his depoſers the greateſt task, ſince they were ſufficiently ſenſible that though they had pull'd down one civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, (they muſt be inforc't though never ſo unwillingly) to ſet up another.</p>
            <p>For they very well knew, that they had already ſo much gul'd the Nation, that they could not but now be ſenſible of their many abuſes; yet they fly to their old pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of Religion and Liberty, and under that pretence (ſince they muſt at leaſt eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh the face of civil government, they call a Parliament again (Reſolving to have one like themſelves) that <hi>Juncto</hi> which was formerly deſolved by <hi>Oliver, was thoſe that murdered their King, &amp; had for ſome years enſlaved their Native Countrey,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet I cannot tell whether it were their inclinations to the General, or <hi>Lambert's</hi> particular perſwaſions; which called theſe men even out of the grave of infamy to ſit again in the Houſe, and rule as Lords <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amount</hi>
               <pb n="162" facs="tcp:204891:89"/>over theſe Nations, though I have a great deal of reaſon to believe it was the latter, ſince <hi>Lambert's</hi> ambition might ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prompt him to begin with thoſe men, &amp; con over an old leſſon, exeperimentally taught him by his old Maſter <hi>Oliver,</hi> then hazard the venture of a new one.</p>
            <p>But this <hi>Juncto</hi> being thus recall'd to their ſeats in the Houſe, and the exerciſe of their former Arbitrary power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority by their <hi>Quondam</hi> ſervants of the Army, accept of the invitation; and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly met in the Parliament Houſe, whether likewiſe there aſſemble ſeverall of thoſe Members which had formerly been ſecluded &amp; debar'd ſitting in 1648. Theſe demand now an equall right with the others, either to Conſult or Vote; but as they had been formerly violently thruſt out: ſo they are now forcibly kept out by the Officers of the Army.</p>
            <p>This cauſes another as great diſtraction of their affairs. For theſe ſecluded Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, doe not only diſpute their right by Law and Reaſon (which could nothing
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:204891:89"/>prevail with ſword-men) but Sir <hi>George Booth</hi> and ſome others levy Armes now more truly in defence of Parliamentary priviledges then thoſe raiſed in 1642.</p>
            <p>This ſmall Army raiſed in <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> gave <hi>Lambert</hi> as fair an opertunity to put in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution his ambitious deſignes, as poſſibly could be; for he being ſent with the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt force of the Army againſt Sir <hi>George,</hi> eaſily overcomes him, takes him priſoner, &amp; retakes thoſe Holds which he had poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt himſelf of, and ſo returnes victorous.</p>
            <p>This fortunate ſucceſs revived his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient credit with the Army, and now he begins to practiſe the ruin of thoſe which he had ſo lately ſet up, that be might give full ſcope to his own Ambition. They found out his deſigns, but yet not being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to hinder them, are forc'd ſhortly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to ſubmit to a diſſolution.</p>
            <p>Thus was this Nation hurried into chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Government, and Anarchicall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions, by perſons who endeavoured only to promote their own ends &amp; ſelf intereſt; yet by theſe ſtrange endeavours of their
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:204891:90"/>own, they only loſt themſelves, for the people, now beginning to diſcover their juggles, do as much deteſt them; &amp; though they might for the preſent force the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to a ſubmiſſion by ſword-law; yet could no Government whatſoever, by them eſtabliſht, be firme or dureable, ſince it muſt be ſettled contrary to the <hi>Genius</hi> of the people.</p>
            <p>For even thoſe who were formerly ſuch ſtrong enemies and oppoſers of Monarchy and Kingly Government, undeceived by thoſe many deluſions which they ſee put upon the Nation (by thoſe who pretended ſo much to Religion and Liberty, and the ſettling of a Free State or Commonwealth, whilſt they intended only their own ends) are now as much affected as they were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly diſaffected with Monarchicall Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, finding that thoſe who adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to change a ſettled Government before they have determined of another in its ſtead, run into fancies and <hi>Chymera's,</hi> and vainly endeavour to build caſtles in the air; But to proceed.</p>
            <pb n="165" facs="tcp:204891:90"/>
            <p>This party being thus divided among themſelves, there were great hopes, and certainly, greater wiſhes that that power wherewith they had for ſome years paſt, arbitrarily governed the Nation by turns, might at length come to a period, which by the eye of reaſon was now in greater probability then ever, they by their inteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine deviſions running headlong to their own ruine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fleetwood, Lambert,</hi> and the reſt of the Officers of the Army, have now the ſole Authority, and having the longeſt ſword, make their wills a law; yet ſomewhat to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy the people, &amp; to make at leaſt the face of a civill government, they ſet up a new kind of a thing which they compoſed of themſelves, &amp; ſome other choice perſons, which they call a <hi>Committee of Safety,</hi> and to theſe they give full Authority over theſe Nations, without ever asking the peoples conſent</p>
            <p>This Government is far more the ſcorn and deriſion of the people, then the the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, yet notwithſtandinding their ſpirits
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:204891:91"/>are by conſtant uſe ſo ſubjected to ſlavery, that their Aſinine backs are forced to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure this as well as other more intolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble burthens, they not daring all this while to adventure the regaining of their Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, nor indeed do other then by their tongues expreſs their hate and anger.</p>
            <p>But all this while thoſe diviſions of theirs, and the peoples being weary of them, and extreamly for his Majeſties in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, it being a rule in Politicks, that the peoples hatred to an uſurper, doth alwayes produce their love to a lawfull Prince, nor had they before, 'till deluded by thoſe Tyrannizers any time to conſider the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries of their lawfull Soveraign, which now they begin to compaſſionate, &amp; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him the only perſon whom theſe men endeavour by all means poſſible to keep down, hatred to their Tyrannies, makes the people naturally deſire his reſtauration, and him whom before they thought juſtly expulſed, they think it both Juſtice and Charity to reinſtate, as much conſidering it to be their own as his intereſt, expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:204891:91"/>having taught them the difference between the Government by one gentle Prince, and many Ruſticks.</p>
            <p>Thus far did theſe mens deviſions inveſt his ſacred Majeſty with the love of his people, who in the mean time lives reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly at <hi>Bruges,</hi> expecting either what the good will of his ſubjects might do for the reſtoring him to his right, or what the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs might be of that Treaty which was then (the grand action of <hi>Europe</hi>) in agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation between thoſe two potent Monarchs <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> from whoſe joynt-forces he might expect ſo great a ſupply as might have reinſtated him in his Dominions by force, a courſe moſt of all oppoſite to his Majeſties nature, who even in private things never attempts any thing by vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence which he can obtain by intreaty.</p>
            <p>Yet great hopes had the Royaliſts both in <hi>England</hi> and aboade, that this Treaty would produce ſome good effects; yet it went on very ſlowly, &amp; after a great deal of tediouſneſs, came to a ceſſation, and from that to an interview between the two
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:204891:92"/>grand Officers of State, <hi>Don Lew is de Hare</hi> Count <hi>de Olivares,</hi> chief favourite to his Catholick Majeſty, and Cardinall <hi>Maza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine,</hi> chief Miniſter of State to the moſt Chriſtian King; theſe being met upon the Frontier, his ſacred Majeſty of great <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> was invited thither by <hi>Don Lew is de Haro.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Majeſty received this invitation at <hi>Diepe</hi> in <hi>Normandy,</hi> whither he had pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately withdrawen himſelf (as likewiſe had his Brother the Duke of <hi>York</hi> to <hi>Calice</hi>) that they might be in a readineſs to have come over into <hi>England,</hi> upon any fit opportunity, they having received many invitations from their friends here, about that time when Sir <hi>George Booth</hi> was up in <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> and all <hi>England</hi> in a manner gap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for him. But Sir <hi>George</hi> being (as I ſaid before) overcome, his Majeſties and the whole Nations hopes fail'd, and the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natick power ſtill continued <hi>Paramount.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Majeſty therefore from <hi>Diepe</hi> begins his journey towards the frontiers of <hi>Spain,</hi> which journey he intended to make pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately,
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:204891:92"/>and being firſt come to <hi>Roan,</hi> he was there nobly entertained and feaſted by Mr. <hi>Scot,</hi> an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Merchant, who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied his Majeſty to the Proteſtant Church, about three miles from the City, where with a great deal of Devotion and Attention he heard a Sermon.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Roan,</hi> his Majeſty accompanied with the Marqueſs of <hi>Ormond,</hi> the Lord <hi>Digby,</hi> Mr. <hi>Oneen</hi> took Poſt, ſteering their courſe directly for <hi>Bayonne</hi> (neer which the two great officers of ſtate were to meet) not ſtaying in any place, but endeavouring by all means poſſible to travel undiſcovered as was before reſolv'd.</p>
            <p>Being come near to the end of his Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, advice was ſent to <hi>Don Lewis de Haro</hi> of his Majeſties approach, who immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately (accompanied with a gallant Train) came forth to meet him, and being come near unto him, <hi>Don Lewis</hi> alighted from his horſe, and notwithſtanding the place where they met was very durty, kneeling down he clapt his hands about his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Knees, and with a great deal of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:204891:93"/>kiſſed them.</p>
            <p>His Majeſty was from hence conducted with becoming Ceremonies, to the place appointed for his accomodation (<hi>Don Lew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is</hi> riding all the way bareheaded by him) where he was entertained with all poſſible ſplendor and gallantry.</p>
            <p>Many overtures and propoſitions there paſſed, between his Majeſty and <hi>Don Lew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is de Haro</hi> touching what aid and aſſiſtance might be granted him by his Catholick Majeſty, for the regaining of his rights &amp; Kingdoms; his Majeſty endeavouring by all means poſſible, to promote and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the preſent Treaty between <hi>France</hi> &amp; <hi>Spain,</hi> and to bring it to a happy concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by the Marriage of the King of <hi>France</hi> to the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Infanta, it tending ſo much to his intereſt, that
'till the concluſion of it, nothing could be effected by thoſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which might any way promote his right or poſſeſſion.</p>
            <p>To all his deſires or propoſitions, the noble Count <hi>de Olivares</hi> returned pleaſing anſwers, &amp; carried himſelf with ſo much
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:204891:93" rendition="simple:additions"/>reſpect towards him, that he could not have been more ſubmiſſive to the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Majeſty of <hi>Spain</hi> his Maſter.</p>
            <p>His Majeſty having ſome time been treated here, returned back again through <hi>France,</hi> being accompanyed ſome part of his way by <hi>Don Lewis,</hi> and repaſſing the reſt privately by Poſt as he had formerly paſſed it, till he came to <hi>Charinton</hi> and <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> where his Mother was, with whom he ſtaid ſome few dayes (though he was not now Courted and carreſſed by the <hi>French</hi> Nobility as formerly) and then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to his reſidence at <hi>Bruſſels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Majeſties private departure from <hi>Bruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels,</hi> &amp; his privacy during his whole jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, made it certainly believed, that both he &amp; his Brother the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> who lay at <hi>Callis,</hi> were come over into <hi>England,</hi> &amp; that they lay hear concealed, expecting accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the event of things, either to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver or ſecure themſelves: nay ſo certain was the belief even thoſe in power had of it, (who had not ſo good intelligence as <hi>Oliver Cromwell</hi>) that many perſons were
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:204891:94"/>aprehended for them, and particularly one Mr. <hi>Colt</hi> was taken for the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> and kept in priſon for him, till ſuch time as certain news arrived in <hi>England</hi> of the Dukes return to <hi>Bruſſels.</hi> Several other perſons likewiſe ſuffered impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment forbeing ſuppos'd tobe like either his Majeſty or his Brother.</p>
            <p>His Majeſty living retired at <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> the continuances of the differences in <hi>England</hi> among thoſe who had uſurped his power, doth ſtill highly promote his intereſt. For though <hi>Lambert</hi> had routed Sir <hi>George Booth,</hi> and by it declared abſolutely againſt a Free Parliament (for which, as the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted right of the Nation, Sir <hi>George Booth</hi> and his party took up Arms) yet the people could not be content, but now once put in the way, they began violently to hanker after their long loſt Liberty.</p>
            <p>Nor could the turning out of the <hi>Rump</hi> (for ſo had the people out of diſgrace term<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the <hi>Juncto</hi> which then ſate) whom they inveterately hated, any whit now ſweeten them in their ſlavery, but they continually
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:204891:94"/>murmured out &amp; agravated their oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions one to another, &amp; though they came to no violence, yet 'tis ſuſpected it was more out of the hope they had that Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <hi>George Monck,</hi> (who was then march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with his Army out of <hi>Scotland</hi>) ſhould aſſert their Liberties, (which ſomewhat allayed the popular fury) then out of any fear or Cowardiſe.</p>
            <p>But in the mean time their expectations ſeem'd utterly to fail them, for the <hi>Rump</hi> had by their induſtry ſo inveigled moſt of the Army from <hi>Lambert,</hi> that by their help they return and take their ſeats in the Houſe and diſſolve his <hi>Committee of Safety,</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded the Souldiers of his Army to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair to their appointed Quarters, &amp; Order Generall <hi>Monck</hi> to bring up his Army to <hi>London,</hi> in all which they are punctually obeyed; <hi>Lambert's</hi> Soulders deſerting him, and Generall <hi>Monck</hi> according to their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, marching up his Army quite through <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet the Nation had ſo great hopes of the Noble General, that in all his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:204891:95"/>through <hi>England,</hi> he is courted with Addreſſes from the Gentry of every County, remonſtrating the diſtractions they long had, and were ſtill like to lye un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and intreating that he would be (as they hoped hee'd prove) the Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer and ſaver of his Countrey; that to ſettle them in ſome way of Government, a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament might be called by the Free Votes of the people, that they might no longer be Govern'd by ſuch Wolves, as only made a Prey of them, nor their Governours be ſubjected to the awe &amp; force of an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orbitant Army. To all theſe deſires he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned anſwers, promiſing ſuch things as might be for the good of the Nation.</p>
            <p>But being come to <hi>London</hi> (where he was received with a great deal of joy) he put the people almoſt quite out of hopes of him, nay rather into a fear, that in ſtead of proving their deliverer, he would be the means to enſlave them; for by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Rump,</hi> he enters the City with his whole Army, impriſons many of their <hi>Common Council,</hi> digs up their Poſts, and
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:204891:95"/>breakes down their Gates, whilſt the ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pifi'd Citizens, having now fear added to their ſlavery, durſt hardly murmur at it, but with ſighs &amp; nods bid <hi>adieu</hi> to their Liberty.</p>
            <p>Yet notwithſtanding this violence, the Noble Generall revives their hopes, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiring himſelf into the City, refuſing to be ſubject to the <hi>Juncto's</hi> command, ſhortly after he admitts thoſe Members of the Houſe of <hi>Commons</hi> which were in 1648. forceably excluded by the Army, (for hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing given their Votes that the Kings Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions at the Iſle of <hi>Wight</hi> Treaty, were ſufficient grounds for a Peace and ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:) who having taken their places in the Houſe, we had now got a ſtep towards our ancient happineſs, one of the three E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates of the Kingdom <hi>viz.</hi> the Houſe of <hi>Commons,</hi> being permitted to ſit freely, a thing not known to us in twelve precedent yeares. God of heaven of his mercy to theſe Nations, grant, that the other two may, in his due time, be admitted to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of their power and truſt, that theſe
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:204891:96"/>Nations once ſo famous under that Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, may no longer continue to be the ſcorne and deriſion of foraign Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries.</p>
            <p>And great hopes there is now that theſe Kingdomes may again return to be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, ſince diſloyalty (the firſt cauſe of their miſeries and diſtractions) begins, bleſſed be God, every day to be depreſſed, and loyalty to flouriſh, many of thoſe who for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly with a zealous fury broak their oath of Allegiance to their King, wiſhing now that they had a King to ſhew allegiance to; &amp; perceiving that al innovations of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment are not what ſome would have them ſeem to be, <hi>viz.</hi> ways to liberty &amp; freedom, but meer baits of ambitious ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded men, to hook in the people to ſlavery.</p>
            <p>But to return to his Majeſty in <hi>Flanders;</hi> of whoſe jtenary life we have already given you a particular account: it will not be impertinent to ſay ſomwhat of his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentary &amp; retired Living, that by his Aeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomy we may judge of his Monarchy, and
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:204891:96"/>of the Government of thoſe few ſubjects in his Family, of that of his three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms.</p>
            <p>His Majeſty hath ſpent moſt of his time, wherein he hath been out of his Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in <hi>Flanders</hi> under the protection of the Catholick King of <hi>Spain;</hi> nor had he ever any where elſe ſo ſettled a Court and Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation, as here, where his chief Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants are the Lord Chancellour <hi>Hide,</hi> the Marqueſs of <hi>Ormond,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Norwich,</hi> the Lord <hi>Wentworth,</hi> the Lord <hi>Digby,</hi> and many other Nobles and Gentlemen, whoſe loyalty to his ſacred Majeſty &amp; his Royall Father hath made exiles to their Country; a particular number of which he makes uſe of for his Councill, doing nothing without ſerious &amp; mature advice; and yet being of ſo ſagatious a judgement, that whatever he ſayes is ſeldome contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted by the moſt Judicious of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellours, not out of fear or flattery, but out of a reall aſſent to, and concurrence with his judgement.</p>
            <p>And indeed thoſe great opportunities
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:204891:97"/>which he hath had, by his ſo long being abroad, of diving into the great Councels of Forraign Princes and States, muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily make him a perſon of a very per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous underſtanding, endow him with all thoſe qualities which may deſervedly attain the name of Great, and render him as well an able Statiſt, as a King; he hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing during his expulſion travelled through &amp; lived in the Countries of three the moſt potent Princes in Chriſtendome, <hi>viz.</hi> the Emperour's of <hi>Germany,</hi> and the Kings of <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>France;</hi> and ſo to the Germain reſolution added the Spaniards prudence, and the Frenchmans expedition.</p>
            <p>To theſe extraordinary helps which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a Prince in Chriſtendome can boaſt of, we may yet add, thoſe more then ordinary gifts, wherewith nature hath been pleaſed to endow him, which being ſo extreamly improved, we can hardly now diſcern; but that it may be known what they were, take the character of an Honourable Lord upon his death Bed, who ſpeaking of him when about fiteen or ſixteen Years of Age,
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:204891:97"/>hath theſe words: <hi>Truly I never ſaw greater hopes of vertue in any young Perſon then in him: Great Judgement, great underſtanding, ſtrong apprehenſion, much of honour in his nature, &amp; a very perfect Engliſhman in his inclinations.</hi> So that both nature &amp; induſtry have ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to uſe their utmoſt endeavours to make him a perfect Prince, his very affliction turning in this to his benefit, and making him in knowledge and ſufferings (the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finer of knowledge) unparalleld. Some forreign Princes as well envying, as pity<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his expulſion.</p>
            <p>This perfect knowledge of his he hath indeed had but ſmall occaſion to practiſe, except a little in <hi>Scotland:</hi> where, I think, he demonſtrated himſelf a perſon ſo pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and careful in his affairs, that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond my Pen's expreſſion.</p>
            <p>His Subjects good was his only care; nor did he ever act any thing but what might tend more to theirs then his own intereſt; ſtill conſulting whether it might benefit them, not himſelf.</p>
            <p>His Letter to Col. <hi>Mackworth</hi> Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:204891:98"/>of <hi>Shrewsbury</hi> ſufficiently demonſtrates his affection to his very Enemies; he would win, not Conquer the Hearts of thoſe who though they have broke their Allegiance to him, yet he would eſteem ſtill his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects.</p>
            <p>He would not conquer with bloud, leſt he ſhould be thought a Tyrant. He endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours by fair means to attain the love of his Subjects, that (what ever his very ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies think of him) he may approve him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be a juſt Prince.</p>
            <p>And did Fortune give him power, yet would he rather attempt Curteſie then Force. He knows that whilſt he kills a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject he weakens his Kingdom. Rebels themſelves may be found uſefull; and though juſtice cannot, yet his Majeſties Clemency will admit their pardon; but if they reſiſt to the utmoſt, their bloud is on their own heads, <hi>what man is not willing to deſtroy him, who he knows would be his mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is his juſtice and his Clemency mixt together; he would not Kill, where
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:204891:98"/>he might with ſafety ſave. Nor does his unſpotted innocency raiſe fancies or fears in him. As he is guilty of nothing, ſo ther's nothing he fears. Whilſt he endeavours to be true to his ſubjects, thoſe endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours force a belief in him, that his ſubjects will be true to him.</p>
            <p>His very nature enclins him to a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion. He pitties thoſe that will not pitty themſelves; and whilſt they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiring his deſtruction, his prayers pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure their ſafety. Nor can the utmoſt of their injuries provoke him to a retaliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. He hath learned not only of God, but of the King his father, to forgive his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
            <p>Nor is it his deſire to obtain his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes that makes him willing to forgive his Enemies, but his deſire to forgive his Enemies that makes him willing to obtain his Kingdomes: he counts the poſſeſſion of his Royalties but as a tranſitory dignity, the pardon of his Enemies a Divine and laſting one.</p>
            <p>Neither is his piety leſs then his Juſtice,
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:204891:99"/>they are both in the Superlative degree, he hates wickedneſs, not becauſe the world ſhould ſee him glory (that would make him an <hi>Hipocrite</hi>) but becauſe God abhors it; 'tis Love not Fear makes him Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, he Fears God, only becauſe he Loves him.</p>
            <p>He hates not the Vicious, but abominates their Vices, his hatred extends not to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, but to things; He diſlikes not the Swearer, 'tis the Oaths he abhors, he hates not the Drunkard but his Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>Yet does his mercy extend beyond their ſins, as he is a King ſo he is a God, he is gratious to pardon, as well as juſt to pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh; nor can a remiſſion or reformation but over take his remiſſion.</p>
            <p>His conſtant ſervice of God excites o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to live by his example, he ſleeps not without invoking the bleſſing of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, nor does his Eyes open with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a returned thanks, he knows 'tis God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone which can reſtore &amp; protect him: nor can the wickedneſſe of Man preval againſt him.</p>
            <pb n="183" facs="tcp:204891:99"/>
            <p>Nor does his publick devotion ſhew him leſſe Zealous then his private, the one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrates him full of Zeal, the other void of Hypocriſie; he would have others ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as well as himſelf; he knows that ſaying concerns him, being a King, above all pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Men, <hi>Non nobis ſolis nati ſumus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Private perſons are not alone born for themſelves, much leſſe Kings, the publick concern is their duty: 'tis not enough for the Maſter of the houſe that he be Godly whilſt his family is wicked. There muſt be Precept as well as Example: and if need be, correction as well as inſtruction.</p>
            <p>This makes his Majeſty deſervedly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous; he counts it as great a fault to ſuffer a ſin in another whilſt he hath power to correct it, as to commit it himſelf, he knows that what crime ſoever a Magiſtrate ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers willingly to be committed, he brings upon his own head.</p>
            <p>He is therefore above all things careful not to father vice, leaſt he ſhould be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted vitious: he deteſts that in another which did he commit, he knows he might
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:204891:100"/>juſtly deteſt himſelfe for; and endeavours by Example to reform that in others which he knows were it in him, would ſeem odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to him.</p>
            <p>He abhors vice, as well becauſe it is ſo, as becauſe God abhors it: His nature in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clines him to vertue, and as he cannot ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit its contrary in himſelf, ſo he cannot in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure it in another.</p>
            <p>His conſtancy in Religon is no leſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous then his piety. His diſcerning judgement knows what is truth, and that truth is followed by his ſettled will; Yet he hates not the Popiſh Religion, but their Idolatry; he abhors not them, but their falſe worſhip: He loves all that knows <hi>Chriſt</hi> at all, but wiſhes that they all might know him more.</p>
            <p>His ſteadfaſtneſſe in Religion proceeds not from ſelf-intereſt; he ſticks not ſo much to be true to Proteſtants, becauſe he knows the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to be addicted to that Religion; nor becauſe he thinks it for his benefit; &amp; becauſe he imagines that it would prove very difficill to obtain his Crown &amp; leave
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:204891:100"/>it. But becauſe he knows it to be true.</p>
            <p>He knows the Prince is born for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as well as the people for the Prince. He knows their intereſts to be interwoven. He knows that without them he cannot ſtand; yet will he ſooner looſe them then relinquiſh verity.</p>
            <p>He is the perfect pattern of Piety, but more of Patience, his Afflictions have not made him repine, he knows God to be juſt: he believes that as God reſtored <hi>Job</hi> twofold, ſo will he likewiſe reſtore him his Kingdomes.</p>
            <p>Yet he thinkes it juſt in God to ſuffer them to be detained from him.</p>
            <p>He Laments more his Subjects ſlavery then his own Exile, he grievs that they have been ſo long blind, yet rejoyſes for their ſakes that they have now a Glimmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; he conſtantly prayes for the reſtoring of their ſight, not ſo much becauſe they ſhould reſtore his, as their own Rights and Priviledges.</p>
            <p>He is inwardly troubled and perplexed at the many Schiſms, Sects, &amp; Hereſies that
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:204891:101"/>are raiſed in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> he is ſory that their riſe is from ſome mens en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy towards him; he pitties, and his pitty produces his prayers for them. He is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling that though they will not obey him, yet that they may ſerve God.</p>
            <p>He was never heard to curſe his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, many times to pray for them, and deſire God to forgive even his Fathers Murtherers; his good will ſurpaſſes their cruelty: And whilſt they are conſpiring his Deſtruction, he is praying for their Salvation.</p>
            <p>He is a perfect Enemy to all Debauched<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, he is ſorry thoſe who pretend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves his friends in <hi>England</hi> are ſo great a ſcandal to him: He wiſhes that they would ſo carry themſelves, that he might adventure to own them as Friends; for he underſtands not the good will of thoſe who drink his Health for the liquors ſake, nor wiſhes for their helpe who over their Sack only ſwear they will fight for him. He is noe greater a hater of vice then a che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſher of vertuous Actions, he loves them
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:204891:101"/>in his very Enemies, &amp; often grieves when he findes occaſion to think that many of them will riſe up in judgement againſt his moſt pretended Friends,</p>
            <p>He is moſt exactly juſt in all his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands and faithfull in performance of all his promiſes Take the Character given him by the dying Marqueſs of <hi>Montroſe. For his Majeſty now living</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Never people I believe may be more happy in a King, his Commands to me were moſt juſt, in nothing that he promiſeth will he fail: He deals juſtly with all men</hi> &amp;c. So punctuall is he, that when a word is once gon out of his Mouth he will rather ſuffer by it then break it.</p>
            <p>To conclude, he is the pattern of Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Piety, the moſt Righteous and Juſteſt of Kings. The moſt knowing &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced of Princes. The Holieſt and the beſt of Men. The ſevereſt puniſher of Vice. The ſtricteſt rewarder of Virtue. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanteſt preſerver of Religion. And the tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt lover of his Subjects.</p>
            <p>This is a ſhort Character of his illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Majeſty, which I feare thoſe that know
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:204891:102"/>him will rather think to come ſhort of then reach his due praiſe, ſo ſweetly ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous is he in all his Carriages, ſo affable in his diſcourſe, ſo void of paſſion &amp; anger, that he was never yet heard or ſeen in Choller, the utmoſt extent of any paſſion that ever was diſcerned in him, being to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards one of his Meniall Servants, who juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying himſelfe in what he had done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe, his Majeſty with ſome motion told him that he was an inſolent fellow.</p>
            <p>Yet this is that Prince whoſe vertues we have given leave to Forraign Nations to admire, whilſt we our ſelves have reſted as well ignorant of his deſerts, as deſtitute of our own Liberty, whilſt either infatuated or blinded by thoſe who have Tyrannical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſurp'd Governments over us, we have been contented to ſit ſtill &amp; ſee him Expul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and exil'd from his due Rights &amp; Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alties, and our ſelves from our Freedom &amp; Priviledges.</p>
            <p>Nor hath God alone been merciful to us in endowing his ſacred Majeſty with ſuch Heroick Vertues, but he hath given us a
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:204891:102"/>ſtock of Noble Princes, who ſeem to Emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late Virtues in one another, and growe up like Royal Oaks to maintain the Honour and Glory of this Nation, but are yet and have a long time been the diſgrace of it, all the Nations in <hi>Europe</hi> laughing at the <hi>Engliſh</hi> folly, who ſlight that happineſſe which they might enjoy.</p>
            <p>As for the illuſtrious Duke of <hi>York</hi> his Fame is ſpread ſo far over the World, that my ſelfe have heard the very <hi>Turks</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend and applaud his Vallour which was ſo eſteemed among the <hi>French,</hi> that before he arrived at twenty one years of Age, he was by that King thought worthy the Command of Liu. General of his Armies, which he managed with ſuch care &amp; pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that ſeldom any affairs he took in hand, produced not its deſired ſucceſſe; &amp; ſince, his being in requital of his ſervices, complemented out of that Kingdome of <hi>France,</hi> though he hath not had ſuch emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent commands confer'd on him by the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> yet have they alwaies thought him worthy the higheſt imployment and reſpect.</p>
            <pb n="190" facs="tcp:204891:103"/>
            <p>As for the Duke of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> he is eſteemed by moſt to be fitter for a Councellour then a Souldier: His Carriage is grave, &amp; ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ſevere; of a Sagace Genious and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and very much prying into State Affairs, which have made moſt judge him the fitter for a Councill board.</p>
            <p>Theſe three Princes, are like three <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds</hi> or <hi>Pearls</hi> which we have ignorantly caſt away, &amp; not come to know the worth of them till we come to want them, Their vertues having made them reſplendent throughout all the World, and rendred them, if we juſtly conſider it, the only means whereby we can attain to happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; for what Nation can be more bleſſed then that which hath for her Prince a juſt King to Govern, a Valiant Duke to Defend, and a Wiſe Counſellour to Adviſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>May the God of Heaven then open our Eyes and let us at length ſee our Errour, and hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:204891:103"/>repent of it, by calling our Native Soveraign to the poſſeſſion of his due Rights, which the Divine Majeſty (I hope) will be Gratiouſly plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to Grant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus far the Hiſtory.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>March</hi> 1660.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:204891:104"/>
            <head>POST-SCRIPT</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen this admirable miraculous foregoing Hiſtory came firſt out, (which contayns ſo great wonders, that noe former age can parralel, or future believe,) it may well without derogation from the author, be owned by a perſon of Quality: for ſo queſtionleſſe he was, and a perſon of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and loyall confidence; that at that time, before the dawning of our day of Liberty, or the ariſing of our long ſet Sun, which by its appearing inlightens, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, and refreſhes theſe our Kingdoms, of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> &amp; <hi>Ireland, CHARLES</hi> the ſecond defender of the faith <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I ſay, much may well be attributed to his confident bouldnes, at that time to publiſh it, when to ſpeak truth, reaſon, or loyaltie, was accounted, Error, Treaſon, &amp; dangerous.</p>
            <p>And although it be not ſo full as it might
<pb facs="tcp:204891:104"/>be, either for manner or Matter, in ſetting forth the worthy &amp; deſerved Praiſe of our moſt gratious Soveraign, (whoſe perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions whoſoever ſhall undertake to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe, muſt needs fall ſhort) and of his Miraculous eſcape; but that it may well be ſaid of it, as the Queen of <hi>Sheba</hi> ſaid of the Wiſdom of <hi>Solomon &amp;c.</hi> behold the halfe was not tould of what ſhe found, (though reported by fame, which ſeldome looſes in the Progreſſe) nor of the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull ſignall mercy to his Kingdoms and Subjects thereby, as is well expreſt in the 107. pſalme and the 43. <hi>Who ſo is wiſe may may underſtand theſe things, and ſuch ſhall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the loving kindneſs of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And truly I think never people had more cauſe, chearfully &amp; thankfully to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the goodnes of God herein: and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe it by their duty and obedience. The wiſemans advice its wiſdome to take. <hi>Pro.</hi> 24. &amp; 21.22. <hi>My Sonfear God and the King, &amp; medle not with them that be ſeditious, and deſirous of change &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Have we not been (ever ſince the ſad Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice
<pb facs="tcp:204891:105"/>of his ſacred Majeſty (who God has made a Saint, and they a Martyr) of moſt pretious and bleſſed memory, who was Murthered by the pretended ſword of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtce: &amp; to ſay noe more of it, was as hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid a crime as ever the Sun beheld) oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by high Courts of Injuſtice, and other arbitrary impoſitions, more then ever was done by coular of authority, in the raigns of all the <hi>KINGS</hi> ſince the <hi>CONQVEST.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Did not the want of our King bring on us? Vſurpation, Tirrany, Enmity, Animoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, Poverty, and all Miſery? All which will be remov'd, and to our comfort (if our ſinnes and diſobedience hinders not) we ſhall aſſuredly enjoy a Settlement of Religion, Law, Liberty, Property, Peace, Penty, Honour and Safety.</p>
            <p>Has not his ſingular wiſdom diſcovered and directed a way, not only for diſcharg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe large arrears (which before dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly increaſed on us) to the Army and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, which is in a ſhort time done, but alſo for their disbanding in <hi>England;</hi> to free us thereby for the future, from thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:204891:105"/>inſupportable burthens.</p>
            <p>Read but his gratious General pardon, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore which who could juſtly ſay he was free) and ſee his unparaleld clemency: who to us <hi>Ariſeth like the Sun of Righteouſnes with healing under his wings Mal.</hi> 4.2. And if ingratitude be the worſt of crimes (as I think was never yet queſtioned) how inexcuſable then in the Eyes of all the world ſhall ſuch be, that after ſo great favour, ſhall either in thought, word, or deed, think, ſpeak, or act any thing againſt him.</p>
            <p>Read but his Declaration concerning Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall affaires; with what Religious care &amp; caution has he fram'd it: to the Satisfaction of all intereſts that pretend to Religion, Reaſon or Civility, Provided they quietly conforme to the Eſtabliſht Laws, and make not Religion (as ſome formerly did) a Match to give fire to Rebellion.</p>
            <p>Who knows not that in our unfortunate jn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terregnum, the deſign of our hardharted task<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters was to blind (if not put out) the Eyes of the three Kingdoms, by endeavouring to pilladge thoſe formerly famous Seminaries
<pb facs="tcp:204891:106"/>of Learning, and diſcourage it for the future, as if they had been of that judgement, that ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance was the Mother of devotion.</p>
            <p>All which and much more that might juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be vrged on this ſubject, muſt needs make us acknowledge, as it is in the forementioned pſalme and that often as it is there, to <hi>Praiſe the Lord for his goodnes in reſtoring him, &amp; declare the wonders that he hath done for him, and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of theſe Kingdones.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am ſure we may juſtly ſay <hi>If God had not been on our ſide, we had been deſtroyed,</hi> but to him for ever be the praiſe; <hi>The ſnare is broken and we are delivered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet there are a ſort of people in the world, and too many in this kingdome (the more is the pitty) God grant there be none in <hi>England;</hi> the Epiſtle of Saint <hi>Jude,</hi> eſpetially the 10. &amp; 16. deſcribs them: that through ignorance, miſinformation, prejudice, or advantage, are redy to ſlander the foot-ſteps of the LORDS anoynted: who live in this dark corner of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and are ignorant of the worth of that happines that is in the King, &amp; to themſelves thereby. I thought it therefore a neceſſary
<pb facs="tcp:204891:106"/>duty, having this Hiſtory by me, to get it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed here for information: being as far from endeavouring to gain applauſe thereby, as I am uncapable of attaining it by any thing from my ſelfe: only that I may manifeſt the goodnes of God, which is the duty of every Chriſtian: and my loyalty, which is the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of every Subject &amp; good Chriſtian, (though for theſe twelve years I have been a ſufferer for it.) and informe thoſe that yet know not ſo much as this manifeſts.</p>
            <p>To the Lord the only ruler of Princes, whoſe right hand and mighty arm hath done it, for ever be the praiſe: Yea let all the People praiſe thee O Lord for thy goodnes to us, in reſtoring the light of our Eyes, the breath of our Noſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trills, the Kings moſt excellent Majeſty! the reſtoring of whom unto his Throne, muſt needs be acknowledged the hand of God, and if enough to convince an <hi>Athiſt:</hi> &amp; may evince to the World the validity of vnited and devout prayers, ſuch as are injoyned with good autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity by the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and are the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Marrow of the Scriptures: and where are not Scripture, are vncontroulably agreeing:
<pb facs="tcp:204891:107"/>compoſed by thoſe that lay'd down their lives to maintaine; and bequeathed as the beſt Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacy to their Wives and Children. And in a word, are thoſe prayers for which our bleſſed Saviour will not refuſe to be an interceſſour: and which have ſo miraculouſly reſtored the defendor of our Faith to his Throne: which noe rational man alive but may well conclude, being (as I am confident they were) put up to the Throne of Grace, with pure &amp; upright hearts, by the dutifull and obedient Sons of the Church.</p>
            <p>And therefore let all (but eſpetially ſuch,) never forget to return due praiſe for his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyes to us and to our King, and as it is there di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, yeild praiſe and thanksgiving for our deliverance from thoſe great and apparent dangers, where with we were incompaſſed: and to acknowledge it his goodnes that we were not delivered over as a prey unto them: beſeeching ſtill his goodnes and mercy to us, that all the World may know, that he is our Saviour and mighty Redeemer. And that all thoſe that do confeſs his holy Name, may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in the truth of his holy word, and live in
<pb facs="tcp:204891:107"/>vnity and Godly love, &amp; that under our Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full King and governour we may be Godly and quietly governed.</p>
            <p>And for our moſt gratious Soveraign alſo let us pray, <hi>That he knowing whoſe Miniſter he is, may aboue all things ſeeke his honour &amp; glory: that ſo we his Subjects duly conſidering whoſe authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty he hath, may honour and humbly obey him accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Gods bleſſed word and Ordinance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as it is directed by that Divine, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox, ancient and beſt lyturgie, of the Church of <hi>England, To keep and strengthen in the true worſhip of thee, in righteouſnes and holynes of life, thy Servant CHARLES. our moſt gratious KING and Governour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That it may pleaſe thee O Lord to rule his heart in thy faith feare and love, that he may ever more have affiance in thee, and ever ſeek thy honour and glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That he may alway incline to thy will and walk in thy way, Endue him plentyouſly with heavenly gifts, grant him in health &amp; wealth long to live: ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then him that he may Vanquiſh and over come all his Enemies; and finally after this life: he may attain everlaſting Ioy and felicity, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:204891:108"/>
            <p>As for thoſe who ſo barbarouſly acted in that horrid crime the Murder of his Sacred Majeſty of bleſſed memory: they have had (at leaſt ſome of them) the reward of Regicides. <hi>So let his Enemies periſh O Lord, and all that riſe up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him: But on his own head let his Crown flouriſh:</hi> Let his dayes be many and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, and let all, (but eſpetially thoſe that are truly loyal,) finde the Comfort of it.</p>
            <p>The unexpreſſable joy of all his Subjects, felt and declared at his return requires a Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume, and at this place cannot be inform'd: it being indeed beyond expreſſion, God inclin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the hearts of all his people, as ſome times all the Subiects of King <hi>David,</hi> the people of <hi>Juda,</hi> to bring home their King: 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.14. Take one for all, a Copie of Verſes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented with his own hand at his return to his Government: By that moſt Honorable and Heroick perſon, and renowned Champion of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> intereſt in <hi>Jreland</hi> (which Maugre all oppoſition, will eternize his fame to all
<pb facs="tcp:204891:108"/>poſterity) The Lord Preſident of <hi>Munſter,</hi> all that know him, know his excellency that way: its enough to ſay they are his; and they follow as well worthy to conclude the Hiſtory of his moſt excellent Majeſty, whom God preſerue.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H: F:</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Cork</hi>
                  <date>22. <hi>No:</hi> 1660.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:204891:109"/>
            <head>TO THE KING UPON HIS MAJESTIES <hi>Happy Return.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the Great World at firſt in <hi>Cbaos lay;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then darknes yeilded to triumpha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t day;</l>
               <l>And all that wild and undigeſted <hi>Maſs</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Did into Forme, and to perfection paſs:</l>
               <l>So, in our leſſer World, Confuſions were</l>
               <l>Many, and vaſt, as now our Bleſſings are.</l>
               <l>Our paſt, and preſent State fully expreſs</l>
               <l>All we could bear, and all we would poſſeſs.</l>
               <l>Wonder not that your forces could not bring</l>
               <l>You to Your Crowns, nor us unto our King:</l>
               <l>Fate made therein this high deſign appear,</l>
               <l>Your Sword ſhall rule abroad, Your Virtues here.</l>
               <l>The leſſer Conqueſt was to you deny'd</l>
               <l>That by the greater it might be ſuppy'd.</l>
               <l>Nor think it ſtrang that ſom ſo long have ſtrove</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:204891:109"/>
               <l>With that which they did moſt admire &amp; love;</l>
               <l>Since all againſt their diſſolution pray,</l>
               <l>Although to Heav'n there is no other way.</l>
               <l>Like to <hi>Betheſdas</hi> Pool, our Common-wealth</l>
               <l>Till it was troubled, could not give us health:</l>
               <l>You as the Angel, did our Waters ſtir,</l>
               <l>And from that motion we derive our Cure.</l>
               <l>The higheſt Bleſſing God to You does yield,</l>
               <l>He, His Anoynted, as His Church does build:</l>
               <l>Nothing of noiſe did to perfection bring</l>
               <l>The greateſt Temple, and the greateſt King.</l>
               <l>Alike he builded both, that all mght ſee,</l>
               <l>Your Kingdom, like his Church, ſhall endleſs be.</l>
               <l>As when Great Nature's Fabrick was begun,</l>
               <l>Expanded Light made day, and not the Sun;</l>
               <l>But Light diffus'd was to perfection grown,</l>
               <l>When from one Planet, it contracted ſhone:</l>
               <l>So when our Government was form'd to laſt</l>
               <l>But till the race of a few dayes was paſt,</l>
               <l>With Ruling Gifts GOD many did endue,</l>
               <l>But, now 'tis fix'd, all thoſe are plac'd in you.</l>
               <l>Your Baniſhment, which your Foes did deſigne</l>
               <l>To cloud your virtues, made them brighter ſhine.</l>
               <l>Thus Perſecution did but more diſpence</l>
               <l>Throughout the World the Goſpells influence.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:204891:110"/>
               <l>Princes, who ſaw Your Sufferings, did eſteem</l>
               <l>'Twas greater to ſubdue thoſe griefs then them.</l>
               <l>And in that conqueſt found how they ſhould fare,</l>
               <l>If they provok'd your Juſtice to a War.</l>
               <l>By Your Return, and by Your Foes purſuit,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Europe</hi> Your Bloſſomes had, but we your Fruit.</l>
               <l>Our Senate does not for Conditions ſue;</l>
               <l>We know we have our <hi>All,</hi> in having You:</l>
               <l>Your Mercy with our Crimes does nobly ſtrive;</l>
               <l>And, e're we aske forgivneſs you forgive.</l>
               <l>Your Subjects thus doubly you now ſubdue,</l>
               <l>Both in the Manner, and the Action too.</l>
               <l>Your great Reception in our neighb'ring State,</l>
               <l>Proves that on you depends their Countries fate:</l>
               <l>Your dreadful Fleet does on their Coaſt appear,</l>
               <l>Yet to their Joy, they yeild up all their Fear;</l>
               <l>For knowing you, they know Heav'n has reſign'd</l>
               <l>A Power unbounded to a bounded Mind.</l>
               <l>Triumphant Navy! Formerly your Fraight</l>
               <l>Conſiſting but of Lawrel, or of Plate;</l>
               <l>But to your happy Country now you bring</l>
               <l>More then both Indies in our Matchleſs KING.</l>
               <l>Twice has the World been truſted in a Barque;</l>
               <l>The New, the <hi>Charles</hi> contain'd, the Old, the Ark,</l>
               <l>This bore but thoſe who did the World re-build,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:204891:110"/>
               <l>But that bore you, to whom that world muſt yeild.</l>
               <l>The ſpacious ſea, which does the Earth embrace,</l>
               <l>Ne're held ſo many Princes in one place;</l>
               <l>Princes whoſe Father ſtill the Trident bore,</l>
               <l>As ſhall their Sons, till time ſhall be no more.</l>
               <l>Now whilſt the Sea, your greateſt ſubject, moves</l>
               <l>Slowly, as loath to part with what he loves;</l>
               <l>And whilſt your Sails the calmed Air ſubdue;</l>
               <l>(For wch he chides the winds, &amp; thanks them too)</l>
               <l>I might preſent you with a Proſpect here,</l>
               <l>Of that vaſt Empire to which now you Steere.</l>
               <l>But on that Theam my Numbers cannot ſtay;</l>
               <l>Copies to their Originals give way,</l>
               <l>For now your Fleet ſees land, which many a peal</l>
               <l>Of thund'ring Cannon to the Shore does tell:</l>
               <l>And now your raviſh'd Subjects ſee your Fleet,</l>
               <l>Wch they with ſhouts, louder then Cannon greet;</l>
               <l>Two Suns at once our ſights now etertain;</l>
               <l>One ſhines from Heav'n the other from the Main.</l>
               <l>All Loyal Eyes are fixed on the Eaſt,</l>
               <l>For you more welcome then that daily Gueſt;</l>
               <l>While on the ſhore your longing Subjects ſtand,</l>
               <l>Subjects, as numberleſs as is the Sand;</l>
               <l>Subjects ſufficient, if but led by You,</l>
               <l>All Countries you have liv'd in, to ſubdue.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:204891:111"/>
               <l>In Raptures now we our great Gen'ral ſee,</l>
               <l>Move faſter to meet you then Victorie:</l>
               <l>He at your Feet himſelf does proſtrate now,</l>
               <l>To whom vaſt Fleets and Armies us'd to bow;</l>
               <l>And greater Satisfaction does expreſs</l>
               <l>In This Submiſſion, then in That Succeſs.</l>
               <l>Your Royal Armes inwreath him, wch he more</l>
               <l>Does prize, then al thoſe lawrel wreaths he wore.</l>
               <l>Now all for his Victorious Troops make room,</l>
               <l>Which never but by Joy. were overcome:</l>
               <l>Loud ſhouts to heav'n for your Return they ſend,</l>
               <l>Whilſt low as earth their dreaded Enſigns bend;</l>
               <l>He leads them ſtill to what exalts their Name;</l>
               <l>Now to their Duty, as before to Fame.</l>
               <l>Their Miſ-led Courage, in a fatal Time,</l>
               <l>Had been too long their Glory and their Crime.</l>
               <l>Now they are truly Great, now truly live,</l>
               <l>Since this you Praiſe, and that you do forgive.</l>
               <l>Thoſe, who ſo long could keep you from your due</l>
               <l>What can reſiſt, now they are led by you?</l>
               <l>Your Great Example will their Model prove;</l>
               <l>Perſwading ſoon, and willingly, as love.</l>
               <l>Such Fleets, &amp; Armies, &amp; our <hi>Charles</hi> their head,</l>
               <l>Are things which all the Univerſe may dread.</l>
               <l>And now you move, and now in all the Waies,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:204891:111"/>
               <l>Thick clouds of Subjects, clouds of duſt do raiſe;</l>
               <l>Through which the worlds chief city now you ſee,</l>
               <l>Great in Extent, greater in Loyalty;</l>
               <l>Their Cannon ſpeak, their Streets the Souldiers line,</l>
               <l>And brighteſt beauties fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their windows ſhine:</l>
               <l>Your Subjects Earthly <hi>Jove</hi> you now are grown;</l>
               <l>Thunder &amp; light'ning guard you to your Throne.</l>
               <l>Thus you triumph, whilſt at your Palace Gates</l>
               <l>The higheſt earthly Senate for you waits:</l>
               <l>One Roof contains thoſe which our laws do make,</l>
               <l>And him from who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the world their laws muſt take:</l>
               <l>Their knees doe homage, whilſt their Tongues confeſs,</l>
               <l>They in their duty find their happneſs,</l>
               <l>And Fame aloud, through ev'ry Region, ſings,</l>
               <l>They are the beſt of Subjects you of Kings.</l>
               <l>The Royal throne ſo fully you Adorn,</l>
               <l>That now all praiſe what ſome before did ſcorn:</l>
               <l>A throne, which now the envious do confeſs,</l>
               <l>Our Safety urg'd your Merit to Poſſeſs.</l>
               <l>Where <hi>Caeſar</hi> could no further Glory win,</l>
               <l>There is the <hi>Scene,</hi> where yours does but begin;</l>
               <l>By which indulgent Fate would have it known,</l>
               <l>Though his Succeſs had end, Yours ſhould have none?</l>
               <l>Or elſe that nothing worthy was of you,</l>
               <l>But what Great <hi>Julius</hi> wanted Pow'r to do.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:204891:112"/>
               <l>Our fierce diviſions made our Courage known,</l>
               <l>But more your wiſdom ſhins, that makes us one;</l>
               <l>Which has ſo fram'd your Empire to endure,</l>
               <l>We need but prudent Foes to be ſecure.</l>
               <l>You might poſſeſs by Armies, and by Fleets,</l>
               <l>All where the Sun doth riſe, or where he ſets;</l>
               <l>But you a nobler Conqueſt have deſign'd,</l>
               <l>The placing Limits to your Greater Mind:</l>
               <l>And may thoſe higheſt titles never ceaſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A King of Greateſt Pow'r, and Greateſt Peace.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of ſufferings paſt let us no more Complain,</l>
               <l>Since you by them with greater Glory Raign;</l>
               <l>Till that we ſaw; your Subjects could not gueſs,</l>
               <l>Heav'n had for them a Bleſſing above Peace.</l>
               <l>Nor can we tell which moſt in you to own,</l>
               <l>Either your Virtues or Extraction;</l>
               <l>Though never any was ſo Great and Good;</l>
               <l>It ſprings from Martyrs, as from Royall Bloud:</l>
               <l>But your own Glories do ſo brightly ſhine,</l>
               <l>You need not borrow Luſter from your Line.</l>
               <l>Yet we muſt ſay, ſince juſtly but your due,</l>
               <l>Though you our glories raiſe, they raiſenot you:</l>
               <l>Like to the Royal Bird that climbs the Skies,</l>
               <l>You leſſer ſeem ſtill as you higher riſe.</l>
               <l>Your ſelf you limit to a triple Throne,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:204891:112"/>
               <l>And all mens Wonder are, except your own.</l>
               <l>Now Sacred Peace &amp; Juſtice ceaſe to mourn,</l>
               <l>And both in you again to us return.</l>
               <l>Religion now ſhall flouriſh with your Crown,</l>
               <l>And the fierce ſword yeild to the peaceful gown.</l>
               <l>The Muſes too ſo highly You eſteem,</l>
               <l>That you are both their Influence &amp; their Theam</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
